<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dialogue between Philiater and Momus, concerning a late scandalous pamphlet called the conclave of physicians</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 237 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 116 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35887</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9162</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11807126</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11807126</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49471</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35887)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49471)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 528:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dialogue between Philiater and Momus, concerning a late scandalous pamphlet called the conclave of physicians</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 226 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Momus is Gideon Harvey. Cf. INU/Wing STC files.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Harvey, Gideon, 1640?-1700? --  Conclave of physicians.</term>
               <term>Philiater.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:49471:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMATUR.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Rob. Midgley.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>March <hi>22. 1685/6.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49471:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN <hi>Philiater</hi> and <hi>Momus,</hi> Concerning a late Scandalous PAMPHLET CALLED <hi>The Conclave of Phyſicians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Whip for the Aſs, and a Rod for the Fool's Back.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Walter Kettilby</hi> at the <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, 1686.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49471:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:49471:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:49471:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>modern book plate</figDesc>
                  <head>Academioe Gantabrigienſis Liber</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49471:3"/>
            <head>A DIALOGUE BETWEEN <hi>Philiater</hi> and <hi>Momus,</hi> Concerning a late ſcandalous Pamphlet called <hi>The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave of Phyſicians.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1-51" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Philiater.</speaker>
                  <p>THIS many a day I have had a Wambling De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to chatt with you, <hi>Momus.</hi> And you ought to allow your ſelf a Play-day ſometimes, and be as merry as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49471:4"/>a Cricket: for to be always ſowre and upon the fret, muſt needs make your life wonderfully ſad and diſmal.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
                  <p>You are much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, <hi>Philiater,</hi> and are but little acquainted with my conſtituent Principles. I was born as ſharp as Vinegar, and ſowre as Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juice; and do hope to become as <hi>piquant</hi> and corroſive as <hi>Aqua fortis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay then indeed I was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregiouſly miſtaken. You are, it ſeems, a particular Jumble of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and are <hi>neither Fiſh, nor Fleſh, nor good Red Herring.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſtill, Does not this croſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grain'd Temper of yours make you very uneaſie and unquiet within your ſelf? A continual ſtate of Hoſtility with your Neighbours, and that without intermiſſion or any the leaſt truce, and the never giving your Thoughts reſpite, muſt certainly tire you out in time, and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49471:4"/>I fear impair your Health. But eſpecially a <hi>Civil War</hi> I do look upon to be the moſt deſtructive and inhumane, the moſt dreadful and deteſted of all others. And men had much better to ſuffer quietly abundance of Incovenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies (which the World ever pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides of ſome kind or other to all conditions) than to hazard the moſt deplorable Extremities and Miſeries, into which <hi>Civil War</hi> does conſtantly bring them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas! You are as much out in your Politicks, as in your Phyſick. Neither the Happineſs of my mind does depend upon do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick Peace, nor the Health of my Body upon being cocker'd with March-panes, and Sugar-plums; I have no ſweet Tooth to pleaſe. You cannot but have heard that in ſome Countries they do feed upon <hi>Poiſons,</hi> and they are ſaid to turn into good Nouriſhment: Nay there are <hi>Cannibals</hi> in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49471:5"/>World who can feed upon one another; and mans Fleſh is never the worſe meat, becauſe it may diſagree with your ſqueamiſh Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach. I would have you to know that Jarrs and Contentions, Revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Calumnies, are the only Muſick that tickles my Ears, and I do as naturally delight in Miſchief and in Civil Animoſities and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels, as Soldiers of Fortune do in Declarations of War between one Kingdom and another.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>If that be your Temper, <hi>Momus,</hi> pray what think you then of the <hi>Author</hi> of a late Pamphlet, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The Conclave of Phyſicians,</hi> which is a piece ſo foul and ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous, and full of groſs Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Faculty he is of, that all perſons unconcerned, who have any ſhare of Goodneſs or Manners, do bluſh at the reading it. But the worſe it is, it ſeems, the better you like it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, you have named
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49471:5"/>the Man of all men that I do the moſt admire. I have inſpired this <hi>Author</hi> with the fulneſs of my <hi>Dae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacal Spirit.</hi> Nay, I have ſo far <hi>poſſeſs'd</hi> him, and he me, that we two are grown to be all one. Never was there ſuch a Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip between two Brothers grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the ſame Trunk, and making together one <hi>Compleat Monſter:</hi> never was there known ſuch a <hi>Diſcordia concors,</hi> as between <hi>Momus</hi> and that <hi>Author.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I could name other ſcurrilous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phleteers, who have done their beſt to inflame mankind, to miſrepre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and ſpeak evil of Dignities and Societies, and on whom I have poured ſome ſmall portion of my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Spirit: but this <hi>Author</hi> is my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, my prime Miniſter, my dear Darling, and choiceſt Inſtrument of Malediction, inſomuch that whatſoever he ſays I aſſent unto it readily, and having my ſelf guided his Pen in the Treatiſe you ſpeak
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49471:6"/>of, I am bound to own it as writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by my ſelf; and he will not, or ought not to take it amiſs, if I take upon the <hi>His</hi> Defence in my own name, againſt your ſilly Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreed then, <hi>Momus,</hi> let us debate that matter as it deſerves. For as to the Numerical <hi>Author him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> I muſt needs ſay, I never ſaw his <hi>Face,</hi> nor ever entertained one word of Diſcourſe with him, nor ever had to do with him in any thing whatſoever, either great or ſmall, good or bad. So that I fear you will ſhew your ſelf much more paſſionate and prejudiced for him, than I can well be thought to be againſt one I know only by his Writings and by Hear-ſay. Indeed I have as great a Zeal for <hi>Truth,</hi> and for the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> as you can have for <hi>Calumny,</hi> and for <hi>Publick Confuſion.</hi> If I had not, I ſhould be more prudent and careful of my Peace and Quiet,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49471:6"/>than to ingage thus with one, from whom nothing can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected but throwing of Dirt and Filth, and a continual ſpawn of Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauldry. However I ſhall ſpare <hi>perſonal</hi> Reflections for the preſent, more than the Book obliges me to; I ſhall not rake up divers paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his Life, nor examine his Morals, as he does very malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly thoſe of the <hi>Conclaviſts,</hi> but <hi>reſerve</hi> Matters of that kind, or lay them aſide according as he mends his Manners, having never received a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular or perſonal provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation from him. And indeed it is exceedingly diſingenuous and unworthy a Liberal Education; beſides that I could never wiſh any Perſonal III to another man, becauſe he differs from me in judgment. It is in order to his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment</hi> that this <hi>Rod</hi> is deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and a little to prevent, if not cure his <hi>Itch,</hi> or rather <hi>Leproſie</hi> of <hi>Scribling.</hi> But, <hi>Momus,</hi> ſeeing you
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49471:7"/>will perſonate this <hi>Author,</hi> tell me what moved you to write this Pamphlet, and therein ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly to traduce the Faculty you were bred to?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>You are not to expect Reaſons for every thing I ſay or do. Ask the reaſon why Fire burns, why Storms and Tempeſts do roar and make a noiſe, why the <hi>Negro</hi> is black, why that which is heavy ſinks downwards, why that which is light flies upwards, and why light inconſiderate Heads do fly at, and revile their Superiours. It is <hi>their Nature</hi> to do ſo, and it is mine to do as I do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>But certainly you muſt have had ſome Reaſon more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for ſuch keen and deadly Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſities as you expreſs towards Phyſicians. The Tigre and Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and other Wild Beaſts have a hungry Stomach to plead for them, when they kill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, and ſeize upon their prey;
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49471:7"/>but I ſuppoſe you will not own that it is for Bread and neceſſary Suſtenance, that you make this lamentable havock of mens Good Names, and expoſe ſo many Grave and Learned men in <hi>Fools-coats,</hi> and <hi>Antick Shapes,</hi> to be baited and hooted at by the <hi>Mobile.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I have Reaſon enough, and many good Reaſons, why I have thus taken in hand my Pen of Defiance, dipt it in Gall, and writ the moſt bitter things I could in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. If the Laws did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain me, there is nothing ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid or dreadful, that I ſhould fear to commit againſt them all, nay, againſt all <hi>Aſſociated Phyſicians</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth: And after I had glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my ſelf in their deſtruction, and ſatiated my Revenge with an intire extinction of that Faculty, I would be content to die in ſo good a Cauſe, and then I ſhould, like a true <hi>Stoick,</hi> laugh even in <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laris</hi> his Bull.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49471:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Your paſſion, <hi>Momus,</hi> is raiſed too high; your Choler is all a fire. The Phyſician, if conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, would adviſe to take away a good quantity of Blood; for doubtleſs you have the higheſt Inflammation of it that ever was known. This is not like a common Heart-burning: Unleſs it be your Temper, as they ſay of the <hi>Salaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> to live in the Fire, you would certainly conſume your ſelf with ſo intenſe a degree of Heat. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed you muſt cool a little, or elſe there can be no diſcourſing with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>For once, <hi>Philiater,</hi> I'll try to conquer my ſelf in ſome meaſure. In a violent Storm, I confeſs, it is prudent to take down the Sails, leſt the Veſſel be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſett: The Rudder, I know, can be of no uſe in a Hurricane; Therefore let the Winds ceaſe their Fury; the Sea grow calm again as ſoon as you will, and you ſhall
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49471:8"/>find me guide my Diſcourſe like an experienced and skilful Pilot. And without any further <hi>Simile's</hi> of Fire or Water, or any thing elſe, I will eaſily ſatisfie any intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Judge, why I writ the ſaid Book you are ſo much offended at.</p>
                  <p>Know then, that when I came to this Town to practiſe, I neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected the entring my ſelf into the <hi>College,</hi> as you call it. I expected at firſt to be courted and ſought to by them, as knowing my own Worth, and the <hi>Excellency of my Education</hi> above that of any the beſt of the Members of this ſame <hi>College;</hi> and therefore it would have been an Honour to them, and a great condeſcenſion in me, to have been admitted into the beſt Capacity among them. By degrees, as I grew into Fame and Renown, and ſo was called to the aſſiſtance of the better Sort (who will not be perſwaded to die without
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49471:9"/>Conſulting more than one Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, let his Name be never ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, or his Skill never ſo great) there was a neceſſity of my meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeveral of them one time or other, and I being a Stranger to them, they preſumed to tax me e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and anon <hi>whether I were of the College;</hi> now I being forced to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer ſtill in the Negative, they would often inſinuate this Foolery into my Patients ſick Head ſo far that I ſoon loſt by this means the ſqueezing many a wealthy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient, and inſtead of becoming ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired for my profound abilities, I was ſcoff'd at, and rejected, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, forſooth, <hi>not of the College.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>And why would you not ſubmit to the <hi>College</hi>'s Examination, which is very candid and gentile, I am ſure; by the undergoing of which, you might eaſily have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voided that exception, and been <hi>Hail fellow well met,</hi> with thoſe naughty Inquirers?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49471:9"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſcorn to be examined by ſuch as they, or by any Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian living.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I know no reaſon, why you ſhould conceit your ſelf a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter man than every body elſe, who took your Degree abroad, and who was dubb'd a <hi>Doctor</hi> at <hi>ſeventeen</hi> Years of Age: A time of Age, or rather of Youth, beyond which the Boyes do commonly ſtay two or three Years at our great Schools, ſuch as <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> and <hi>Winchester,</hi> before they ſet footing to the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</hi> And if you had been kept longer at School, when you were pertly <hi>Commencing Doctor,</hi> you might probably have learnt to be leſs malapert, than thus to prefer your Dearly Beloved Self before all the Learned Doctors of our two Famous <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> who are taught better things, and who in order to their Degrees are fain to ſtay twelve or fourteen Years at leaſt, before they are ſuffered to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49471:10"/>take it, and by that means they do become much riper in Years and in Underſtanding, than you, who,<note place="margin">Caſus Med. Ch. p. <hi>142.</hi>
                     </note> as your ſelf tells us, <hi>In making the</hi> Petit Tour <hi>of</hi> France, <hi>did in your way take your Degrees in Phyſick, both of Batchelor and Doctor.</hi> It ſeems then you alighted from your Horſe, I hear at <hi>Leyden</hi> (to whoſe Honour be it ſpoken,) walk'd to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick-Schools, and <hi>took</hi> thoſe <hi>Degrees,</hi> one with one hand, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with t'other. For it is plain by your deſcription, your firſt and chief buſineſs was to make the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit Tour;</hi> your leſſer and ſecondary Affair was to take along with you thoſe <hi>Degrees,</hi> which indeed had much better have been left behind, than to have cauſed all this Strife and Animoſity about their Worth and Precedence. But how you came to find <hi>Leyden,</hi> a Town in <hi>Holland,</hi> to lie in <hi>your way,</hi> as you were making the <hi>Petit Tour</hi> of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49471:10"/>
                     <hi>France,</hi> is a Myſtery that I cannot comprehend. For all Travellers that ever I met with do aſſure me that they did uſe to frolick it down the River <hi>Loire,</hi> when they did <hi>make</hi> this famous <hi>Tour.</hi> But you have a ſingular art to find <hi>London</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Paris</hi> in <hi>Venice;</hi> you can find nothing but Ignorance in the Learned, and Learning to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflow in Changelings and I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deots; you can make a Mountain of a Molehill, turn Light into Darkneſs, and by ſome wonderful skill in Magick can confound the Order of Nature. Again, thoſe your Youthful, Foreign, and <hi>light-come light-go Degrees,</hi> did coſt much leſs Pains, Expence, or Time, than our Grave and Manly <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity-Degrees</hi> uſe to do. Wherefore I am amazed why you ſhould thus overvalue thoſe your foreign De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which our Laws do allow no Priviledges to, but rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain under a due ſubjection,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49471:11"/>and at the ſame time you ſhould thus undervalue the ſtaple and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Degrees of <hi>Oxford</hi> and <hi>Cambridge,</hi> which our Laws do highly and deſervedly favour. When you were matriculated at <hi>Oxford,</hi> you might remember that you took an Oath, which becauſe a Cuſtomary thing, I fear, you have quite forgotten. By that <hi>Oath</hi> you ſolemnly ſwore to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, as much as in you ſhould lie, the Honour and Good of that Univerſity. Beſides, where-ever you took your Degrees in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king your <hi>Petit Tour,</hi> you could not but take <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his Oath. You did then ſwear, <hi>Per Deum Omnipotentem, quòd ſanctè Vitam &amp; Artem tuam conſervave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">By Almighty God, that you would live, and exerciſe the Art of Phyſick, like a Good man.</q> You did then likewiſe ſwear, <hi>Quod quae inter curandum videris aut audieris, imò etiam ad medicandum non adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitus,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49471:11"/>in communi hominum vita cognoveris, ea ſiquidem efferre non contulerit, tacebis: &amp; tanquam ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cana apud te continebis. Hoc igitur jusjurandum tibi integrè ſervanti, &amp; non confundenti, contingat &amp; vitâ &amp; arte feliciter frui, &amp; apud omnes ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines in perpetuum gloriam tuam ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrari. Transgredienti autem, &amp; pejeranti, his contraria eveniant.</hi> 
                     <q rend="margQuotes">That what things you ſhould ſee or hear in your Practice of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, nay even where you are not called upon as a Phyſician, what you ſhall happen to know in the common converſation of men, if it be not convenient to divulge them abroad, you ſhall not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulge them, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, as judging ſuch things fit never to be once mentioned. Therefore according as you keep this Oath inviolably, and make no breach of it, you beſeech God to grant, that you may enjoy a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable Life, and have a ſucceſsful
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49471:12"/>Practice, and that you may be held in eſteem among men as long as you live, and be famous to fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages. But that if you vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olate, and go contrary to this Oath, you wiſh all evil on the contrary to your ſelf.</q> Thus I have given you ſome part of your Oath in Latine, becauſe you took it in Latine not in Greek. And I have rendred the words into as plain and proper Engliſh as the true Senſe of the Original would bear. Now, <hi>Momus,</hi> tell me ſoberly, have you no Remorſe upon your Mind, no Stings of a guilty knawing Conſcience, for that you have ſo publickly acted contrary to the Tenour of this Oath, for the writing ſuch wicked Invectives againſt the Faculty of Phyſick, and for your thus <hi>divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging</hi> not only <hi>things fit to be conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but <hi>malitiouſly expoſing</hi> them in the worſt and blacker colours in which your Invention could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive to draw them?</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49471:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art too weak to dive into my Politicks, or to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the ſolidity and firmneſs of my Temper. My heart is paſt relenting, paſt admitting poor <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cavi's,</hi> it is not ſophiſticated with Gumms and <hi>Lachrymae,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A Stone u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick tried that way.</note> but is hard as <hi>Stone,</hi> and impenetrable to the teſt and pricks of a red-hot Needle. Doſt thou think Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or doelful Stories will now mollifie it? The tender Virgin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed has much adoe to get over the firſt great Fault, and when ſhe has at laſt yielded after a long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, the poor creature is full of confuſion and terror. But when once ſhe is arrived to the audacity and courage of a Common Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Strumpet, ſhe is then paſt ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and repentance, and little leſs than an abſolute Miracle can reclaim her into ſome degrees of her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer natural Modeſty. And ſo the ſhame-ſac'd Youth, who has been
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49471:13"/>bred in a virtuous Country Family, when he comes firſt to Town, and enters into one of our <hi>Academies</hi> for Education, he cannot but keep good hours, and is inticed or dragg'd to a Brothel Houſe, like a Bear to the Stake; but after a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle initiation into the Myſteries of Debauchery, all his diſcourſe ſhall be flouriſhed with Dam'mees, he brings them out with a good grace; he proclaims aloud in the Play-houſe how many Claps he has got alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, nay, he ſhall make himſelf, if poſſible, ten times filthier than he really is, and glory moſt in that which formerly he would have bluſh'd to think of.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>But yet methinks the Laws of our Countrey, which have long impowered and eſtabliſhed the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege of Phyſicians,</hi> ſhould be ſome Motive to perſwade you, that it is better and more prudent to enter into the Union of that Learned Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, than to continue thus <hi>without<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doors,</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49471:13"/>indiſtinguiſhable in the wretched and contemptible Herd of Quacks, Mountebanks, Wiſe-Women, Aſtrologers, and other ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant or impudent Impoſtors.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I have been divers years at abſolute Defiance with them and their Laws; I have provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, nay worried them with unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Indignities and Defamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: in a word, I have never fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to encounter the moſt powerful and celebrated of them all; and to this day I have ſtood and kept my ground, no one of them daring to enter the liſts, to ingage publickly with me. And do you now think I have any reaſon to be timorous, or to ſtartle at their <hi>idle Laws?</hi> No, they know their own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and are conſcious to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what a folly they ſhould commit in contending with me at <hi>points of Law.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I know not what cunning you may have to evade the force
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49471:14"/>of their Laws. but I have heard it confidently aſſerted, that never any Empirick yet, whom the College has thought fit to proſecute, could make his Defence ſo good againſt their Power, but that at laſt he was forced to ſhoot the pit and run for't, or elſe was reduced to very great Extremities.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope you will not range me among thoſe little Empiricks, whom I ſcorn as much as the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clavists</hi> themſelves. Read the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of my <hi>Education</hi> in my <hi>Caſus Medico-Chirurgicus,</hi> read it throughly, and with attention, and you will find me to be <hi>ſome-body;</hi> and not a contemptible, creeping Empirick. I defie them again and again, I laugh and grin at them all in a lump. They deal with me at Law!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>But really, bold Sir, it is very unfitting that ſo many ſwarms of Empiricks, and illegal Practiſers, as do now-a-days peſter this great
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49471:14"/>City, ſhould be ſuffered, as they do, to murder and deſtroy the King's Subjects, and the <hi>College</hi> not call them to account for it; as they did in times paſt. The whole <hi>Nobility,</hi> and the flower of the <hi>Engliſh Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> do ſpend ſome part of their time in this <hi>Metropolis;</hi> their Wives and Children are many of them here trained up and educated, and every body can't diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Ninny and a man of Sence, between an Empirick and a true Phyſician.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>For my part, I ſee no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between the <hi>Learned</hi> and the <hi>Illiterate Empirick.</hi> Put them in two Scales, and you will find the one weigh as much too heavy, as the other does too light. The one does often do as much good at a venture, as the other does miſchief deliberately, and through ill Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceive then you are wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer, in your own opinion at leaſt,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49471:15"/>than our Noble <hi>Kings,</hi> and moſt Wiſe <hi>Parliaments.</hi> For they ſaw matters of this kind quite otherwiſe than you do. The Preamble to the 3 of <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>chap.</hi> 11. runs thus: <hi>Foraſmuch as the Science and Cunning of Phyſick and Surgery (to the perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge whereof be requiſite both great Learning and ripe Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) is daily within this Realm exerciſed by a great multitude of ignorant perſons, of whom the greater part have no manner of inſight in the ſame, nor in any other kind of Learning: ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo can no letters on the Book, ſo far forth, that common Artificers, as Smiths, Weavers and Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, boldly and accuſtomably take upon them great Cures, and things of great difficulty; in the which they partly uſe Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Witchcraft, partly apply ſuch Medicines unto the diſeaſe as be very noious, and nothing
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49471:15"/>meet therefore; to the high diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God, great infamy to the Faculty, and the grievous hurt, damage and deſtruction of many of the King's Liege-people; moſt eſpecially of them that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not diſcern the uncunning from the cunning: Be it therefore (to the ſurety and comfort of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of people) by the Authority of this preſent Parliament ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Again, the Preamble to King <hi>James</hi>'s Royal Charter granted to the <hi>College of Phyſicians</hi> does run thus: <hi>Whereas our moſt Noble and Renowned Predeceſſor, King</hi> Henry <hi>the Eighty late King of this our Realm of</hi> England, <hi>in his Princely wiſdom deeply con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidering, and by the Example of Foreign well-governed States and Kingdoms, truly under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding how profitable, benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial and acceptable it would be unto the whole body of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49471:16"/>of</hi> England, <hi>to reſtrain and ſuppreſs the exceſſive number of ſuch as daily profeſſed themſelves learned and profound Practiſers in the Faculty of Phyſick, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in truth they were men illite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and unexperienced, rather propounding unto themſelves their private gain, with the detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Kingdom, than to give relief in time of need: And likewiſe duely conſidering that by the rejecting of thoſe illiterate and unſkilful Practiſers, thoſe that were learned, grave and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Practiſers in that Faculty, ſhould received more bountiful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and alſo the induſtrious Students of that Profeſſion would be the better incouraged in their ſtudies and endeavours. For theſe and many other weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Motives,</hi> &amp;c. The Charter which our late moſt excellent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch gave them, runs much in the ſame ſtrain. So that our <hi>Kings</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49471:16"/>
                     <hi>Parliaments</hi> do expreſs a juſt and ſufficient indignation againſt thoſe illegal Practiſers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, come, <hi>a Blot is not a Blot until it be hit.</hi> I have travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led through <hi>Germany,</hi> and the beſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> and have learn'd with a few <hi>Chequeens</hi> to make my ſelf ſhot-proof againſt all they can do. Nor did I ſpend my time ſo ill in <hi>France,</hi> but that I quickly got the trick to purchaſe with a few <hi>Piſtols,</hi> a Title big enough to make me deſpiſe the pedantick Priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of <hi>Colleges</hi> and <hi>Conclaves.</hi> There it is a common thing for a man of Knowledge, who has learn'd the Art of Curing Diſeaſes by fits and ſtarts, hither and thither, out of the ordinary dull road, to write himſelf <hi>Phyſician in Ordinary to his Majesty, and Counſellour to the King in his Councils,</hi> after which he can ſafely interlope where-ever he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Nay, every ordinary Mecha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick is not only treated with the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49471:17"/>ſtyle of <hi>Monſieur,</hi> but can hang at his door, in great or Golden Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>MARCHAND in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the King,</hi> from the loweſt Trinket to the higheſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure you cannot but know, that in <hi>France</hi> no Phyſician though never ſo highly doctorated, will be permitted to practiſe Phyſick in any of their Towns of Reſort, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he be firſt <hi>Aggregated,</hi> or Imbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyed into the Society of Phyſicians dwelling in that place, and in order to that, be examined by them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh let him ſhew a <hi>Diploma</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fairly Gilded, or be his Pretences never ſo Honourable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not deny the matter of Fact: But I did not go to <hi>France</hi> to learn <hi>Faſhions,</hi> or the <hi>Rules of Civility.</hi> The Cuſtom you ſpeak of is a <hi>Monopoly,</hi> and it is equally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and diſhonourable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>The Cuſtom we ſpeak of is highly neceſſary: And there ought to go more to the being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49471:17"/>with mens lives than the meer getting a <hi>Diploma, en paſſant,</hi> whilſt a man is upon the ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, ſowing his wild Oats. For otherwiſe more over-forward Youths of <hi>ſeventeen</hi> than one, might probably in their Travels ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble upon the <hi>Degrees</hi> of <hi>Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> and <hi>Doctor,</hi> when they ſhould better be conning <hi>Tully</hi>'s <hi>Offices</hi> at School, and learning many ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious verſes in <hi>Horace, Juvenal,</hi> and <hi>Perſius.</hi> The Morals of thoſe Books well digeſted will lay good foundations for the making a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter man, and conſequently the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Phyſician. Beſides, the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Cuſtom may be one true Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, I am ſure it is a good Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why the <hi>French</hi> do multiply and increaſe at the rate they do, inſomuch that they can alwaies ſpare vaſt numbers of <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> to ſupply all their neighbour Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, nay ſometimes more than the jealous Natives would willingly admit.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49471:18"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>But ſtill theſe Monopolies are not to be endured.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>In troth, <hi>Momus,</hi> our <hi>Pariſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> are the moſt negligent and inar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial Monopolizers that ever were heard of. For them to ſuffer ſuch an inundation of Empirical Interlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, when they have in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>the Monopoly of Phyſick ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law,</hi> they do really de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be blamed! For them to ſuffer ſo many noxious and dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terious <hi>Weeds</hi> to grow and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread their Countrey, when they are intruſted with the care that none but <hi>uſeful</hi> and beneficial <hi>Plants</hi> ſhould grow in their <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick-Garden,</hi> 'tis a ſad and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous fault! But ſtill theſe <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies</hi> may better be endur'd than <hi>Levelling.</hi> A little good order is to be preferr'd before a <hi>Chaos</hi> of Confuſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I acknowledge there ought to be a certain ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among men, and can ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49471:18"/>diſtinguiſh between a Prince and a Peaſant; between a Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and a Clown. That which I inſiſt upon is this, that all <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claves of Phyſicians</hi> do tend to the deſtruction of mankind, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore out of my abundant Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhes to the World, I have fired this Beacon, and give ſuch a loud Alarm to the Countrey, that all <hi>Paris, and more than ſeven miles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout,</hi> will ring of it with a witneſs, this many a year. In a word, <hi>I have detected the Intrigues, Frauds, and Plots of the Phyſicians againſt their Patients, and their deſtroying the Faculty of Phyſick.</hi> Let me tell ye, it is a <hi>Pill</hi> that will ſtick in their Throats as long as they live, and will give them more bitter Gripes and woful Pains than ever <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquintida</hi> could do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>No ſuch matter, I aſſure ye. I have heard it indeed now and then <hi>mentioned</hi> among the Learned Members of the Faculty; and all
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49471:19"/>that ever I could obſerve upon it was only this, that they look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Author to be a malicious, mad, and <hi>Giddy Hair-brain,</hi> and look'd upon the Pamphlet with the greateſt contempt imaginable; no one, that ever I heard, thinking it worth the pains of an Anſwer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>No! I called all the Infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Spirits to my aſſiſtance. I row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed all the Faculties of my Heart and Brain, with more violence than the Lyon is ſaid to do himſelf with his Tail, when provoked to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat; I whetted my memory, put my imagination upon the Rack, <hi>in ſcirpo nodum quaerere;</hi> and I got <hi>Argus</hi> his eyes to ſearch into every corner of the Town, to ranſack e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Patient's Chamber, and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarie's Shop, in order to find proper materials for the greater perfection of this <hi>Work;</hi> and do they at laſt deſpiſe it, as you ſay?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>The very ſame upon my honeſt Word. Alas, the Faculty
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49471:19"/>of Phyſick is built upon ſurer Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations than to be ſhook with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whiffling Wind. It is not to be battered down with Pop-guns, and Boys play. They have <hi>Salves for every Sore;</hi> they have Antidotes for every poiſonous Dart that is ſhot at them, and generally the Dart that is ſhot againſt 'em rebounds upon the head of their Enemy, to his great Miſfortune, if not utter Ruine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I can never think them ſuch men of Might as you ſpeak them. For would any one that pretends to Manhood, and has Power and Strength on his ſide, ſuffer, as they tamely do, every ſawcy Jack to pull them by the Beard, and every licentious Buffoon to ſcoff at them how he pleaſes? What if their Predeceſſors had ſome power to curb the Inſolences of thoſe that contended with 'em? I am well ſatisfied that their ſtrength is gone: they are now
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49471:20"/>come to a Decrepit Old Age, and doth intolerably.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twill be well for you, if you find them ſuch dull <hi>Hocuſes,</hi> when you come to try the point together. You would do well to read a Book lately printed, called <hi>The Royal College of Phyſicians of</hi> London, <hi>founded and eſtabliſh'd by Law, as appears by Letters Patents, Acts of Parliament, adjudged Caſes, &amp;c.</hi> Collected by one of their worthy Collegue's D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> G. You will find likewiſe in the ſame Book, <hi>An Hiſtorical account of the College's Proceedings againſt Empiricks and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlicenſed Practiſers in every Prince's Reign, from their firſt Incorporation, to the Murther of the Royal Martyr King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt.</hi> This Book does plainly prove, that they have exerciſed very great Power, both by way of <hi>Fine,</hi> and <hi>Impriſonment</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Bail or Manprize, and by divers Overthrows at Law; and the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Law (who can beſt judge
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49471:20"/>of thoſe matters) do poſitively affirm that they have the ſame power ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Let the Lawyers ſay what they will, and the Confederates write what they will, in ſpight of all they can do, I will think, and ſay, and alſo write what I will. <hi>Moreover, he that is ſo far debauch'd in his Senſes as to be admitted into any</hi> Conclave <hi>of</hi> Phyſicians, <hi>doth,</hi> ipſo facto, <hi>as much entitle himſelf to all their Man-ſlaughters, Fourbs, and Impoſtures, as he that is liſted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a Troop of</hi> Neapolitan Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti <hi>doth at that moment participate in the guilt of all their former Crimes and Villanies, in the ſame manner as if he had been a part in them himſelf.</hi> Preface.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>So that by your way of Arguing, <hi>the Communion of Saints</hi> ought to be expunged out of your Creed, as well as a Combination of <hi>Banditi.</hi> It ſeems a man ought not to unite with any society of Chriſtians, for fear he ſhould be
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49471:21"/>thereby infected with the Guilt of every particular Pretender to that Communion. Henceforth let no man bind his Son Prentice to a Trade, leſt <hi>ipſo facto</hi> he make him go ſnacks in all the Lies and Cheats of every individual Knave that in turning the penny. Let all Societies and Corporations be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by your Magiſterial <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> becauſe they ſo nearly reſemble theſe <hi>Conclaves</hi> of <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> Let no man marry a Wife, leſt himſelf be guilty of Adultery every time the ſlippery <hi>Aſſociate</hi> takes a frisk abroad to ſee a Friend. And is that the reaſon why ſome men do divorce themſelves <hi>à mensâ &amp; thoro,</hi> even from Virtuous Women, and upon ſecond thoughts do become Melancholick Celibates, after <hi>God had joined them together?</hi> I have heard it often affirmed (to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Married State) that the Converſation of Women (in a lawful way) does wonderfully
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49471:21"/>ſweeten, and civilize the manners of men, and that they <hi>are Helps</hi> very <hi>meet</hi> for us upon many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts. But I ſhall grant that Marriage cannot make the <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian change his Skin, nor the Leopard his Spots.</hi> He that is born an <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſociable Creature,</hi> in whom Sowre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Auſterity are radically im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted, and who by the abuſes of Chymiſtry has turned all his Animal Spirits into keen and corroſive, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he can think of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what is ſowre and grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ingenious ears, it muſt not be expected that the State of Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſhould tranform him into a Lamb, or make him mealy-mouth'd. But again, let us conſider. <hi>He that is ſo far debauch'd in his Senſes as to be admitted into any</hi> Conclave <hi>of</hi> Phyſicians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is a ſtrain of that rapture, and extravagance, that certainly you muſt have been in ſome <hi>Trance</hi> when you penn'd it. It is ſo ſhamefully ſilly, as well as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49471:22"/>malicious to the higheſt degree, and every body that reads muſt needs ſo ſee through it, that I am almoſt aſhamed to repeat a piece of ſuch groſs weakneſs, wherein you have taken ſuch timely care to expoſe your ſelf to the Cenſure and Scorn of all men, Have you always had ſo implacable a hatred unto, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant opinion of all <hi>Conclaves</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>No. Time was, when I though well enough of ſome of them, and particularly the <hi>Conclave</hi> of <hi>Phyſicians</hi> at <hi>London.</hi> It was at a time when I had no ſmall hopes of getting an Honourable Admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance among them, and in order to it did uſe frequently to meet Doctor <hi>A.B.C.</hi> near the Plot-Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, (ſince ſo called) in <hi>Alderſgate-ſtreet.</hi> About the ſame time I writ an excellent and popular Treatiſe, called <hi>The Diſeaſe of London, or a New Diſcovery of the Scurvey,</hi> Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Anno</hi> 1675.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49471:22"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>By the good token that you ſpoke well of people once in your life; Pray let's hear a little of the Harangue you then made in favour of the College, and the Leanred Members of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>The Preface to that work begins thus:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>It is obſervable, that the Firſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Foundation of Phyſick, was laid by the great Architect of that Art</hi> Hippocates, <hi>in an Iſle called</hi> Coos; <hi>and it is no leſs remarkable, that the trueſt Superſtructure was made on it, in this Iſland by the</hi> Famed College of Phyſicians of <hi>London. It was a Member of that Society. Doctor</hi> William Harvey <hi>of</hi> Immortal Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, <hi>that had laid another</hi> Baſis <hi>by detecting the</hi> Circulation of the Blood, <hi>for which this</hi> Britain <hi>may as juſtly merit the Title of</hi> Divine, <hi>as the other</hi> Coos. <hi>The Rubbiſh that was caſt about it by</hi> Pariſanus, Leighnerus, <hi>and others, to obſcure it, tended to render it more firm; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49471:23"/>this was ſo ſmoothly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by that</hi> Incomparable Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian <hi>Sir</hi> George Ent, <hi>the now</hi> Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>of the</hi> College, <hi>in his Apology, that all <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities did then adjudge thoſe void of Apprehenſion, that did not readily imbrace that Principle, and that it was impoſſible for any man to arrive</hi> to be a Phyſician <hi>without the knowledge of it.</hi> A little after in the ſame Preface, I did call <hi>the whole Body an Apollinean Society, and a Society whoſe fame is ſpread as far as the Art of Phyſick it ſelf.</hi> Nay, and <hi>giving an account of the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Phyſick,</hi> I did declare, <hi>that the</hi> Fellows <hi>of the</hi> College <hi>have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo wonderfully ſucceſsful in it, that their Methods of Curing the moſt ſtubborn of Diſeaſes, may ſerve for a fit</hi> Pattern <hi>to</hi> all <hi>the</hi> World <hi>to practiſe by; and I cannot deny but in many Caſes it hath proved ſo to me, which to acknowledge is the ſole occaſion of my introducing this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:49471:23"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>And can you read the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of ſo great a Truth without bluſhing, and confuſion? A Truth hich Foreigners do uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally own; (and you could not chooſe but find it ſo in your Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vells) but yet as true as it is, they are too modeſt and ingenuous arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly to proclaim their <hi>Methods</hi> of Curing for <hi>Patterns to all the World.</hi> You cannot but know that we have greater plenty of <hi>ſtubborn Diſeaſes,</hi> than thoſe Hotter Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries have, though which you tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velled. Nay, the ſame untoward and <hi>ſtubborn Diſeaſe</hi> ſhall be <hi>more ſtubborn</hi> with us, than it is with them; a Clyſter, and a purge, and a Bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or two will not do, in this <hi>ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Countrey.</hi> Our Phyſicians do find they have a great deal more to think of, or elſe they would never have proved ſo <hi>wonderfully ſucceſsful</hi> as <hi>you</hi> ſay they are, (and there is no doubt of the truth of it) in the Practice of Phyſick. Therefore he
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49471:24"/>is not <hi>debauch'd</hi> very <hi>far in his Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> who ſpeaks true ſence in the opinion of ſober men, and who forbears not to give to Deſerving men their due; but that man's <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd</hi> beyond hopes of recovery, who is gone <hi>ſo far,</hi> that he has loſt all <hi>common Senſe,</hi> loſt the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the principal things he writ of, even <hi>the ſole occaſion of</hi> ſo late <hi>a Diſcourſe,</hi> in acknowledgment o the juſt worth of the Learned <hi>Fellows of the College, whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of Curing may ſerve for a fit Pattern to all the World to practiſe by.</hi> This is not an ordinary <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch</hi> of the Mind for a Phyſician of <hi>your Education</hi> to rail, like a Madman, at <hi>all Societies;</hi> and even of <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> with a moſt bloody <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> worſe than any <hi>Anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</hi> If Malice and ill Nature had not only overclowded, but extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd your Reaſon, if the <hi>Senſes</hi> of your Mind were not abſolutely <hi>beſotted</hi> or infatuated, you could
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49471:24"/>not but have known who is the moſt likely to be <hi>debauch'd in his Senſes;</hi> either he that eaſily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits himſelf to the Laws and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of his Countrey, and lives in a due ſubjection to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under which he is born and bred, or elſe he that would break and confound all order, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn and diſſolve, by his good will, all Societies in the World, and who would rather be a ſolitary Wild Beaſt, range all alone, like a decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Enemy to Mankind, than be any ways <hi>Sociable,</hi> though it be in the Conyerſation of moſt Learned and Admitale men.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Piſh! That Treatiſe was written ten Years ago, and though it had the advantage of bearing my Name before it, yet I muſt tell you, it was not written by me. It was a different Hand, and different Perſon that writ it. For they ſay that Phyſicians do generally hold that once in every <hi>ſeven Years</hi> our
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49471:25"/>Bodies are quite changed from what they were. Our Gizzards are wholly new, and there is a total ſupply of new Matter, though under the ſame Form; And further, that Arch-Philoſopher, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtotle,</hi> is ſo extreamly of the foreſaid opinion, that he poſitively maintains, a man can't go twice the <hi>ſame man</hi> into the <hi>ſame River.</hi> Now I have very good reaſon to think that <hi>Mores animi ſequuntur Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramentum corporis,</hi> and therefore the Body of that Hand which writ that <hi>Treatiſe of the Scurvey,</hi> might be of another-gueſs Frame and Temperament, than this which writ the <hi>Conclave of Phyſicians,</hi> and ſo the Mind might then be more inclined to write Panegyricks of Worthy men, than to expoſe them to the laſh of Satyrical Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections. Does not a <hi>Sun-ſhiny</hi> day alſo ſtrangely influence the Mind, and make it brisk and frol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickſome, kind and debonaire,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49471:25"/>when the effects of a <hi>Clowdy</hi> Seaſon are quite the contary? ſo that you ſee there might be very many, and very good reaſons, both for the one, and for the other.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed I ſhould hardly have thought you ſo great a <hi>Changeling,</hi> as you learnedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak your ſelf. If the Weather-Cock of your Brain does ſo depend upon the Wind and Weather, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as the Phyſick-Seaſon is fair or foul with you, I fear we muſt never expect more of thoſe <hi>Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiny</hi> Books, theſe laſt of the <hi>Cloudy</hi> and <hi>Malevolent</hi> ſort being now ſo <hi>natural</hi> to you. You are too old to <hi>change</hi> to the better, and are ſo exceeding bad, that you cannot poſſible <hi>change</hi> to the worſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
                  <p>Whatever you may therefore think of my future Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in the ſame tenour of ill will to the Faculty, I do find ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable alteration in my Dyſcraſy, ſince the firſt Edition of my laſt
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49471:26"/>Book. For whereas other Authors do reprint their books with ſome <hi>Additions,</hi> I have publiſhed <hi>the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Edition</hi> of mine <hi>with many Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>That's pretty. That you ſhould ſpy ſuch Faults worthy to be <hi>Altered</hi> in the Brat of your own Brain! But I would fain hear a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle more of the Preface of that <hi>Scurvey-Author,</hi> adjourning one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute our further Entertainment by the <hi>Conclave-Author.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For many Ages the World was ignorant, whence the ſuperfluous moiſture proceeded, which we hourly ſpit out, until the out-let,</hi> viz. <hi>the</hi> Ductus Salivales <hi>were diſcovered by the Learned Doctor</hi> Wharton, a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of the College; <hi>and though it was generally believed, nothing could be further declared, touching the Structure of the</hi> Liver, <hi>yet ſo elegant a deſcription of its moſt intime Parts, and Diſſemination of its Veſſels,</hi> Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidochus, <hi>and a very exact purſuit of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49471:26"/>the</hi> Lymphaeducts, <hi>was made by the moſt accompliſh'd Doctor</hi> Gliſſon (<hi>the late</hi> Prefident) <hi>in his</hi> Anatomi-Hepatis, <hi>that in a manner it appeara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as if nothing had been ſolidly written of it by any before him.</hi> ibid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Now give us a caſt of the <hi>Conclave-Autor</hi>'s opinion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>College</hi>'s Ignorance in Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and his own ſuperlavtive Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency in it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
                  <p>That is not fair; you unſeaſonably interrupt me. I was going on; but becauſe you are in haſte to have it, hear the <hi>Conclave-author</hi> ſpeaking thus in the Preface: <hi>What new Diſcoveries have they made in Antaomy theſe twenty Years? Certainly none: and I dare preſume to ſay, I my ſelf have divulged more new Anatomical Obſervations, which are of greater uſe, than all of 'em in a Bundle.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phiol.</speaker>
                  <p>Say you ſo, moſt mighty <hi>Author?</hi> Are thoſe Worthies late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mentioned, of <hi>Immortal Mentory,</hi>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:49471:27"/>thoſe <hi>Incomparable Phyſicians,</hi> thoſe famous and <hi>moſt Accompliſht Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi> that <hi>Learned Fellow of this College,</hi> to be all caſhiered and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getten, with a <hi>What new Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries have they made in Anatomy theſe twenty Years?</hi> You would have the incautious and leſs-knowing Reader to underſtand a hundred Years by your ſlily limited <hi>twenty Years.</hi> The light-headed Gallant muſt not have one word of hint, as if any the leaſt thing in Anatomy had ever been diſcovered by them before. But he ſhall have his Belly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of your hidden Diſcoveries, and muſt ſwallow them with an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite Faith. Yet in all the Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Diſcourſes that ever I heard ſince my coming to this Town, which is ſome many a Year, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v er heard Man, Woman, or Child, neither Learned nor Unlearned, no Curious <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> nor Incurious Cox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comb of any kind, to mutter the leaſt Syllable of <hi>your New Anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49471:27"/>Obſervations;</hi> whereas not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this Town and Kingdom rings, but Foreign Univerſities, and Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomical Authors far and near, do with one conſent acknowledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud, how highly they are indebt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to our <hi>Divine Britain,</hi> as you called it, and particularly to <hi>the moſt Experienced and Learned Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians of the College of</hi> London, as in another place, for their many <hi>improvements of Anatomy.</hi> I could name divers Members of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege now living, whoſe Names are deſervedly Great in that reſpect, and are not like to be forgotten in after-ages, no more than thoſe men of <hi>Immortal Memory,</hi> of whom you read us a Lecture, are forgotten in this. But I find you expected eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Year from the College a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of <hi>New Anatomical Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> as conſtantly as the Spring and Harveſt. When <hi>Apelles</hi> has drawn his Picture, and finiſh'd it in every Point, would you have the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49471:28"/>of Painters be always dabling about it, until they ſpoil it again? Friend, this <hi>Century</hi> has done very well, and much better than you could wiſh, in <hi>Anatomy,</hi> perhaps more than all the Ages in the World before; and it deſerves little blame from <hi>Momus</hi> himſelf. Beſides, we ought in civility to leave ſomething for our Children after us to do; and not to become ſuch <hi>Monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> of <hi>Anatomy,</hi> as You, <hi>who dare preſume to ſay, I my ſelf have divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged more new Anatomical Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are of greater uſe, than all of 'em in a bundle.</hi> I wiſh you would have directed us where we might meet with a <hi>Bundle</hi> of your ſpick and ſpan <hi>New Anatomical Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations.</hi> I fear you have <hi>divulged</hi> them to none but your ſelf. And though you <hi>dare preſume to ſay</hi> as much as any Scioliſt whatſoever, yet you are not ſo very competent a judge of their <hi>greater uſe,</hi> than thoſe of all the World beſides, or
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49471:28"/>even of all the Members of the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege. And ſo thus much for the <hi>Conclave-Preface.</hi> Now give me one <hi>reliſhing Bit</hi> more, out of that <hi>Scurvey-Preface.</hi> For really I muſt needs take it all by <hi>Bits</hi> and Snaps, and my further Anſwer to the Book of the <hi>Conclave</hi> muſt be in ſome meaſure according to the Book it ſelf, which gives us our Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, not in ſolid ſubſtantial Diſhes, but by way of haſh and piece-meal. Beſides, it would clog and lye hard upon our Stomachs, and tire our patience, if we were to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine nicely, to feed upon, and to digeſt the whole and every part of it. And I would have this <hi>Oglio</hi> of the <hi>Author's particular preparing</hi> ſo ſerved up, that there may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to pleaſe the Palate of the Merry and Moroſe, the Sowre and the Sweet, nay, a little for all ſorts of Readers, who have been amuſed with his Book.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="51-100" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Momus.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That ſome Diſtempers
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:49471:29"/>had eſcaped the Obſervation of the Grecian and Arabian Phyſicians, was evidenced by the eminently learned Doctor</hi> Bates, <hi>Doctor</hi> Gliſſon, <hi>and Doctor</hi> Regemorter, <hi>Collegues, in that excellent Treatiſe</hi> de Rachitide. <hi>In all my Travels, I had never the good Fortune to be particularly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with a perſon equal in Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terature, Experience and Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, with Doctor</hi> Bates; <hi>I muſt confeſs, I went ever from him more knowing than I was before.</hi> ibid.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis true, theſe Collegues have prov'd notable men in their Generation, and Doctor <hi>Bates</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly deſerves his due, as being Dead, and ſo not like to incommode or interfere with the <hi>Caprichio's</hi> of the Living. I am mightily miſ-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, if this Great Man, at the very beginning of your <hi>particular acquaintance</hi> with him, did not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, upon the firſt Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, ſo ſoon as your Back was turn'd, declare to your Friend
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49471:29"/>who introduced you, that <hi>he thought you could never fix to any thing, nor ſo much as fix in a place,</hi> or in plain Engliſh, that you had a <hi>Maggot,</hi> or a <hi>Worm</hi> in you <hi>Head;</hi> which indeed has ſince driven you about from <hi>Hatton Garden</hi> to <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> and from <hi>Fleetſtreet</hi> to <hi>Hatton-Garden</hi> again; from thence to <hi>Chelmsford</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> and from <hi>Chelmsford</hi> to <hi>Ipſwich;</hi> and now at laſt from <hi>Ipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> to I know not where; the one half of you to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and t' other half to about <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge.</hi> But again, if you had had the <hi>good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne</hi> to have been received a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that College in due time, and by that means had got a fair opportunity to be more <hi>particularly acquainted</hi> with divers Eminent and very <hi>Knowing</hi> Men ſtill living a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, you might poſſibly have met with others as Inſtructive <hi>Acquaintance</hi> as you did <hi>in all your Travels.</hi> If you had <hi>Aſſociated</hi> with them, you would certainly have
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49471:30"/>learn'd more Modeſty and leſs Arrogance, than you now have. You might then have accounted it a greater Honour to have been the <hi>leaſt</hi> among thoſe <hi>Learned Collegues,</hi> than thus to pride your ſelf with be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thought the <hi>firſt</hi> among the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible <hi>Empirical</hi> Tribe. Now proceed, and read me ſome of thoſe places I have mark'd with a <hi>black coal.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you take no notice then of <hi>I Conuglio pitolo,</hi> and the <hi>Conuglio Grande. <hi>You are to believe this</hi>
                     </hi> Tract <hi>is not written to pleaſe many.</hi> Preface to the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes: Thoſe great let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters do give us to underſtand that you can ſpeak ſome <hi>Italian;</hi> we will not doubt but that in your Travels you pick'd up ſome ſcraps of that kind. And you had a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to it, by travelling ſo young. For an idle Boy is much better at learning Languages, than a wiſe or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:49471:30"/>full-grown Man. <hi>Momus,</hi> you need not have told us that <hi>we are to believe this</hi> your <hi>Tract s not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to pleaſe many.</hi> I ſhould rather incline <hi>to believe</hi> that <hi>it was not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten to pleaſe any,</hi> but to gratifie an inveterate rancour of mind, to pleaſe only your own ſelf, and to quench a little your <hi>ſitis inextingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis,</hi> your unſatiable thirſt of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, and moſt implacable hatred to the Faculty, for not court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you forſooth to be of their Number. But perhaps your <hi>Tract</hi> may pleaſe ſome beſides your ſelf, it may pleaſe ſome beſides your ſelf, it may pleaſe ſome little Quacks and Mountebanks, to whom the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege is a declared Enemy <hi>according to Law;</hi> it may pleaſe ſome ſquandring frothy Gallants, who have been privately great <hi>Sufferers</hi> by your <hi>Little</hi> ſtrowling <hi>Menus,</hi> whoſe Contagion they could not diſcover by reaſon of her <hi>Mask,</hi> and who in all probability had <hi>ſuffered</hi> moſt of all from you <hi>Grand Hermaphrodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49471:31"/>Cure,</hi> your <hi>Herculean, Gigantean, Vulcanous,</hi> or other Conceited <hi>Cures.</hi> Their <hi>ill Cures,</hi> no doubt, might make them angry with <hi>Phyſick</hi> it ſelf, becauſe they <hi>ſuffered</hi> under the hands of an <hi>Ill Phyſician,</hi> and had not the wit to diſtinguiſh between a good Commodity and a bad, or between a man and a poſt. Laſtly, Your <hi>Tract</hi> might pleaſe thoſe who are never pleaſed with any thing that is good, ſuch who continually ſneer at all that is <hi>ſerious,</hi> who think it Wit to expoſe Vertue and Religion in uncouth <hi>Burleſque,</hi> and whoſe profligate Lives do make it their Intereſt to declare for Scurrili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on your ſide.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>You are too ſevere, <hi>Philia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> If you had been one of our Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and had ſhewed ſo great a Zeal for Errors, Defamations, and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſentations, as you do for <hi>Truth,</hi> and for the <hi>Publick,</hi> I ſhould not have wondred; but thus to exceed the bounds of Moderation for the
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:49471:31"/>ſake of others more than ones own particular, is a Myſtery, and a Rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to me that I cannot unfold. For they ſay, <hi>Every bodies buſineſs is no bodies buſineſs.</hi> Sure a <hi>good Fee</hi> of our ſide would abate this heat you ſhew for the Good of the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>A <hi>good Fee</hi> is no ſuch tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter, as to make me forget my duty. You and I are great ſtrangers I find. If you knew me throughly, you would poſſibly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that I am more eaſily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed into a Paſſion, when I meet with wretches who conſpire the <hi>Publick Ruine,</hi> and who care not how they <hi>trouble the waters</hi> of their Countrey, ſo they may the better <hi>fiſh</hi> in them, than when I meet with <hi>particular</hi> Affronts, or <hi>perſonal</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations. I have learn'd that <hi>Love is the fulfilling the</hi> Chriſtian <hi>Law.</hi> And I hope I ſhould ſooner cut my own fleſh, than willingly injure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother man by Word, or Deed,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49471:32"/>unleſs I look'd upon him to be a <hi>common Enemy to mankind,</hi> and to become a <hi>Wolf</hi> or a <hi>Tigre</hi> to us all. Therefore, <hi>Momus,</hi> read on, but before you enter into the <hi>Tract,</hi> let us have one of thoſe <hi>Advertiſements,</hi> which immediately follows the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Modern Curioſities of Art and Nature,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>compoſed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimented by the Sieur</hi> Lemery <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary to the French King.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>That's falſe, and a trick; it is a Baſtard laid at the wrong door, and therefore fit enough to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to the ſucceeding <hi>Tract.</hi> I can tell you, from undoubted Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, that the <hi>Sieur Lemery</hi> in his Letters to his Friends here, who were inquiſitive upon the matter, does with great concern diſclaim his being the Author of this delicate piece. He thinks himſelf extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly injur'd, in being thought the Author of ſuch a Rhapſody of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Experiments, Aſtrological
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49471:32"/>Cures, Houſewifery and Cookery, and a tedious long Miſh-maſh of Tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. It was written (and ſo printed) by a <hi>Sieur</hi> named <hi>d'Emery,</hi> a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man at large, and not by the ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Sieur Lemery,</hi> now a Doctor of Phyſick. Now as for the other three Books, there advertiſed toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, we'll e'en let them paſs, as needing to be hung out with ſuch a <hi>Buſh,</hi> in order to force a <hi>ſale.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Solomon <hi>gives us this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> (Eccleſiaſt. <hi>chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.) <hi>There is a time to kill, and a time to heal;</hi> which my mother-wit interprets, That a Phyſician, at ſome times he kills, and at ſome times he cures. <hi>Furthermore, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that as</hi> Solomon <hi>ſets down that there is a</hi> time to kill <hi>before the time to heal; ſo generally Phyſicians (eſpecially of pretended Societies)</hi> kill <hi>more than they</hi> cure. p. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſame <hi>Solomon</hi> (<hi>Prov.</hi> 26.4, 5.) gives us another good remark, worthy your ſerious conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49471:33"/>
                     <hi>Anſwer not a Fool ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Folly, leſt thou alſo be like unto him.</hi> Which I do under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thus: when you diſcourſe with a Fool, or proud conceited Coxcomb, do not fawn upon him, and ſooth him in his follies, but boldly and honeſtly expoſe them to deſerved ſcorn, leſt thou alſo be thought like unto him, and ſo thou become ſo unfortunate, as to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for <hi>a Bird of the ſame feather.</hi> And then again, in the next verſe: <hi>Anſwer a Fool according to his folly, left he be wiſe in his own conceit.</hi> Which is eaſie enough to interpret: <hi>Anſwer a Fool,</hi> (when he writes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregiouſly ſilly, and maliciouſly) not with a grave diſcourſe, and ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous arguing, but ſerve him up with his own ſawce, ſhew him the hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous deformity of his Viſage in a true Looking-glaſs, let the ſcoffer be ſoundly ſcoff'd at, <hi>leſt he perſiſt wiſe in his own conceit.</hi> In the ſame <hi>third</hi> Chapter of <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> not
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49471:33"/>
                     <hi>ſecond,</hi> (as you miſtake and blun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, being not uſed to read the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> carefully and with any good deſign, but meerly to profane, and groſly abuſe them) in that <hi>third</hi> Chapter, I ſay, you will find <hi>a time to weep</hi> for your unparallell'd offences, as well as <hi>to laugh</hi> without reaſon, like a Fool; <hi>there is a time to keep ſilence,</hi> eſpecially in what you have taken an Oath to keep ſilence; and <hi>there is a time to ſpeak</hi> ſeriouſly and diſcreetly which the <hi>Tract</hi> before us does too much inſinuate that you never obſerve. Likewiſe <hi>there is a time to love as well as to hate.</hi> But you can ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve no other times, but <hi>there time of killing and healing.</hi> The firſt you obſerve too much, and take a moſt particular notice of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing infinitely tickled with the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, that the <hi>Wiſe-man</hi> has put the <hi>killing time</hi> in the firſt place. Whether you obſerve as you ſhould do, <hi>the time of healing,</hi> will beſt be
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:49471:34"/>judged by the following diſcourſe. And now, <hi>Momus,</hi> I ſhall adviſe you to forbear abuſing <hi>Scripture</hi> ſo ſcandalouſly and conceitedly. Wee'l give you leave, for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>ludere cum corio humano,</hi> but by no means <hi>cum ſacris. Be merry and wiſe,</hi> and remember that we are acting a fulſome farce, wherein it is very improper to conſult ſuch a man as <hi>Solomon. Your Mother-Wit</hi> to pretend to the Wiſdom of <hi>Solomon!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In moſt Countries, a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal who is to be put to the Rack, or any ways executed, is uſually, from his ſuffering, called the</hi> Patient <hi>or</hi> Sufferer; <hi>and ſo is the ſick man that is to ſubject himſelf to the rigid ſentence of ſome of theCombined Phyſicians, which renders the word</hi> Patient <hi>or</hi> Sufferer <hi>truly ſynony<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous to both.</hi> p. 5.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>In all Countries, that ever I heard of, a <hi>Criminal</hi> is called a <hi>Criminal,</hi> as a <hi>Spade</hi> is called a
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49471:34"/>
                     <hi>Spade.</hi> But in <hi>your</hi> Practice wee'll allow a Venerial Criminal, who is to undergo your <hi>Herculean,</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Bombaſtick <hi>Cures,</hi> to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly called a <hi>Sufferer.</hi> And yet let him <hi>ſuffer</hi> the <hi>Rack</hi> you put him upon, never ſo much, in order to expiate for his paſt <hi>Crimes,</hi> I gueſs you would take it very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly to have him uſually called your <hi>Sufferer.</hi> But when once he is in your <hi>Limbo,</hi> the ſick man muſt e'en be contented to take it <hi>Patiently,</hi> and ſo may be called your <hi>Patient.</hi> Pray would you your ſelf, in ſober ſadneſs, allow a good Generous Patient <hi>who ſubjects him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to your rigid</hi> uncontroulable <hi>ſentence,</hi> to be called immediately your <hi>Sufferer?</hi> I believe the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman would ſoon take his leave of you, and would much rather <hi>ſubject</hi> himſelf to the milder ſentence <hi>of ſome of the combined Phyſicians,</hi> in hopes to find out a <hi>Preſerver</hi> from the <hi>Sufferings</hi> you thus impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49471:35"/>threatned him withal. Now let <hi>the word Patient or Sufferer be truly ſynonymous</hi> with you, we of the <hi>Combined</hi> Party, <hi>Combined</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the knowledge of better things, ſhall always diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Fools Cap, and a Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers Beard, between the Muſick of a Rattle and a Baſe-Viol.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>If <hi>that be not</hi> reverâ <hi>the greateſt truth,</hi> I think I paid off <hi>the men of Phyſick</hi> about <hi>the New Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, a name of ignorance, their</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſylum ignorantiae. <hi>One time they ſhall tell you, it is an Ague; another, it is a Feavor; a third, it's an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue and Feavor; a fourth, it's Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor and Ague; a fifth, it's the new Diſeaſe; a denomination ſo idle, that every Novice in Phyſick might well ſuſpect they had never read</hi> Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates <hi>or</hi> Galen; <hi>eſpecially upon obſerving, that every Autumnal or Epidemick Diſtemper is by them termed new: whereas, the gentle Pox excepted, there is not any among
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49471:35"/>all thoſe they have nominated new Diſeaſes, but what is amply deſcribed in many ancient Authors.</hi> p. 10, 11.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I believe we ſhall find you horribly out, <hi>reverâ,</hi> in moſt of your <hi>greateſt truths. The men of Phyſick</hi> you ſpeak of, have read <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> both <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Old,</hi> and they have read <hi>Men</hi> too. What if one Woman tells you, it is an <hi>Ague,</hi> the Nurſe, a <hi>Fever,</hi> the Midwife, an <hi>Ague</hi> and <hi>Fever,</hi> and after all an old Goſſip comes and tells you, it is the <hi>New Diſeaſe;</hi> muſt the <hi>Men of Phyſick</hi> become <hi>Sufferers</hi> for the <hi>Womens</hi> tittle tattle? But what if a raging Autumnal Epidemical Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver has been ſometimes even by Phyſicians called <hi>the New Diſeaſe?</hi> Is a Diſeaſe not to be called <hi>New,</hi> becauſe it had entred into your Crotchet before, or becauſe you might poſſibly have read ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like it in ſome antient Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor? It is certainly <hi>New</hi> to <hi>John-a-Stiles,</hi> and <hi>John-a-Nokes,</hi> in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49471:36"/>one ſenſe at leaſt; they never ſaw, nor heard of it before. But it ſeems you, and <hi>every Novice in Phyſick might well ſuſpect they had never read</hi> Hippocrates <hi>or</hi> Galen. Whereas if your ſelf had but cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorily (as <hi>Novices</hi> uſe to do) lookt into <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of Epidemical Diſeaſes, you would have found him immediately de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing the firſt, ſecond, and third Conſtitution of the Air, and the variation of Diſeaſes according to its various Conſtitution, in the Iſle <hi>Thaſus.</hi> And do you, and your <hi>Novices</hi> think, that this <hi>Iſland</hi> of <hi>Great Britain</hi> is leſs ſubject to the various alterations of Air and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons (and conſequently to a great diverſity of Diſeaſes) than <hi>Thaſus</hi> was? You muſt needs have heard that many good Women in our <hi>Iſland</hi> do carry <hi>Almanacks</hi> in their <hi>Bones,</hi> and do very ſadly bemoan the great uncertainty of our Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. We need not go back to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49471:36"/>
                     <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen</hi> for the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding ſo plain a truth; you might eaſily have conſulted one of our own late <hi>Authors,</hi> but indeed a <hi>Combined Phyſician,</hi> and you might have had ſufficient ſatisfaction in this matter. In his <hi>Works,</hi> after his excellent Treatiſe <hi>De Morbis Acutis</hi> (wherein the Circulation of New Diſeaſes, and New Epidemical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions is made as plain as a Pike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaffe) you will find an <hi>Epiſtola Reſponſoria</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> a Head of a Medical Colledge there, and he <hi>one of Her Majeſties Phyſicians in Ordinary, with Fee,</hi> to the Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author of the foreſaid Treatiſe. This <hi>Epiſtle</hi> from ſo Great a Man is full of acknowledgments to the Author, for his ſo nice Obſervations of the different Conſtitutions of the Air, many years paſt, and for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo Hiſtorical an account of the ſucceſſion of different Epidemical Diſeaſes, according to the predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:49471:37"/>of this or that Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>However you value and ſet forth that Modern Author, yet I muſt tell you, I have in divers places of my <hi>Tract</hi> made him a meer <hi>Bumpkin;</hi> I ſcorn to read the Works of our Modern Aſſociates, unleſs to ridicule and expoſe them. I do aver, that <hi>the gentle Pox excepted, there is not any among all thoſe they have nominated</hi> New Diſeaſes, <hi>but what is amply deſcribed in many an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Authors.</hi> p. 11.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I know very well that you have ſhamefully abuſed many Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and excellent Men, and can tell the true reaſon why you have taken ſuch pains to abuſe <hi>this particularly.</hi> When we come to diſcourſe of the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> you ſhall have it as freely as I had it. In the mean time let us mind the buſineſs before us. <hi>The gentle Pox!</hi> If it be ſo <hi>gentle,</hi> I would fain know why you ſhould think of nothing but <hi>Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean</hi>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:49471:37"/>and <hi>Gigantean Cures</hi> for it, as you unwittingly do it your <hi>Little Venus unmaskt.</hi> Is it ſeemly, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming a Man of your <hi>Education,</hi> that has Travelled ſo far, to call for <hi>Hercules</hi> his Club, or a <hi>Giant</hi>'s ſtrong arm to encounter a poor <hi>gentle Pox?</hi> The Female, the <hi>gentle</hi> Sex does often ſuffer under this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe; and will you preſently fright the poor Creature out of her wits, with telling her, ſhe muſt undergo your <hi>Herculean</hi> or your <hi>Gigantean Cure?</hi> You are exceedingly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to the <hi>little <hi>Venus,</hi>
                     </hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if it be conſidered, what you <hi>obſerve</hi> in the <hi>Gigantean Cure,</hi> Art. 14. <hi>Indeed a Patient had better half hang himſelf, than undergo this Cure, there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing comparable to the pain in their mouth, anguiſh about their heart and ſides, and the extream thirst they endure, having, like</hi> Tantalus, <hi>their mouth full of water, and yet ready to periſh for want of drink. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49471:38"/>is this all, ſome growing Phrenetick in the Cure, others Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralytick and Apoplectick. Momus,</hi> if this be your way of curing <hi>gentle</hi> Diſeaſes, that a <hi>Patient had better half hang himſelf than undergo it,</hi> truſt me, I'll have a care of you in <hi>violent</hi> diſeaſes: for by your rule a man had better be <hi>quite hang'd than undergo that Cure.</hi> Well but if the <hi>Pox</hi> be not <hi>gentle,</hi> we'll allow it to be <hi>gentile,</hi> though not ſo over-gentile neither, as your Adage would have it: <hi>Three Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pains and ſix grand Cures make a Grand Gentleman.</hi> The <hi>grand Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman</hi> truly is but in a poor condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if he muſt undergo no leſs than <hi>ſix grand Cures,</hi> your <hi>grand Hermaphroditick</hi> gallimaufrey <hi>Cures,</hi> in order to be ſo accompliſh'd. But <hi>the gentle Pox excepted, there is not any,</hi> &amp;c. What, have you ſo ſoon forgot, <hi>that ſome Diſtempers,</hi> (more than one) <hi>had eſcaped the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the</hi> Grecian <hi>and</hi> Arabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49471:38"/>an <hi>Phyſicians, was evidenced by the eminently learned Doctor</hi> Bates, <hi>and others, Collegues in that excellent Treatiſe</hi> de Rachitide? You ſoon forget your Friends, I ſee, though never ſo <hi>particularly acquainted</hi> with them. Here the <hi>Rickets,</hi> and <hi>ſome</hi> other <hi>Distempers</hi> were ſolemnly and formally acknowledged to be <hi>New Diſeaſes,</hi> but the Maggot biting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother part of your head, the <hi>gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Pox</hi> muſt only be excepted. And are they <hi>amply deſcribed,</hi> and <hi>in many antient Authors?</hi> I dare venture a Chequeen or two, that you cannot ſhew me <hi>one ancient Author,</hi> wherein the <hi>Rickets</hi> are ſo <hi>amply deſcribed.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I can be eaſily perſwaded, that how great an Idol ſoever a Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low is ſet up by the Vulgar, from the falſe ſuggeſtion of Dog-fleying, he ſhall never arrive to a ſagacity of diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing Diſeaſes, unleſs he hath</hi> from the beginning <hi>been trained up to it, by the conduct of able Profeſſors at
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49471:39"/>home and abroad, and frequently viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Hoſpitals in ſeveral Countries.</hi> p. 15.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>That <hi>Fellow,</hi> that you make ſo ſlight of, is one who ſpends his whole time ſo diligently in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Publick, that you ſhall hardly for your <hi>Jacobus</hi> get one mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute of his time, more than is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary. Indeed he's a worthy Member, and <hi>Fellow</hi> of the <hi>College,</hi> but he is not a Fellow for every ſawcy Jack. He is not made an <hi>Idol</hi> only by the <hi>Vulgar,</hi> but is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely courted and ſought to, by the <hi>Nobility,</hi> and even the <hi>Royal Family;</hi> and his late <hi>Majeſty</hi> of Bleſſed Memory (who could paſs as good a judgment on a Phyſician as perhaps any other Prince) did in his laſt ſickneſs, as I have heard, make Particular Applications to this <hi>Fellow,</hi> as much at leaſt as to any of his other excellent Phyſicians. It is abundantly better to be made an <hi>Idol</hi> in Anatomy by others, than
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:49471:39"/>to make an <hi>Idol</hi> thus pitifully and wretchedly of ones ſelf, as <hi>you</hi> do, <hi>who dare preſume to ſay, I my ſelf have divulged more new Anatomical Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, which are of greater uſe, than all of 'em in a bundle.</hi> Nor is he ſet up for an <hi>Idol,</hi> only <hi>from the falſe ſuggeſtion of Dog-fleying;</hi> he has fley'd not only many a Dog, but many a Man, who perhaps has not half ſo well deſerv'd to be <hi>hanged</hi> for <hi>ſtealing,</hi> or <hi>robbing</hi> a poor Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen pence half penny, as thoſe who make it their trade to <hi>ſteal</hi> away or <hi>rob</hi> the good names of Excellent Men. But the beſt of it is, <hi>the mouths of ſome men are no ſlander.</hi> And ſo that your <hi>falſe ſuggeſtion of Dog-fleying,</hi> will never make this great man the leſs an Anatomiſt, whoſe name is ſpread far and near over the learned World, and much farther than your <hi>Travels,</hi> ſo often boaſted of, could reach. But alas! <hi>He ſhall never arrived to</hi> your <hi>ſagacity of diſtinguiſhing Diſeaſes, unleſs be
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49471:40"/>hath from the beginning been trained up to it, by the conduct of able Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors at home and abroad.</hi> I could ſhew, too clearly to your ſhame, what little <hi>ſagacity</hi> you have in that reſpect, notwithſtanding the multiplicity of your ſcribling, but that I ſhould be guilty of too te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious and troubleſome a diverſion. I could lay before you thouſands of indecencies in expreſſion, and ſuch groſs follies that a School-boy would deſerve to be whipt for 'em. Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that every man of common ſenſe and <hi>Education,</hi> cannot but ſee the greateſt want of <hi>ſagacity</hi> imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, in thoſe leſſer things, and therefore cannot but ſhrewdly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect before-hand your <hi>ſagacity in diſtinguiſhing Diſeaſes:</hi> So that I doubt extreamly, that you have not been <hi>train'd up to it,</hi> as Horſes are to their paces, with a Whip and Bridle; I fear you broke looſe too ſoon, which might occaſion your unproficient wandring into other
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49471:40"/>Countries, <hi>from the beginning.</hi> But, <hi>Momus,</hi> you have e'en condemn'd your ſelf; pray what <hi>able Profeſſors</hi> of the Art <hi>of diſtinguiſhing Diſeaſes</hi> did you learn under <hi>at home?</hi> For we do not now talk of chopping of Logick, but Phyſick Profeſſors. I know you can name plenty of <hi>Profeſſors abroad,</hi> but I defy you to name one <hi>Profeſſor at home,</hi> from whom you learnt <hi>to diſtinguiſh Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,</hi> under <hi>ſeventeen</hi> Years old, your <hi>Year</hi> of <hi>Perfection,</hi> wherein you took the <hi>Degrees both of Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and Doctor.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me tell you, it is a rare and extraordinary thing to be <hi>ripe</hi> ſo ſoon as I was. How Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple will ſtare in a very forward Year to ſee a handful of <hi>green Crabs</hi> at Chriſtmaſs! You may be ſure, that if I had got a knock in my Cradle, I ſhould never have come to this perfection at writing Books; beſides, I was born a Phyſician, and <hi>frequently viſited
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:49471:41"/>Hoſpitals in ſeveral Countries.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me, that you ſhould be a <hi>ſowre Crab</hi> ſo early! You con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm me much inmy opinion, that it is not good nor ſafe to ſend Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from School (where) they are carefull ykept <hi>out of harms way</hi>) to the Univerſity ſo ſoon. Your Friends had better have ſent you to a Manſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Moor-fields,</hi> than to <hi>Exeter Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege,</hi> when they did. No doubt this great error of theirs did occaſion your ſo rank and deſperate a hatred of <hi>Colleges</hi> ever ſince. If you had been kept a while longer under a ſtrict hand, you would not have bragg'd, <hi>that you were born a Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> whereas all others are fain to take great pains to be one, and do tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel over many god Athors, more abundance of them than you did Countries. But the laſt accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment to your Phyſick was, that you <hi>viſited Hoſpitals,</hi> which our Univerſities do want, and therefore can never ſufficiently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:49471:41"/>their Scholars with a <hi>due Education.</hi> We have <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> too in <hi>London,</hi> though not in the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities, and yet we ſeldom hear of Students in Phyſick leaving their Studies, and coming to Town to <hi>viſit</hi> the <hi>Hoſpitals frequently.</hi> 'Tis well, if they <hi>viſit</hi> them once in cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſity, when their other affairs do bring them to Town. For they know well enough that the Practice of Phyſick in <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> is not to be nicely imitated, when they have taken their Degrees, and are Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to practiſe <hi>per totam Angliam.</hi> What, muſt Gentlemen and Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ladies and Oyſter-women be ſerv'd with the ſame coarſe treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? But perhaps the <hi>Hoſpitals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad</hi> have greater vertue in them to edifie and inſtruct young Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. The <hi>Able Profeſſors</hi> there do wonders, and the hearing them prate magiſterially, as if they were reading Lectures without controul in their Schools, may perhaps be of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:49471:42"/>admirable efficacy. No, the moſt that the Scholars do learn from them (as I have been informed) is to give a Clyſter of <hi>Decoctum commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> and <hi>Electnarium Lenitivum,</hi> or to give a large fulſome <hi>Bolus</hi> of <hi>Caſſia,</hi> or <hi>Catholicum,</hi> or to take their <hi>Bouillon</hi> and <hi>Ptiſan.</hi> Truly the practice of <hi>Hoſpitals</hi> in your <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Countries</hi> will not ſo well agree with the humour of our Countrey. <hi>When you are in</hi> England <hi>you muſt do as they do in</hi> England, as when you were in <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>paris,</hi> you might do as they did in <hi>Rome</hi> or <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But that which puts almoſt the laſt hand to render a man a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician 9all others, though they have clambered up to a Degree, are little different from Mountebanks or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlayers) is to be very well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the true Method of Phyſick, or order of applying proper Remedies, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal and external, to Diſeaſes in their juſt time and Doſes.</hi> p. 17.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Some part of this might
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:49471:42"/>paſs indifferently well: only I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but obſerve, that, whatever you may think, there is abundance of probability, you were not your ſelf ſo <hi>very well grounded in the true Method of Phyſick, &amp;c.</hi> I'll give you an inſtance or two of it hereafter. But why ſhould you craftily inſinuate, as if moſt Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giate Phyſicians <hi>clamber'd up to their Degree</hi> (as it is eaſie to ſound the depth of your Intrigues) and ſo you would proclaim to the people (looking another way) that they are <hi>little different from Mountebanks or Man-ſlayers?</hi> I would ask you, which is moſt likely to be the <hi>Clam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berer</hi> to Degrees, he that ſtays at School to ſixteen or <hi>ſeventeen</hi> at leaſt, and then ſtays twelve or fourteen Years at the Univerſity, before he has the Ambition to <hi>think of the Degree</hi> of <hi>Doctor,</hi> or he that at <hi>ſeventeen</hi> (your <hi>Year</hi> of <hi>Jubilee</hi>) has done with Univerſities and Travels, and nothing forſooth can content the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:49471:43"/>Youth, but <hi>both the Degrees of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelor and Doctor?</hi> It was a <hi>Clamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> time of Age you took them in; and more, you were then ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the <hi>Ramble.</hi> So that it is too plain, you had not this <hi>laſt hand, the true Method of Phyſick, to render you a Phyſician,</hi> but <hi>the hand</hi> of ſome Cunning <hi>Doctor</hi> (who knew well enough what he did) was employed firſt in taking your money, and then conferring upon you (who did covet and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to them) the <hi>Titles</hi> of <hi>Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor</hi> and <hi>Doctor;</hi> I warrant, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member'd the <hi>old Adage</hi> in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: <hi>Accipimus pecuniam, &amp; dimitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus Aſinum.</hi> Which I leave to your <hi>Mother-wit</hi> to interpret. And now <hi>difference</hi> your ſelf <hi>from Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banks or Man-ſlayers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And now after all this</hi> Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratus, <hi>we will ſuppoſe our Inſant-Phyſician, his mind gaudily painted and daub'd with the antient, uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and ſome new tickling Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:49471:43"/>in Medicine, &amp;c.</hi> p. 17, 18.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You are ſtill for clapping your childiſh Fools coat of <hi>Infant-Phyſician</hi> upon the back of our <hi>Men of Phyſick.</hi> 'Tis mighty ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to call others in contempt by your own <hi>Proper name.</hi> Of all the Phyſicians, both far and near, that ever I heard of, I never <hi>ſuſpected</hi> one man ſit to cope with you for right of claiming this Title of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant-Phyſician.</hi> Indeed I had thought of the year <hi>one and twenty</hi> before now, but could never have believed (unleſs you had told it in the height of your vanity) that a <hi>lad</hi> of <hi>ſeventeen</hi> could by Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mick Authority be inveſted with the power and care of <hi>other mens lives,</hi> when the Laws of his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey would not truſt him with his <hi>own Eſtate.</hi> Well! But <hi>his Mind</hi> muſt be <hi>ſuppoſed to be gaudily paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and daub'd,</hi> as his Body is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deck'd with Ribbands and fine things, and his Head with a <hi>Feather
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:49471:44"/>in the Cap;</hi> ſo the mind of this <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick-Child</hi> or <hi>Infant</hi> muſt be <hi>gaudily painted</hi> like S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>George</hi> a Horſe-back, and <hi>daub'd</hi> like the Sign-poſt, but with what? <hi>With the antient uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and ſome new tickling Notions in Medicine.</hi> How ſadly therefore ought we to lament the unhappy Date of poor <hi>Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Galen!</hi> their <hi>antient Notions</hi> are all <hi>uncertain,</hi> and not to be depended upon! We have <hi>read</hi> them then to little purpoſe. <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> you muſt be no longer <hi>Divine,</hi> for <hi>the Infant-Phyſician</hi> will have it ſO. For alas! <hi>Momus,</hi> the <hi>new Notions</hi> only are <hi>tickling</hi> to your laſcivious Mind. And why do they <hi>tickle</hi> you? Only becauſe they are <hi>New:</hi> which nevertheleſs I cannot but a little admire, that you ſHould be ſuch a <hi>friend in a corner</hi> to <hi>new No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> when you are ſo declared an Enemy to <hi>new Diſeaſes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now upon application of this Diſcourſe to two or three hundred
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:49471:44"/>Phyſicians, you ſhall ſearce find ſix, tha tcan juſtly pretend to the title of a good Phyſician, or whoſe Education doth hardly qualifie them to be ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred ſuch.</hi> p. 21. and <hi>adding there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, that they are inſufficiently edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, ignorant, inſagacious, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expert (as moſt are) in what a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate caſe are their patients?</hi> p. 22.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Now to me <hi>this Diſcourſe</hi> of yours, without any tedious exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of a deal of Fiddle-ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, but meerly putting it to be tried by the reaſon of your <hi>Mobile</hi> (to whom, and for whoſe ſake, you writ your <hi>Tract</hi>) or by any one of your <hi>able profeſſors at home and abroad; this Diſcourſe, I ſay,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not well avoid the being preſently condemn'd to be burnt by the hands of the common Hangman. For it is a kind of Hereſie in Phyſick as you <hi>apply</hi> it. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon application of it to two or three hundred Phyſicians, you ſhall ſcarce find ſix, &amp;c.</hi> Scarce <hi>ſix!</hi>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:49471:45"/>Indeed you ſHould have allowed us <hi>ſeven</hi> or <hi>eight</hi> at leaſt in civility. the number <hi>ſeven</hi> is by much a more famous number, from the <hi>ſeven</hi> Wiſe men of <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Gotham,</hi> from the <hi>ſeven</hi> Deadly Sins (in which you have ſuch a ſhare) and from its being a <hi>Climacterical</hi> num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Beſides, how many young mens heads are <hi>tickled</hi> with <hi>New Notions,</hi> when they come to the <hi>ſeventh</hi> year of their Prentice ſhip. You know they have priviledges that Year greater than ordinary, and can tell how to fit there <hi>Hats</hi> to their head, nay many of them that year think themſelves <hi>better</hi> men than their <hi>maſters.</hi> And again, the very derivation from <hi>ſeven, ſeventeen</hi> is a number of great note with <hi>you.</hi> It was the remarkable year of your <hi>Aſſumption</hi> of thoſe Titular <hi>Degrees,</hi> and ought never to be forgotten, being the <hi>Clambering</hi> year of all. I ſhall ſay nothing to the other famous derivation from
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:49471:45"/>
                     <hi>ſeven, ſeventy.</hi> Indeed we ſhould have been better contented, if you would have vouchſafed us but <hi>eight good Phyſicians</hi> in <hi>the two or three hundred.</hi> For that is a very <hi>compleat number,</hi> the moſt compleat of all numbers, ſay the <hi>Pythagore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> I dare not inch any further, gueſſing at your ſtingy nature and narrow Soul; a Soul that <hi>Pythago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras</hi> will be puzled to find a body upon the next Tranſmigration, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enough to contract it ſelf in. We'll never diſpute the ſtanding of <hi>a thouſand ſuch Souls</hi> as yours upon the <hi>point</hi> of a <hi>needle. Scarce ſix,</hi> you ſay, <hi>that can juſtly pretend to the Title of a good Phyſician.</hi> No, not <hi>ſix</hi> allowed of, <hi>in two or three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</hi> Pray how came you to be ſo well acquainted with <hi>two or three hundred Phyſicians?</hi> You that have lived in ſuch <hi>Phyſical Obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> that you have never ſhewed your ſelf in the <hi>light</hi> of the <hi>College,</hi> which if you had, you had certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:49471:46"/>been <hi>enlightned</hi> with a better <hi>knowledge</hi> of them, than thus to condemn them all, and more than all, by <hi>dark</hi> and uncertain hearſay. let the Spectators judge who <hi>can</hi> moſt <hi>juſtly pretend to the Title of a good Phyſician,</hi> either they who have chearfully ſubmitted to the <hi>legal teſt</hi> of a <hi>good Phyſician,</hi> the college's Examination, and are thereby <hi>re &amp; nomine</hi> what they pretend; or he that never dared, or never did ſubmit to be tried by his lawful Peers, as to his <hi>abilities,</hi> but got an empty <hi>Title</hi> or Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation (thanks to the <hi>Courteſie</hi> of <hi>England</hi>), to whoop and hollow thus at <hi>bundreds</hi> of worthy Perſons, he knows very little or nothing of. But <hi>their Education doth hardly qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifie them to be rendred ſuch.</hi> And <hi>adding thereunto that they are inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently educated,</hi> &amp;c. How many times muſt we hear of their <hi>mean and inſufficient Education!</hi> And how often muſt your <hi>Tracts</hi> ring of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:49471:46"/>
                     <hi>your</hi> wonderful <hi>Education,</hi> and with a, <hi>read the deſcription of my Education in my</hi> Caſus Med. Chir. <hi>Compariſons,</hi> you might know, <hi>are odious, and</hi> Laus in ore proprio foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet. <hi>You live near</hi> very <hi>ill Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</hi> The good <hi>Education</hi> of our Collegiates is better proved by their Modeſty and Ingenuity, than by Vaunts and Boaſtings; there are very few of them but can tell ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of their Travels, and Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities, as well as <hi>Thraſo</hi> or <hi>Momus.</hi> But it is not their Court faſhion. I ſhall end this tireſome <hi>Rhodomanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do</hi> of yours with your <hi>own</hi> words, which you ought the rather to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, becauſe they are your own; After you had, in your <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Philoſophy,</hi> p. 21. fallen out unmercifully with <hi>John Baptiſta van Helmont</hi> (a perſon that I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected to have found you in love with, for his <hi>ſtrange melancholy</hi> and extravagant Whimſies) and told us of him, that <hi>the Church-yard
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:49471:47"/>was the ſure Regiſter of his Patients,</hi> you adjoin, <hi>His Arrogance and Boastings were ſymptoms of his depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate conceptions.</hi> And ſo I conclude this fulſome, unmannerly, concerit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ridiculous Splutter you make about your <hi>Hogen Mogen E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation:</hi> That your nauſeous <hi>Boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of it is a certain <hi>Symptom</hi> of your <hi>depravate conceptions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay but now <hi>in what a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate caſe are their patients,</hi> they being ſo <hi>ignorant, inſafacious, and inexpert, as moſt</hi> of them <hi>are? But the matter is not much; the greater part of humanity (I ſhould ſay inhumanity) not deſerving a good medicine, Method, or Care of a good Phyſician.</hi> p. 22. And ſo in great wrath and dudgeon I have ended the firſt long Chapter of my <hi>Tract.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>What, <hi>deſinere in piſcem,</hi> end in Wrath, and Anger! But we know you cannot help it, your <hi>head</hi> and <hi>Tail</hi> being all of the ſame Lump. If I might paſs a judgment
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:49471:47"/>upon your <hi>Face</hi> from this <hi>Chapter,</hi> I ſhould think the one ſide of it <hi>paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> with the ſilly Mimick, the other <hi>bedaub'd</hi> with the ſowre <hi>Momus.</hi> You began it with the rude and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper, but ſtill <hi>witty, witty,</hi> intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing <hi>Solomon</hi> to laugh with you as you were <hi>caſting fire-brands</hi> at Phyſicians, and <hi>ſaying, Am I not in ſport?</hi> And now at laſt you turn the other ſide of your Face, and full of anger tell us, that <hi>humanity is inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity,</hi> and that no body hardly <hi>deſerves a good Medicine, Method or Care of a good Phyſician.</hi> Momus, <hi>the matter would not be much,</hi> if the Town and Countrey both were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to want your <hi>care</hi> and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; for it may be much better for many a <hi>humane</hi> Creature to have no Phyſician at all, than ſuch a peeviſh, teſty, unkind, <hi>inhumane</hi> one as he who makes ſo ſlight of <hi>humanity</hi> in general. When he ſpeaks of <hi>humanity,</hi> he ſays <hi>he ſhould ſay inhumanity,</hi> as if there were no
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:49471:48"/>difference between a <hi>Man</hi> and his <hi>Dog.</hi> Come, come, this Town is very well ſtored (to your hearts grief and diſcontent) with <hi>good medicines, good Methods,</hi> and <hi>good Phyſicians,</hi> without any need of learning <hi>good things</hi> from you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſervation ſpeaks this truth; he that dwelleth a long time upon any particular introductory part of Phyſick, ſeldom or never arrives to a conſiderable proficiency in his Art.</hi> p. 23.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Obſervation</hi> alſo <hi>ſpeaks this truth:</hi> An empty veſſel ſounds loudeſt. <hi>Obſervation</hi> ſays likewiſe: A good beginning makes a good ending; or as the Poet, <hi>dimidium facti qui bene coepit, habet.</hi> Now upon application of theſe obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to your caſe, <hi>Momus,</hi> I fear that your <hi>dwelling</hi> ſo <hi>long a time</hi> as you did <hi>upon many particular intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ductory parts of Phyſick,</hi> was the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate cauſe that you <hi>never arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to a</hi> more <hi>conſiderable proficiency
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:49471:48"/>in this Art.</hi> For t' other day in rummageing a Book-ſeller's ſhop to ſee what rarity I could find, I chanc'd to meet with a thick <hi>Quarto</hi> of yours, that I never heard of before, called <hi>Archeologia Philoſophica Nova,</hi> or, <hi>New Principles of Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy.</hi> You had a good opinion of it, no doubt, for you put your <hi>Phiſ-nomy</hi> before it, with your hair comb'd, large Band and Band<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrings, with your Out-landiſh Whiskers, turn'd up <hi>à l' Hiſpaniole,</hi> and a Death's head in your left hand. The Work is full of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>the introductory parts of Phyſick</hi> (with which your head was then <hi>ſtuff'd</hi> as full as ever it could hold) <hi>Philoſophy in general; Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks</hi> or <hi>Ontology; Dynamilogy, or a Diſcourſe of Power,</hi> (not Political but Tautologico-ſcholaſtical) <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio Philoſophi, or Natural Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy,</hi> (dedicated to your Mother, in thanks for your <hi>Mother-wit</hi>) and laſtly, <hi>Phyſicks, or Natural Philoſophy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:49471:49"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>It is a Book that I ſhall never be aſhamed of. <hi>Suſpend your Verdict upon thoſe Writings, until you have peruſed them</hi> twice, <hi>and then if diſreliſhing, diſhering, falſe or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting, to give your ſelf the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of letting me know my Errors in the Senſe of them. But that my further duty may not prove a regret to me, the anſwering of ſuch deſires in</hi> latin <hi>will oblige me to remain, Courteous reader, your Humble Servant.</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Peruſe them twice!</hi> I would not be condemn'd to ſuch a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable drudgery for many a Piſtole. He that reads them <hi>once,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands what he does, will have enough and enough of them, I'll warrant him. Young men eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, I would warn to have a care of theſe <hi>Writings;</hi> and that they may take the more warning, I'll give them a ſmall taſte of the <hi>Ocean</hi> they will there meet with in his <hi>Natural Philoſophy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:49471:49"/>
                  <p>They will learn there,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the</hi> Chaos <hi>had a forme.</hi> p. 11.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The different Effects of the ſeven Knocks of the</hi> Chaos.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What the Catochization of a Flame is.</hi> p. 145.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why a potch'd Egg doth commonly reſt it ſelf in the middle of the water in a Skillet.</hi> p. 66.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why a Kiſs feels pleaſing to ones Lips, and why the ſame delightful feeling happens alſo to a Dog, apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Chops to a Bitches Tail.</hi> p. 201.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Whence it is that a man may carry a greater weight upon a Wheel-barrow than upon his Back.</hi> p. 427.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>How Virginals and Organs are made to play by themſelves.</hi> p. 154.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why a Squib turns into ſo many whirles in the Air.</hi> 38.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why Feathers, Cobwebs, and other light bodies do expand themſelves, when thrown into the Air.</hi> p. 40.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Why a man, whilſt he is alive,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:49471:50"/>ſinks down into the Water, and is drowned, and afterward is caſt up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</hi> p. 105. And there he repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hends <hi>The trying Witches by ſwim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in the water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That Water is not moiſt naturally, neither doth it moiſten.</hi> p. 36.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That the Scent of Excrements ſmels ſweet to a Dog. And that a Dog ſcents a Bitch a great way off, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though lock'd up, without ſeeing of her, and apprehends the Scent under the Tail to be no ill Scent.</hi> p. 197.</p>
                  <p>Now theſe your profound <hi>Phae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomena</hi> being to my dull Apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion very <hi>diſreliſhing, diſ-hering,</hi> and meer Whim-wham, you would have me <hi>give my ſelf the trouble</hi> of expoſing your <hi>Errors in latin.</hi> Without <hi>giving my ſelf that trouble,</hi> (as you eſteem it) the plenty of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curate latin Expreſſions in your <hi>Tract <hi>de Febribus,</hi>
                     </hi> has ſhewed you juſt as good a <hi>latin</hi> Scholar, as your <hi>New Principles of Philoſophy</hi> do ſet you forth for an <hi>Engliſh</hi> one.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:49471:50"/>But however our Mother-tongue be the more proper for expreſſing our Minds at preſent, yet I would not have you to deſpair; for if in good time a fair ocaſion offers it ſelf (as much lies you know in your own power, you being hencefroth upon the good Behaviour) I may think it no ſuch great <hi>trouble</hi> to be the <hi>Courteous Reader's humble Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</hi> with you in <hi>Latin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mon.</hi> Some of theſe <hi>Problemes</hi> may be very divertive to Young men. But I have provided in that Work variety of Entertainment for all ſorts of <hi>Students.</hi> I have confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Renè des Cartes</hi> his Principles in general, and in particular. I have taught <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to define Nature better than he has done. But the ſtrangeſt thing of all is, that I ſhould be able to write ſo large, and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Book in Engliſh, <hi>ſince it was never my fortune to read two ſheets of any Engliſh Book in my Life, or ever to have had the view of ſo much as a ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-leaf
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:49471:51"/>of an Engliſh Grammar.</hi> Preface.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas great pity therefore that you ſhould never have read <hi>Lilly</hi>'s <hi>Qui mihi.</hi> There are nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Documents in it. But we ſee what a man may come to, when left to himſelf betimes. You brought forth a thick <hi>Quarto</hi> at the very firſt attempt! But how came you ever ſince to ſpawn nothing but <hi>Duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimo's,</hi> and <hi>Sexageſimo's?</hi> Sure you found that you had ill luck with <hi>Quarto's,</hi> otherwiſe we could not have miſs'd a <hi>Folio</hi> all this time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I do take that <hi>Quarto</hi> to be the Glory of all my Writings. It was writ like a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. And they, who <hi>peruſed it twice,</hi> as I adviſed them, could not but ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily perceive that I could have writ <hi>Folio's</hi> enough, if I had thought fit. <hi>My chiefeſt deſign ever ſince the ſeventeenth Year of my Age, when I had juſt finiſh'd my courſe in Phyſick, and taken my laſt Degree</hi> (Oh brave
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:49471:51"/>boys!) <hi>conſiſted in elaborating ſuch demonſtrations in Natural Philoſophy, as might ſerve to unfold the nature of Beings in relation to the Art of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, hitherto ſo uncertain, blind and unfounded on Art, that I dare confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently aſſert, &amp;c.</hi> ibid. Pref.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, or you'll make me to work <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. A little at a time, I beſeech you. A man may eaſily ſurfeit of your <hi>demonſtrations,</hi> they are ſo hard of concoction, and apt to lie upon the Stomach. And beſides, if we take too much of them, we ſhall have no room for the Banquet that lies before us, the principal deſign of our preſent meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. You are a man of as much might in <hi>elaborating demonſtrations,</hi> as <hi>Don Quixot</hi> was at encountering Giants and Wind-mills. You are no leſs than a Knight Errant in Phyſick, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to vaſt and daring deſigns, and <hi>as bold as blind Bayard,</hi> at the <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folding the nature of Beings, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> (God bleſs us) <hi>ſo blind and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain,</hi>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:49471:52"/>until all-ſeeing <hi>Bayard dares confidently aſſert,</hi> what in his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and deep Politicks he ſhall think fit. It is in troth a thouſand pities that every conceited ſoft-head ſhould thus be ſuffered to venture upon <hi>removing Mountains</hi> ſo much above their ſtrength, or to <hi>elaborate demonſtrations in Natural Philoſophy.</hi> You ſoared at high and lofty matters from the year you were abſolutely ſpoil'd in, <hi>the ſeventeenth year of your Age,</hi> for ever afterwards; and from <hi>Puer imi ſubſellu</hi> in the Phyſick-Schools, from receiving Dictates to day, nothing forſooth can content your ambitious mind, but the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Doctor in Cathedrâ,</hi> the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Maſters to morrow. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Fate of young <hi>Icarus,</hi> who would not be perſwaded to hearken unto good Counſel. He flew high, as well as you in your younger days. But what came of it? His wings were ſoon melted by the heat of the Sun, as yours are
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:49471:52"/>like to be by any little Degree of heat, by way of anſwer. <hi>Why the</hi> young <hi>man whilſt he is alive ſinks down into the water, and is drowned,</hi> as you have it before, to the juſt terror of over-forward Youths, who ſhall aſpire at ſuch high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as to teach <hi>Cicero</hi> to perform the part of an Orator, <hi>Hannibal</hi> the Art of War, or even <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> how to define Nature, or Grave Profeſſors any thing elſe <hi>in relation to the Art of Phyſick,</hi> or the Science of <hi>Natural Philoſophy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>You may ſave your labour, and counſel thoſe that will hearken to you. But will you take ſo lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle notice of a Book of that mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude? It is worth your <hi>Peruſal</hi> more than you are aware.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, if we muſt loſe ſome more time, let us have your opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Divines,</hi> which made way for your New <hi>Natural Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Divines heavy dull
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:49471:53"/>imaginations hallucinating in the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the Scriptures, like ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral eyes in apparent objects of the Sky, ſome framing this, others that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them. I am not now to be confirmed in my belief that the worſt of Atheiſm is latent in many ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Divines, their ſiniſter ends, cheats, and vile ſecret paſſions of the fleſh, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traying their Hypocriſy. Certainly, were I to pick (out of my own Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion) ſome that were to ſurmount all others in wickedneſs, I ſhould not need long time to ponder upon my Verdict.</hi> Pref. You ſee I am not afraid to <hi>ſhoot my Bolt</hi> at <hi>them</hi> too, for their heavy dull Sentiments in <hi>Theology.</hi> They do <hi>confound their ſmall relicks of Natural Faith into a deteſtable Atheiſm, however cloathed with a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled time-holineſs under their dark habits, to feed their covetouſneſs out of their Benefices.</hi> Ibid.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="100-151" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Fie, fie! doth ſuch <hi>Bil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingſgate</hi> Rhetorick become a man with <hi>Spaniſh Whiskers,</hi> and a <hi>Deaths-Head</hi>
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:49471:53"/>in his hand? And it is the greater aggravation of your fault, that you uſe ſuch bitter expreſſions ſo near the <hi>Title leaf,</hi> and hang them over the Door, that they may be ſeen by all thoſe who have neither leiſure, nor will, to enter into the Work it ſelf. Beſides, it was not well done, to put them for an Introduction to your <hi>Religio Philoſophi,</hi> becauſe they neither contain the Moderation and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of True Religion, nor the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and Sobriety of True Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy. I'll warrant, that pretty <hi>tickling</hi> Title of <hi>Religio Medici</hi> did run to and fro in your head, and you were grievouſly ſorry that it was taken up before. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>I dare confidently aſſert,</hi> you would never have been contented with <hi>Religio Philoſophi.</hi> But if you will give me leave to deliver my <hi>Verdict,</hi> and without <hi>long pondering</hi> upon the Buſineſs, you ought in propriety of ſpeech, to have called
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:49471:54"/>it <hi>Moroſophia Juvenilis,</hi> or <hi>Religio Stulti.</hi> You know I reprehended you a little for abuſing <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Words, and grinning as you did when you made him mingle Nonſenſe. But now in a ſerious mood, deliberate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in <hi>prepenſe Malice,</hi> to call ſo many Divines, without reſtriction, <hi>Cheats,</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites, Blockheads</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> deſerves a more ſevere Correction than an ordinary Repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand. I have ſeen naughty Youths of above <hi>ſeventeen</hi> whipt ſoundly for much leſs faults. Now as for that <hi>detestable</hi> thing called <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> I ſhould think it very ſerviceable for the publick, if all Boys, and Buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foons, inconſiderate Scriblers, and Soft-heads, were ſtrictly prohibited from medling at all with it. For all their weak and ridiculous defences of <hi>Truth</hi> againſt <hi>Atheiſm</hi> do only ſerve to raiſe <hi>Devils</hi> which they have not the <hi>Wit</hi> to <hi>lay</hi> again. And to conclude, I have that juſt veneration for <hi>Holy Perſons,</hi> and
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:49471:54"/>
                     <hi>Holy things,</hi> (which no body ought ſo much as to <hi>play</hi> with, much leſs mortally to <hi>hate</hi>) that I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther e'en ſuffer you (as you did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) to <hi>bewray your own Neſt,</hi> than profanely to meddle with matters of <hi>Theology.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, then let us return and ſee how affairs ſtand with the <hi>Conclave.</hi> There you will <hi>diſcern</hi> that <hi>ſome Phyſicians get a greater Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by killing, than others by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</hi> p. 28.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You know beſt who thoſe <hi>Some Phyſicians</hi> are that have ſuch a cunning knack of <hi>getting reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> They may be your <hi>Particular Acquaintance,</hi> and you ſpeak inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely of them. Indeed <hi>ſome Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians</hi> (who are tried and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enced in their Art, and are known to be through-paced in the Practice of Phyſick) though they may have ſome Patients dye under their hands, let them do their beſt, may yet <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve,</hi> and doubtleſs do <hi>get greater
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:49471:55"/>Reputation</hi> by their excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement and apparent Skill, than others, either deſperate Chymiſts, or profeſſed Empiricks, or other ignorant Undertakers can poſſibly deſerve, though a Patient may have eſcaped under their hands. <hi>Momus,</hi> I do much doubt, for all that we have your word for it, that any inhumane Phyſicians of your Acquaintance do get ſuch mighty <hi>Reputation</hi> by downright <hi>Killing,</hi> and more than our Collegiates do by their <hi>Curing;</hi> take my word for this, that however the <hi>Curers</hi> may for ſome time (as you know <hi>there is a time for all things</hi>) be hindred in gaining their deſerved <hi>Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> yet one <hi>Curer</hi> will at the long run become conſpicuous in the face of the Sun, and in the middle of this great City, when an hundred of your infamous <hi>Killers</hi> muſt be fain to lurk in obſcurity and little corners, not daring to ſhew their heads before the face of the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Curer.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:49471:55"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Some</hi> Phyſicaſters <hi>by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting themſelves</hi> Virtuoſo<hi>'s,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicians, Philoſophers, <hi>and witty</hi> Cracks, <hi>have inſinuated this</hi> Enthymeme <hi>to the Commonalty, that therefore they muſt neceſſarily arrive to the top of their Profeſſion; for ſince their porous Brain was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to imbibe ſuch knotty Myſteries, it's not improbable, they might much eaſier ſuck up the quinteſſence of the Art of Medicine. To this Category belong'd that famed Doctor of</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich, <hi>who being Poſted away from his Houſe with a Coach and Four, to a ſick Gentleman,</hi> &amp;c. p. 49.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Do thoſe <hi>Phyſicaſters</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute themſelves <hi>Virtuoſo</hi>'s, <hi>Mathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticians</hi> &amp;c. as wretched and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful <hi>Scriblers</hi> do <hi>repute them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> good Writers? Or are not thoſe <hi>Virtuoſo</hi>'s, <hi>Mathematicians,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> inſipidly called <hi>Phyſicaſters?</hi> The <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> among all the reſt, that you pitch upon to fleer at is, forſooth, <hi>that famed
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:49471:56"/>Doctor of Norwich,</hi> the very man to whom you were ſo highly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding for furniſhing you with that notable hint of <hi>Religio Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phi,</hi> taken plainly from that leading Card, <hi>Religio Medici.</hi> But it is not fair, that becauſe one excellent Phyſician, a man of ſenſe, did once write a <hi>Religio Medici,</hi> that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore every Sylliton muſt follow the Example, and broach <hi>New Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> or rather <hi>Irreligious Whimſies</hi> to the Worlds end. but why is it that you have ſuch an aking tooth at this ever-famous <hi>Doctor</hi> of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> that City being ſeated ſo much out of the way, and at ſuch a diſtance from <hi>London?</hi> Certainly your mouth water'd at that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince for your Practice; and it is the more likely, becauſe you made two <hi>Stages</hi> of your Practice, in the way towards it, at <hi>Chelmsford,</hi> and at <hi>Ipſwich.</hi> Indeed you did not ſtay long in thoſe places, whether it were that you had ſome final <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuendo's</hi>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:49471:56"/>(as you call them) from the ill-affected Inhabitants to <hi>depart in peace</hi> from among them, or that it be the deſtiny of your trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome life to be always an <hi>Erratick Phyſicaſter,</hi> and upon the Travel, as it is ſaid ſome Phyſicians of old were; though the difference is great be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their Travels and yours: the fame of thoſe old Phyſicians did cauſe them to be <hi>courted</hi> out of one Countrey into another, whereas the miſcarriages of New-fanglers, do make every Country think it a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed riddance to part with 'em. And now let us conſider the pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtory you tell of this Eminent <hi>Doctor.</hi> The catching a <hi>gawdy But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfly</hi> made him loſe ſo much time, that the Patient was dead before he came. Here I obſerve that you make them <hi>hunt the Butterfly ſo long,</hi> that one would think they were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hunting a wild Bore, or a ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Stag, than a poor fluttering But<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfly.
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:49471:57"/>Again, the <hi>Coach-driver</hi> is made to have no more wit, than to leave his <hi>four Horſes</hi> to the wide World, and to go a hunting too over Hill and Dale, after the Fly: And what was the Patient's diſeaſe? A <hi>Syncopal Fit,</hi> or in plain Engliſh, a Swound. Do <hi>Syncopal Fits</hi> uſe to laſt ſo long, whilſt four Horſes can be harneſſed, and ſent to the Doctor, and his coming expected? You ſhew us here your great Skill in Diſeaſes. <hi>Syncope est praeceps omnium virium lapſus:</hi> A Swound is a ſudden failure of the Faculties, both Vital and Animal. The very Pulſe is gone, and the Perſon too for good and all, if there be not ſome Friends by to throw water in his Face, to lay him upon his Back, to pull him by the Hair, to wind his Fingers, and to give him ſome <hi>Cordial</hi> immediately. They are not to fold their hands, and be meer Spectators, waiting for the Doctor's Cordial, and Preſence.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:49471:57"/>If they be ſo ſilly, the Gentleman will be as cold as Marble, long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Doctor can come, let him poſte away as faſt as he will. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs therefore the Doctor was ſent for, by way of prevention againſt the future, not to cure in all haſte the <hi>Syncopal Fit.</hi> So that, <hi>Momus,</hi> you have told a very likely Tale, and the <hi>Virtuoſi</hi> are like to ſuffer much by it.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Mathematician</hi> you fling at, for getting the Reputation of a Great Phyſician upon that account, is really a very extraordinary Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and deſervedly <hi>arrived to the very top of his Profeſſion;</hi> he has approved himſelf not only a <hi>Prime Phyſician,</hi> but a moſt Dextrous Surgeon, he is not only a moſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute Mathematician, but a man of univerſal Learning, and laſtly a moſt accompliſh'd Courtier, and every way very much a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. But becauſe your head is ſhallow, no body's elſe muſt have
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:49471:58"/>any depth; becauſe your <hi>Worm</hi> takes up ſuch a deal of room, <hi>Great Men</hi> muſt not be allowed one ſpare corner, even for the <hi>Mathematicks. Ariſtotle</hi> is ſaid to obſerve, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very idle Coxcomb can make a <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> of one kind or other, but that only curious Wits are capable of learning to purpoſe thoſe <hi>Knotty Myſteries,</hi> the Mathematicks.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> are now-a-days a thing exceeding cheap and common, and though it were once an ineſtimable Jewel, yet it hath been ſo often counterfeited and abuſed by inſipid and fantaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Youngſters, ſcribling <hi>Books</hi> of <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> that there are few of the <hi>Conclaviſts</hi> that will now ſo mightily contend for it. Yet there is one thing, wherein I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but acknowledge them very <hi>Great Philoſophers.</hi> They have for divers years undergone your inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Taunts, and vile Detractions, with a Philoſophical Patience, and
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:49471:58"/>Magnanimity, nay even with a kind of <hi>Stoical Inſenſibility,</hi> when they had Pens among them, which could put you to ſo much confuſion and ſhame; that if you have any ſenſe of Truth, Honeſty, or Honour, you could not avoid <hi>the more than half-hanging your ſelf, rather than un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo</hi> the torment they would put you to.</p>
                  <p>As for your <hi>Witty Cracks,</hi> we ſhall give you free leave (and take it kindly of you) to ingroſs the whole Monopoly of that Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to your ſelf, and your Cronies, if you have any. A <hi>Crack</hi> is a Common Shore of filth and naſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that hath loſt all ſenſe of ſhame or modeſty. She repreſents all good Men to be bad, and bad ſhe makes to be worſe than they are. She is made up of Lyes, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and Hypocriſie; and take this for a Truth, <hi>Whatſoever ſhe ſays is falſe.</hi> Never believe her ſtories, though ſhe ſwears upon her Soul,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:49471:59"/>or her Salvation, or though ſhe does (with you in your Preface) <hi>protest, and call Heaven to witneſs,</hi> to this Wheedle, or to that Untruth. And the <hi>wittier</hi> the <hi>Crack</hi> is, ſo much the more is ſhe to be avoided. For ſhe will pick your Pocket in her Embraces, and her Snares are hard to be diſcovered. She is a dangerous and infectious Creature, and let her paint, or mask it how ſhe will, ſhe'll at laſt make you to find by ſad, though late, Experience (as one of them once told a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of my Acquaintance, who taxed the Damoſel for unkindly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him more than his due) that <hi>if you will fiſh, you muſt catch Frogs ſometimes. How came ſhe by it?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The only ſure way to eſcape the Infection of <hi>Witty Cracks,</hi> is the ſame we obſerve for avoiding the Plague, to fly before them, and not to come near them. For if you will dally and play about their Flame, think it no marvel if your
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:49471:59"/>wings be burnt ſome time or other, and at laſt you meet not with a <hi>gentle,</hi> but virulent and deſtructive <hi>Pox.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But alas! The heads of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalty are apt to be intoxicated with <hi>Enthymems</hi> and Categories, or rather to be puzled with Fuſtian and Bombaſt. You tell them, in pure Nonſenſe, that the <hi>Phyſicaſter</hi>'s <hi>porous Brain is</hi> thought <hi>capable to imbibe Knotty Myſteries,</hi> as if <hi>Knots</hi> were liquid, and the <hi>imbibing,</hi> or drinking <hi>Knots</hi> were as common as drinking the King's Health. And by the ſame Catachreſtical Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phor they <hi>ſuck up the Quinteſſence of Medicine,</hi> whereas it is much ſafer for a Ninny to <hi>ſuck a Bull</hi> than to <hi>ſuck Medical Quinteſſences,</hi> becauſe they are ſo hot in the mouth. Now, <hi>Momus,</hi> you ſee what it is for half-witted people to meddle with <hi>Wit. Wit</hi> is a two-edged Tool, that Fools and Children are abſolutely forbid to play with. If
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:49471:60"/>they do, 'tis ten to one <hi>they cut their own fingers with it,</hi> before they have done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>You have been horrible tedious upon this Paragraph, and will tire a ſober Reader's Patience. I have great variety of divertiſing and curious paſſages for you, and you e'en run your ſelf out of breath upon one thing. Leave this light and whimſical Raillery, and you ſhall hear me preach ſerious and ſober Matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>The field is ſo large and fruitful, that I cannot help expati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating in it. A tolerable good Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician will draw ſome good out of any ill Plant, and you are well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with <hi>that trite Aphoriſm</hi> (though you know beſt, who made it an <hi>Aphoriſm</hi>) <hi>viz. that there is nothing ſo hurtful or poiſonous, be it Spider or Toad, but hath it's uſe.</hi> p. 97. And ſo you muſt give me leave to provide you ſome good and beneficial Inſtructions, though the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:49471:60"/>Subject be never ſo bad. Why, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Paragraph could ſpin out into a laudable <hi>Duodecimo,</hi> or <hi>Sexageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> if there were not ſuch an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of new matter preſſing ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly for admittance. Therefore let us hear you preach ſome ſober ſerious buſineſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thoſe who ſhall have liſted themſelves in the Service of the great God, and by aſſuming Orders, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh themſelves from the Laity; exerciſing that most honourable Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, by praying, preaching, and their exemplary Life and Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the glory of their great Maſter, and the ſaving of Souls from Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, thoſe I ſay that ſhall do this only for a time. &amp;c.</hi> p. 57, 58.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſs me! That ſuch good Words ſhould drop out of ſo foul a mouth! That a man who ſo late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly profaned God's Prieſthood, and called the Divines <hi>Cheats, Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> ſhould now ſo ſtrangely transform himſelf into a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:49471:61"/>
                     <hi>precious Saint! that moſt honourable Function, the great God, their great Maſter, and the ſaving of Souls from Perdition:</hi> Theſe are very ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious words, and ought not to be uſed in Maſquerade. Doubtleſs you would never have thus lifted up your Eyes to Heaven, proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Faſt, and made this Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; unleſs the murthering ſome man's Reputation were very near. <hi>Momus,</hi> this Nation has ſuffered too much already from the Intrigues and Deſigns, and the direful Effects of Hypocritical Canting. We ſhould as ſoon believe <hi>Hugh Peters <hi>Incarnate again,</hi>
                     </hi> as give any credit to you, when you preach Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But tell me, what miſchief is now upon the Anvil, and againſt whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>It is againſt one, who <hi>(Scelus horrendum!) from the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Miniſtery,</hi> betook himſelf <hi>to the Exerciſe of Phyſick.</hi> Do you think that I (who could be heartily
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:49471:61"/>contented that there were no Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians at all, and with whom it has been a Maxim a good while, The fewer Phyſicians the better:) think you that I can endure with Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that other Profeſſions ſhould thus dare to treſpaſs upon their Neighbours Copy-hold, or <hi>Fee?</hi> My Wrath riſes at ſuch men, let them be never ſo Learned.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You are much in the right, <hi>Momus,</hi> in what you ſaid laſt, yet it was much to the Glory of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that he was <hi>ex utroque Caeſar,</hi> that be had both the Pen of an Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Orator, and could write curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Commentaries with it; and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that he had a keen and invincible Sword, with which he cut down all his Superiours, and eſtabliſhed himſelf in the Imperial Throne. The Soul and the Body are linked together in a moſt ſtrict Union, and in all likelihood the Phyſicians of the Soul have full as hard, if not a harder Task, to cure mens
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:49471:62"/>Vices, and correct their Manners, than Phyſicians of the Body can have to cure their Diſeaſes, and purge their Bodies from peccant humours. But yet the Perſon you mean has proved no ſhatter-brain in the Faculty of Phyſick, nor has he ſpent his time to little purpoſe, like an unſteady <hi>Rambler;</hi> he has taken his <hi>Doctor</hi>'s <hi>Degree</hi> where you were once, to their ſhame and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Matriculated.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Can it be imagined, that one who had for ſeveral years mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Pulpit, ſhould to increaſe his Fame in Phyſick, be guilty of ſo pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable an Impoſture, as to aſſert pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly, that by giving ſix grains of Salt of Ambar, he had cauſed a Drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Patient to piſs the meaſure of a Kilderkin? In ſhort,</hi> libera nos <hi>from thoſe that practiſe Phyſick</hi> in Nomine Domini. <hi>p.</hi> 62, 63.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>This wild Freak, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable <hi>Chimaera, can hardly be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined</hi> by any but <hi>Momus</hi> himſelf.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:49471:62"/>You may as well <hi>publickly aſſert,</hi> that it has rained Nuts and Suggar-plums, or that you can cure all incurable Diſeaſes with a wet Finger, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the World that a man of ſenſe, eſpecially a <hi>Phyſician of the Conclave,</hi> ſhould thus ſillily talk of <hi>curing Dropſies.</hi> The true State of the caſe, according to the beſt information I have of it, is thus: This Phyſician, and another of the ſame <hi>Confederacy,</hi> joined in Conſultation, upon a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient that had been troubled with the <hi>Strangury,</hi> and who had hardly made any water in nine or ten days, did adviſe the taking <hi>Salt of Ambar,</hi> among other things; not <hi>ſix grains,</hi> as you ignorantly pronounce, but more than three times ſix, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated Doſes. The things he took did open the Tap, and ſet the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a running, not to a <hi>Kilderkin</hi> (you might as well have ſaid to a Tunn) but to about a <hi>Gallon,</hi> which was much to the Patient's Eaſe, as well as the mirth of ſneering Buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoons.
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:49471:63"/>This was the Foundation upon which you built this pretty contrivance of a ſtory, wherein you miſtook unconſcionably the Patient's Diſeaſe, the Remedy and the Effect. And by ſuch groſs or wilful miſtakes in one Caſe a man may judge of your Candour and Sincerity in the reſt. But, <hi>in ſhort,</hi> you are not for <hi>libera nos <hi>from thoſe that practiſe Phyſick</hi>
                     </hi> in <hi>Romi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Domini,</hi> you are altogether <hi>for thoſe that practiſe Phyſick</hi> in <hi>Romine Diaboli.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon thoſe, that lay ſo weighty a ſtreſs on their Opiniator Methods, ought to be impoſed a Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to</hi> Ruſſia, <hi>there to exerciſe their Galeniciſms upon the Boyars, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of their next ſubordinate quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who receive Phyſick from the hands of their Medico's upon no other condition or terms, than if the Pills, Potions, Powders, and Bleedings, have not the pretended ſucceſs, thoſe that adviſed them, are to juſtifie the
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:49471:63"/>rationality and experience of them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own Bodies, in a double pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion. As thus: A noble Patient having by three or four Bleedings re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a palpable prejudice, or poſſibly his untimely diſpatch into the other World, the adviſing Phyſician for a puniſhment of his unwarrantable and unskilful raſhneſs, is to be blooded ſix or eight times, &amp;c.</hi> p. 76, 77.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſort of Medical Hotch-potch are you made of, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> that thus unwittily talk of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piniator Methods,</hi> and <hi>Galeniciſms.</hi> Ever now and then you beſprinkle your <hi>Tracts</hi> with the venerable Name of <hi>Galen,</hi> and would hint as if you were not a little vers'd in his <hi>Methods</hi> and Writings, but now they are all <hi>Galeniciſms,</hi> and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Soleciſms, as the <hi>Worm</hi> will have it. Neither the Novelties of <hi>Helmontius,</hi> or <hi>Renè des Cartes</hi> pleaſe you at all, nor the antient <hi>Methods</hi> of <hi>Galen,</hi> which have paſs'd the Teſt and Approbation of ſo
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:49471:64"/>many ages. New and Old, Jeſt and Earneſt, Right or Wrong, are all alike Bad, when <hi>Momus</hi> in his Dream ſtumbles upon them. And who is the greater <hi>Opiniator?</hi> Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Galen,</hi> who was ſo modeſt, that he never put his Name (much leſs his Picture) before any of his Books, as you may read in his ſeventh Book, <hi>de Methodo Medendi;</hi> or <hi>Momus</hi> who writes his <hi>Name</hi> to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Tract</hi> in Great Letters, and who one while writes himſelf <hi>Phyſician in Ordinary to his Majeſty, and in the time of the Rebellion, Fellow of the College of Phyſicians at the</hi> Hague (thanks to his Mother's <hi>Bohemian</hi> Intereſt) another while he ſtyles himſelf (after his Name in Great Letters) <hi>Med. Spag. Dogm. Chir. &amp; Phil. D.</hi> perhaps in imitation of <hi>Dn. Aureol. Philip. Theophraſt. Bom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bast. ab Hoenhaim,</hi> or <hi>Paracelſus.</hi> To day he tells you his Name, with plain <hi>M. D.</hi> without a word of his Degree of <hi>Batchelor;</hi> to morrow
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:49471:64"/>he is only <hi>Phyſician in Ordinary to His Majeſty,</hi> and not a word of <hi>the College at the</hi> Hague. So that, <hi>Momus,</hi> you are always at variance even with your own <hi>Titles.</hi> A Lad at School ſhall have ſomething to do, to turn and wind a <hi>Golden Verſe</hi> into Changes, ſo often as you can do your <hi>Gilded Titles.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Every Body can't <hi>vary the Phraſe,</hi> as I have had the Honour to do, in the <hi>Title-Leaf.</hi> But what think you, would not that excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Cuſtom of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> if practiſed here, make our <hi>Galenists</hi> to quit the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Stage, and to travel, as I have done, into other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You are groſly ignorant, I perceive, of the State of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> or elſe abominably malicious. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I ſhall give my ſelf the trouble to inform you a little. The <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites</hi> have ſo fond an opinion of the Phyſicians Skill, that they do make him to be <hi>Infallible,</hi> and <hi>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent</hi>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:49471:65"/>in his way, and if a Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent miſcarry, they impute it to his want of <hi>will</hi> to ſave the man, and not to Nature, or the defect of Art. Hence ſome of them, as being bred meer Barbarians, and being all ignorant in any point of Learning, may perhaps paſs ſome indignities upon their Phyſician, when he does not fully anſwer their groundleſs Expectation. But that conceit of yours, their making the Phyſician <hi>to bleed a double quantity himſelf,</hi> and <hi>the ſwallowing down double the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of a Purge he gives,</hi> when it has not the deſired effect, I do take to be the pure invention of <hi>Momus,</hi> who cannot for his life tell a ſtory as he ſhould do, but has the frail memory of common Liars, and ſo adulterates every Truth he hears with ſome groſs alloy of Falſhood. It is no new thing for the beſt Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician to meet ſometimes with an unworth treatment. And ſo <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper Alpinus de Medicin. Aegypt.</hi>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:49471:65"/>lib. 1. cap. 3. tells us how Phyſick came to degenerate there from the Rational Antient Methods into a meer obſequiouſneſs, and the treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or flattering Symptoms, inſtead of encountering the Cauſes of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes, as <hi>Galen</hi> teaches to do in his 9<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Book <hi>de Meth. Med. Hic cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptus medendi modus non à priſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum illorum medicorum ignorantiâ principium duxit, ſed ut ex Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is hiſtoriarum peritis audivi, à bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barâ priſcorum Aegypto imperantium tyrannide; tempore enim quo Mama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luchi illiuſce regionis obtinebant im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perium, omnia ea loca Medicis doctiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimis florebant, qui dogmaticê ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mâque cum ratione medicinam facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant, ſed tanta erat ea in dominis barbaries, ut optimi illi doctiſſimique medici vel rebus benè geſtis ſaepè lucri loco ab iis contumeliis afficerentur. Illorum aliquis dolore aliquo corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptus non ſecùs quàm furens bestia, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitò ut ſanaretur imperabat, quod cùm non ſemper ita citò eveniret, peſſimè
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:49471:66"/>miſeros eos Medicos tractabat. Alpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> has in the ſame place much more to the ſame purpoſe. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> (without the <hi>impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of a <hi>Voyage</hi> thither) although ſome particular brutiſh <hi>Bojar</hi> (who perhaps knows no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a Pearl and a Pebble, and who probably is not ſo well civili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed as a Boore or a Peaſant in the Southern parts of <hi>Europe</hi>) may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly have been as rude as a Bear, and as unmannerly to his Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, as the <hi>Author of the Conclave</hi> is to the Faculty of Phyſick; yet the <hi>Czars,</hi> or Emperors of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> have more than once applyed themſelves to our Princes, to beg the Favour of a Phyſician from hence. In Quene <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time the Fame of our Learned and Skilful Collegiates had ſo far reached the Ears of the <hi>Czar,</hi> that he ſent Letters on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to that Great Queen, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech her, that ſhe would ſend him a <hi>Phyſician to his Perſon.</hi> And the
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:49471:66"/>
                     <hi>Queen</hi> ſent him Doctor <hi>James,</hi> a <hi>Fellow</hi> of the <hi>College,</hi> with a Royal Letter, in which, among others, are theſe words. <hi>Quòd hominum genus</hi> (meaning Phyſicians) <hi>quoniam &amp; plurimarum rerum cognitionem, &amp; morum probitatem non vulgarem po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulat; Noluimus vel non parum pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidae eſſe ſalutis tuae, vel negligenter honoris noſtri, quin virum tàm probi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis laude inſignem, quàm cognitionis in re medicâ, uſâſque laude com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendatiſſimum, ad te mitteremus, eáque propter è domeſticis, è noſtris ex eorum numero, qui corporis ſalutis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que noſtrae, ſecundum Deum, cuſtodes ſunt,</hi> Robertum Jacob. <hi>in Medicinâ Doctorem, virum literatum artis ſuae peritiſſimum, morum honeſtate proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimum, ad te mittimus; non quia libenter eo careremujs, ſed quoniam ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi, tanguam nobis volumus &amp; cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus facere benè: Eum ut pari cum gratiâ à nobis accipias, &amp; honore me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rito proſequaris, etiam atque etiam ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Annals</hi> of the <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:49471:67"/>do mention others afterwards ſent thither on the ſame account, whither there would hardly have ventured a <hi>Second</hi> after the <hi>Firſt,</hi> if they had not known how to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue men, under God ſo exceedingly uſeful. The Learning of the <hi>Ruſſians</hi> goes no farther than to write and read in their own Language. And he that can do that, is a great Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lard among them. One of our ſorry Aſtrologers, who has Skill e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to underſtand an <hi>Ephemeris,</hi> and thence to read and foretel the time of the Moon, and Eclipſes, ſhall infallibly be eſteemed a <hi>Conju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer,</hi> and a dealer in the Black Art. They think there is more Wiſdom in the Beard than the Word of him that has a Beard, than the Oath of a ſmooth-fac'd Gentleman. They will write upon their Knees, though a Table ſtands before them. They are a ſavage, ſottiſh, ſhameleſs peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, (as <hi>Olearius</hi> tells us) and can
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:49471:67"/>never learn any good of their Neighbour-Countries, becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Ruſs</hi> is forbid upon ſevere penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to travel, or ſee Faſhions abroad; and if any Rambler has not the wit to hold his tongue, but muſt be blabbing what fine things he has ſeen without doors, his <hi>Tongue</hi> ſhall moſt certainly be cut out, that he may tell no more Tales. The beſt of it is, they are of a healthy and ſtrong Conſtitution, and are ſeldom ſick, Drunkenneſs excepted. When they are, Garlick and Strong-waters are all their Remedies (even in a Feaver) becauſe they know no better. But now their <hi>Bojars</hi> begin to know the happineſs of having a good Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, and can diſtinguiſh well enough between ſuch a one a Mounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bank, who will commonly let down his Breeches before them, and ſhew all he has to the Multitude, in order to recommend his other Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I have enough and enough of theſe <hi>Muſcovians,</hi> but after I had
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:49471:68"/>flung my Wild-fire to frighten my Conclave-Enemies, I gave you a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moire of fatal Memory. <hi>But did the publick good ſo much influence any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt judicious Phyſician, as to become an Obſervator of ſuch Methodiſts; in the ſpace of a year he might exceed a Volume larger than the</hi> Septuagints; <hi>but then for that term it's neceſſary he ſhould have a</hi> Sauve-garde, <hi>to ſave his Brains from being knock'd out.</hi> p. 79.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I know your beloved Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im: <hi>Fling dirt enough, and ſome will ſtick;</hi> and know from whom you learn'd it in your Travels. We fear no juſt and honeſt <hi>Obſervator.</hi> Such an <hi>Obſervator</hi> is one that has wit and ingenuity in abundance. He writes good ſenſe and appoſite words, and ſcorns to rake the Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel for abominable and filthy ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries to abuſe and beſpatter his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors. In a word, he is ſo conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with himſelf, that let him write never ſo many <hi>Volumes,</hi> he will defie <hi>Momus</hi> to convict him of
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:49471:68"/>
                     <hi>one</hi> plain <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntruth.</hi> We know like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, what a long and hard Labour you had to bring forth the <hi>Firſt Part of your Conclave,</hi> and what Pain and Gripes you have endur'd about it, ever ſince the Publication of your <hi>Caſus.</hi> There in the Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of your Unfortunate, and ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſtowed <hi>Education</hi> you give us in Short-hand an <hi>Abbregè</hi> or Embryo of this illſhapen Monſter; you told us there in few words the greateſt part of thoſe unlikely ſtories, which were in time, and with good huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandry, to grow into a diſtinct Pamphlet. But conſidering how large the Town is, and how wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling many an angry Nurſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded Apothecary, or diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Melancholick Patient, might prove to furniſh ſcandalous matter for your premeditate and long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intended purpoſe; certainly you had but very little Intereſt, or Power, and would find it a harder task than you think it, to take
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:49471:69"/>together a ſufficient number of ſcandalous Aſperſions, in order to equal, much leſs <hi>exceed a Volume larger than the</hi> Septuagints, <hi>in the ſpace of a year.</hi> Eſpecially if you do take the <hi>Septuagints</hi> to be <hi>ſeventy Volumes,</hi> as perhaps you may. But it may be you might have taken the hint of the <hi>Septuagints</hi> from its dear Relation to the <hi>Year ſeventeen,</hi> the Year of Triumph, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyful Memory, for ſake of thoſe early <hi>Degrees</hi> of yours, <hi>both of Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelor and Doctor.</hi> Again, What great matter is there in your <hi>Second Part of the Conclave,</hi> beſides <hi>Cram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be his costa,</hi> the ſame jarring Tune grateing ingenious Ears over again, a little more ſtuff of the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> of which it is very eaſie to collect enough to make a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, after ſo much written, as there is, by the <hi>French,</hi> and others, concerning it. Then indeed you ſhew your <hi>Wit</hi> as well as <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> in moſt ſhamefully perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:49471:69"/>the Ghoſt of the late Glory of Phyſick, Dr. <hi>Willis. De mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is nil niſi benè,</hi> ſay we; but with you it is, <hi>Nil niſi malè tm de mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuis quàm vivis.</hi> After this, you add almoſt <hi>four leaves</hi> of Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, on the <hi>five leaves</hi> in the <hi>Firſt Part,</hi> which are ſaid <hi>to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the chief Subject of this Treatiſe;</hi> all the reſt being doubtleſs very impertinent, or at leaſt of mean concern, in compariſon with the <hi>Chief-ſubject.</hi> Next, you give the Apothecaries more of your Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection than they deſerve, which muſt needs cauſe a very ſtrange Wonderment in any one, that does not conſider it is Kindneſs of <hi>Momus</hi> his beſtowing. After which, you entertain us with a long Story of a Lady, which ſingle Story you call in the Title of the Chapter, <hi>Some eminent Caſes in Phyſick.</hi> Now if it were ſo eaſie as you would hint, <hi>to exceed a Volume larger than the Septuagints,</hi> with your ſcurrilous,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:49471:70"/>and often profane Ribaldry, you would not ſerve us as you do, fill our expectations with <hi>ſome eminent Caſes in Phyſick,</hi> and at laſt put us off with <hi>one only Caſe</hi> and no more.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But then</hi> (if you ſhould write ſo <hi>large</hi> a <hi>Volume</hi>) <hi>for that term</hi> (or rather for that piece of Nonſenſe) <hi>it's neceſſary youſhould have a Sauve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, to ſave your Brains from being knock'd out.</hi> No, no! <hi>Momus,</hi> you need not fear the <hi>knocking</hi> out of that which you never had, or loſt long agoe. Your <hi>Skull</hi> is <hi>thick</hi> enough to defend you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Knocks,</hi> and eſpecially of ſuch who uſe only <hi>Argumenta Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenica,</hi> not <hi>Bacilina.</hi> We never order <hi>Madmen</hi> to be <hi>knock'd</hi> o'tho' head, but to be tyed and bound faſt enough, and to be kept in ſafe Cuſtody that they may do no more miſchief, either to themſelves, or others. And, <hi>Momus,</hi> I dare ingage, that's all you need fear from our <hi>Actions of the Caſes</hi> how
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:49471:70"/>large a <hi>Volume</hi> ſo ever you ſcribble, <hi>Of eminent Caſes in Phyſick.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I am not only of opinion, but poſſibly certain,</hi> &amp;c. p. 83.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>We ſhall not have room for all your odd <hi>Opinions,</hi> and <hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Certainties;</hi> or rather plain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties. We ſhould run into <hi>a Volume larger than the Septuagints,</hi> if we ſhould undertake to examine the truth of all your idle <hi>Opinions,</hi> and uncertain poſſibilities; or your Whimſical Conceits, frequent Inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herences, pert and dul Expreſſions, and the groſs Errors you commit, even in your own Mother-Tongue. This is not poſſibly the laſt time you and I may meet. And I would have ſome pity upon the Reader, not to overcharge him too much at a time; leſt he ſhould come to nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeate the very ſight of ſuch courſe and inſipid Fare, as you do help us to. Give us ſome of your Certain <hi>Concluſions,</hi> which you have drawn (by head and ſhoulders) from
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:49471:71"/>the beſt of your Obſervation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then, <hi>I may justly conclude, among a hundred Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans you ſhall find ninety five learned Mountebanks, and poſſibly five Real Phyſicians.</hi> p. 85.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>The whole Body of the <hi>College</hi> does not yet make up the Number of <hi>a hundred Phyſicians,</hi> ſo that (to fill up) we would admit one ſcabbed Sheep into the ſound Flock, in hopes to cure him. But where to place you, I know not. Sure you will not have the impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to pretend to a Place among the <hi>five Real Phyſicians;</hi> and as for the <hi>Learned Mountebanks,</hi> in troth you have not yet deſerved ſo good a <hi>Title.</hi> For it is no great point of Learning to reſolve <hi>Phaenomena</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Wheel-barrows</hi> and <hi>Potch'd Eggs,</hi> to deſcant upon the <hi>Whirles of Squibbs,</hi> or <hi>the Expanſion of Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Cobwebs;</hi> but eſpecially about the <hi>Application of a Dog's Chops to a Bitches Tail,</hi> or to expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:49471:71"/>and give deep Reaſons <hi>why a Dog apprehends the Scent of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements under the Bitches Tail to be no ill Scent.</hi> Theſe nice points might do very well for a <hi>Merry-Andrew,</hi> but can by no means become the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur and Dignity of a <hi>Learned Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebank. Learning</hi> is a thing of great Value and deſerved Eſteem, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Unlearned. It is a <hi>Rarity</hi> too in my Opinion, and unleſs we look after <hi>True Learning</hi> among <hi>a hundred Phyſicians,</hi> I cannot tell where to find it in ſuch plenty among <hi>a hundred</hi> of any other Profeſſion. You <hi>conclude</hi> then, that there are <hi>Ninety five Learned Men</hi> in the <hi>hundred Phyſicians,</hi> but your kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, bitter as well as ſweet, they muſt be <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks</hi> forſooth! Prithee which are moſt like <hi>Mountebanks,</hi> either thoſe Modeſt, Learned, Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and Experienced Men, who never vaunt and boaſt more than they can do, but often do more
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:49471:72"/>than they ſay; or he that <hi>dares pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to ſay, <hi>I my ſelf</hi> have divulged more new Anatomical Obſervations, which are of greater uſe, than all of 'em in a Bundle.</hi> See Preface, and who, p. 100. preſumes to ſay, <hi>I dare undertake <hi>in a Weeks time, to inform the most illiterate Capacity, having but an ordinary Memory, how to manage thoſe five Courſes</hi>
                     </hi> (before mentioned) <hi>with a better Method, and far greater Succeſs, than any of theſe Anatomical Pretenders ever were fortuned with.</hi> And <hi>I can eaſily make it appear, <hi>that it is poſſible to comprehend as many plain and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Inſtructions, Rules, and Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies in one ſingle Sheet, that by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of them, any man without other advice may in moſt Caſes cure himſelf, with far greater ſafety, ſpeed, and ſucceſs, than the beſt of the Pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to Anatomy could ever yet chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, or lay claim unto.</hi>
                     </hi> Ibid.</p>
                  <p>Here you have outdone <hi>Theſſalus</hi> himſelf, that <hi>moſt impudent</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:49471:72"/>as <hi>Galen</hi> calls him, and gives us an account of him in his firſt Book <hi>de meth. medendi,</hi> a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject you are often apt to talk of. This brazen-fac'd Empirick <hi>was grown to that heighth of folly and raſhneſs, at</hi> Rome, <hi>that he proclaim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he could teach the whole Art of Phyſick in half a Years time, without mens applying themſelves to any other ſtudy, or learning any thing more. Wherefore Coblers, Diers, Carpenters, and Smiths, being enticed by his bold and eaſie pretences, did at that time, ſays</hi> Galen, <hi>whole crowds of them leave their Handycrafts, and under that Maſter did betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to phyſick (which ought to have been moſt Sacred to ſuch men) to the deſtruction of Mankind.</hi> What would that great Phyſician have ſaid, think you, if he had heard of your <hi>dare undertake in a Weeks time</hi> at <hi>London,</hi> and of your <hi>one ſingle ſheet,</hi> wherein you ſay, <hi>you can eaſily make it appear, that any
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:49471:73"/>man may by you be taught in moſt caſes to Cure himſelf with far greater ſafety, ſpeed, and ſucceſs, than the beſt of the pretenders to Anatomy could ever yet challenge, or lay claim unto:</hi> Whereas that through-pac'd admirable Phyſician, in the Book aforeſaid, uſed the very argument of <hi>Anatomy</hi> againſt <hi>Theſſalus</hi> his ſhameful pretences, urging that all Philoſophers, and knowing men, did with one conſent agree, that no man could be able to Cure Diſeaſes, nor had any right to offer at it, until he had firſt ſearch'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>the nature of the whole Body,</hi> by underſtanding its <hi>Anatomy.</hi> Now though <hi>half a year</hi> be a very ſhort time for <hi>Carpenters, Diers, and Smiths, to learn the whole Art of Phyſick,</hi> you have out-ſhot him exceedingly, who can <hi>in one ſingle ſheet, and in a Weeks time,</hi> teach <hi>any man</hi> ſtranger things than all the Empiricks before you. One word more: though <hi>Theſſalus</hi> did
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:49471:73"/>(as you now do) ſpeak mighty things of himſelf, and in an Epiſtle he writ to <hi>Nero,</hi> had theſe arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant expreſſions: <hi>Seeing that I do make a new Sect of Phyſicians, and the only one of all that is true, becauſe all the Phyſicians who have been before me, have writ nothing that is uſeful, either to the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Health, or the Cure of Diſeaſes.</hi> And afterwards ſays he, <hi>Hippocrates has taught pernicious Principles.</hi> At this rate did that Rhodomontado then yelp againſt Phyſicians, and though he did crack and bounce (as you will needs now do) yet what is become of his <hi>Communitates</hi> and <hi>Syncritica,</hi> &amp;c. They are all gone, periſhed and forgot. We ſhould never have heard of the Wretch by his own Writings, unleſs <hi>Galen</hi> had thought fit to give a check to his preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by vouchſafing to expoſe his folly to Poſterity. Now you, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> muſt expect a worſe fate of
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:49471:74"/>Oblivion; for though you have provoked with tooth and nail the <hi>Galens,</hi> as well as the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> of our time, to take notice of your malevolent and ſcurrilous Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets againſt the Faculty, yet you ſee none of thoſe great men will do you that Honour, looking on your rage and madneſs with more Contempt than Anger. I would adviſe you to write your next Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject againſt Phyſicians in <hi>Latin,</hi> and if you follow the Copy of that pure, elegant, ſmooth, and oh how excellent Pattern of that <hi>nonpareil de Febribus,</hi> you will give the greater diverſion; however take your own way, write either in your own ſtyle, having a care of <hi>Priſcian</hi>'s head; or after that indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent good Latiniſt, <hi>Thomas Willis</hi> his ſtyle, I'll promiſe you for your Comfort, you ſhall be <hi>anſwered in Latin</hi> (the thing you once long'd for) and if the beſt Pens be too buſie to mind you, you ſhall have
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:49471:74"/>your <hi>Match</hi> at leaſt, a Pen (don't you doubt) as good as your own, and of a <hi>Galemſt</hi> too, a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirer of excellent men, a natural Enemy both to Fopps and turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Spirits, and yet one who will give even a <hi>Devil in Phyſick</hi> his Due.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>But is not that a great matter for a lonely ſolitary man, who ſo ſeldom ſees the face of any <hi>Real Phyſician,</hi> and who ſcorns to have any Knowledge of them; is it not a mighty matter that he ſhould thus be able to teach all the World out of his own <hi>ſimple</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, it would be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful ſtrange, if <hi>Sir Politick</hi> ſhould among his other Concluſions, draw as <hi>Army of forty Thouſand Men</hi> out of the Ventricles of his Brain, and muſter them in his Bed-Chamber, whilſt a Man can crack a Nut. It would be a wonderful matter if a Lad ſhould write good Latin, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:49471:75"/>he can ſpeak common Senſe; but eſpecially if a Child ſhould at <hi>ſeven</hi> years old, or a Boy <hi>before ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venteen</hi> (the year that it has been done in, to our everlaſting aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment) ſhould, becauſe he crys and roars, be dubb'd <hi>Batchelor</hi> and <hi>Doctor,</hi> in order to make him quiet. What ſtrange Phyſical <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections</hi> ſuch young and early <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> might in time bring about, I cannot well comprehend; but we that have been of a ſlower growth, and who have learned long ſince (not from you, who do <hi>cant</hi> it impertinently in the beginning of your firſt Chapter of the <hi>Conclave</hi>) that <hi>Life is ſhort, and Art is long:</hi> We know the <hi>Art</hi> of Phyſick to be a much <hi>longer</hi> buſineſs, than to be any ways <hi>comprehended in one ſingle ſheet:</hi> As we know, that every thing is not <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which a <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebank comprehends</hi> in his Printed Paper of Directions. You cannot but know better things too, but
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:49471:75"/>your Spleen works into your Head, and ſuggeſts many ridiculous Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick Whimſies, which ought to be imputed to your Diſtemper, and is the true cauſe that your Pen runs ſo faſt before your Wit. But give your reaſon, why you thus condemn very unmercifully <hi>ninety five of a hundred Phyſicians</hi> to be only <hi>Learned Mountebanks.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They are thoſe falſe Metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſts, who boaſt, that with Opium and Jeſuits Powder, they can Cure all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. Neither are they advanced to a much higher form, that imagine ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Diſpenſatories are ſufficiently ſtockt with Medicines adequate to the Cure of all Diſeaſes, whereas they contain ſew others, than ſuch as may ſerve for vehicles for greater Medicines, or are only virtuated to remove ſlight ſuperſicial Diſtempers. Whence I may juſtly conclude,</hi> &amp;c. as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, p. 84, 85.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ex ore tuo te judico.</hi> Once more I muſt return to conſult the
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:49471:76"/>
                     <hi>Preface</hi> (before-mentioned) to your <hi>Tract</hi> of the <hi>Scurvy, the Diſeaſe of</hi> London, as you call it, though I doubt you can give no great reaſon to Philoſophers, why the <hi>Scurvy</hi> ſhould be more <hi>the Diſeaſe of</hi> Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, than other Places, eſpecially the <hi>Maritime Towns.</hi> Only you cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culated that <hi>Tract</hi> for the Meridian of <hi>London,</hi> to tempt <hi>Londoners</hi> to take good notice of the <hi>Authors Name,</hi> and <hi>Titles,</hi> and to give them a hint what notable help they might expect from this Man of Might, who is able to write a Book about it, and can teach o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers how to Cure this reigning <hi>London-Diſeaſe.</hi> But firſt, who are <hi>they,</hi> and <hi>thoſe falſe Methodists, who boaſt</hi> ſuch ridiculous and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable things? I openly challenge you to name one Man of the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave,</hi> or any other related to it by the way of Domeſtick <hi>Degrees,</hi> who has been ſo vain and ſilly, as to <hi>boaſt, that with</hi> Opium <hi>and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:49471:76"/>Powder, he can cure all Diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.</hi> This I can tell you, from an Eminent Druggiſt, who is beſt able to judge, what vent there is of Druggs, that he has not known ſo ſorry a Market, for the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> this many a Year as this laſt Year of all. He ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſold near ſo little, ſince it came firſt into play. And he will now ſell the very beſt <hi>Jeſuits Powder</hi> for <hi>twenty ſhillings</hi> the Pound, or under, who five or ſix Years ago ſold it for <hi>eight Pounds</hi> the Pound. So that inſtead of <hi>Curing all Diſeaſes,</hi> you ſee it grows to be a <hi>meer Drugg.</hi> And for <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> he could not obſerve any greater vent of late than ordinary. Some of that indeed muſt be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways uſed, for making <hi>Venice-Treacle</hi> and <hi>Mithridate.</hi> Now read me what this <hi>Scurvy Author</hi> ſaid to the buſineſs of <hi>Diſpenſatories,</hi> that we may compare Notes a little be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him, and this Antagoniſtical Paragraph.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:49471:77"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The</hi> Pharmacopoea <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piled by the whole body of this Apolline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Society</hi> (meaning the <hi>Conclave</hi>) <hi>doth juſtly merit the Character of a moſt Elaborate Work, from thoſe that ſhall compare the ſeveral com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions in it with their Original, where the amendments of omitting of ſuperfluous, incongruous, or aſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrous ingredients, and ſubſtituting of neceſſary and proportionate Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives, are to every eye very obvious, and their care, that thoſe Medicines be neatly and artificiality prepared by the Apothecaries of</hi> London, <hi>hath proved ſo ſucceſsful, that Travellers are obliged to Atteſt, that Pharmacy is in no foreign part ſo much impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, as it is here.</hi> And a little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>still I muſt ſay, that Medicines are no where ſo neatly, ſo honeſtly, and ſo skilfully prepared as here at</hi> London, <hi>and in that particular you may eaſily believe me a judge,</hi> &amp;c. Preface to the <hi>London</hi> Diſeaſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="149" facs="tcp:49471:77"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You have here given a high <hi>Character</hi> of our <hi>Pharmacopoea,</hi> as <hi>of a moſt Elaborate Work, and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers,</hi> you ſay, <hi>are obliged to atteſt</hi> it; ſo that we will <hi>eaſily</hi> take your <hi>judgment</hi> in this caſe, and not expect from our Diſpenſatory <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines adequate to the Cure of all Diſeaſes,</hi> no more than from <hi>Opium</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits Powder.</hi> We do not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to make men Immortal, no more than to free them from the common accidents of humane Life, from the unavoidable Malice and Detraction of ill men. Waſpiſh Bees will ſting many times without a cauſe, though they become <hi>Drones</hi> by their little ſpight; <hi>Dogs</hi> will ſnarl and bark, as well as <hi>delightful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply their Chops to a Bitches Tail.</hi> We may as well expect the Wind to blow always from the ſame corner, or the Tide never to flow, as that inconſiderate Scriblers ſhould not write palpable Inconſiſtencies, and groſs Contradictions. <hi>Momus,</hi> you
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:49471:78"/>e'en <hi>ſhoot at Rovers,</hi> and therefore it is no wonder you ſo often <hi>miſs your mark. But Diſpenſatories are not ſufficiently ſtock'd with Medicines adequate to the Cure of all Diſeaſes.</hi> It is plain that <hi>your</hi> head runs ſtrangely upon <hi>the Cure of all Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes,</hi> notwithſtanding that you lay all the blame upon <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodiſts,</hi> who deal ſo extravagantly in <hi>Opium,</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits Powder.</hi> We do take it <hi>pro conſeſſo,</hi> that the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſatory-Medicines</hi> can <hi>cure ſome Diſeaſes,</hi> but you ſay <hi>they are only virtuated to remove ſlight ſuperficial Diſtempers.</hi> Now I do take the <hi>Vinum Benedictum, Oxymel Elleboratum, Theriaca Andro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machi, Mithridate, Merturius dultis, Pilulae è duobus, Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Salis Armoniaci, Lavendu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae compoſitus, Nitri,</hi> &amp;c. to be <hi>virtuated</hi> with a great deal ſtronger qualities, than <hi>only for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving ſlight ſuperficial Diſtempers.</hi> Some of them might do very well
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:49471:78"/>in your own <hi>Diſtemper,</hi> which is no <hi>ſlight</hi> and <hi>ſuperficial</hi> one, but very tough and untoward, very deep and remote, in the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward receſſes of your Skull; and which occaſions your writings to be ſo <hi>ſlight</hi> and <hi>ſuperficial.</hi> Let me adviſe you before you write again, to try the vertue of ſome of them, eſpecially the <hi>two</hi> firſt. For other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we may have ſuch an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of filthy, naſty ſtuff, thrown forth, altogether unbecoming a man of <hi>your Education,</hi> that the ſight of it will be apt to nauſeate the very ſtomach of any tolerable, or Indifferent Reader, and may make him <hi>caſt</hi> in ſpight of his teeth.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="151-226" type="pages">
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Were it put to debate which of theſe two ſorts of</hi> Sharlatans, <hi>viz. the</hi> Anatomical Theater-Mounter, <hi>or the</hi> Orvietan Bank-Mounter, <hi>is the greater Impostor, it would beyond all peradventure be determined by men of Brains, in favour of the latter,</hi> &amp;c. p. 89.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:49471:79"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Were it put to debate,</hi> which of your Leggs, the right or the left, ought to go firſt, <hi>beyond all perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture</hi> they would kick up one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers heels during the conteſt or <hi>debate.</hi> For you ſo often declare for the <hi>wrong</hi> ſide, and when you fight, <hi>take the wrong end of the ſtaff,</hi> that any <hi>man of Brains</hi> muſt needs wonder how you can ever be in the <hi>right.</hi> And how ignorantly you talk of <hi>Anatomical Theatre-Mounters!</hi> You ſuch a mighty man in <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy,</hi> and not know the Structure of an <hi>Anatomical Theatre!</hi> Their <hi>Theatres</hi> are not <hi>mounted,</hi> or raiſed like the Recreation. <hi>Theatres</hi> above the Pit, or the <hi>Mountebank-Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres</hi> above the People, but the <hi>Doctors</hi> do ſtand or ſit as level with the Floor, as a Gentleman does in his Parlour. Indeed for the convenience of Spectators there are ſome little aſcents to Seats, that young <hi>Batchelors,</hi> and young <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> (much above <hi>ſeventeen</hi>) may
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:49471:79"/>the better learn and ſee. And are not you a fine <hi>Viper</hi> thus to tear the Bowels of your <hi>Mother-Anatomy,</hi> from the ſucking of whoſe Milk you ought to have got greater Skill in Diſeaſes, than from ſucking <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Quinteſſences.</hi> I rather fear, that, Viper-like, after you had done your beſt to kill that good Mother, you e'en <hi>ſuck'd ſome Sow,</hi> which has made you thus to hate <hi>Anatomy</hi> ever ſince. For if this were not ſo, you could never have thus haſtily <hi>determined,</hi> (like a man of no Brains, or at leaſt who has no guts in his brains) <hi>in favour</hi> of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <hi>Charlatan,</hi> or <hi>Mountebank,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the <hi>Learned</hi> and never ſo compleat <hi>Anatomiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The uſe of pretended Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomical Phyſicians is great and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary in a populous Countrey, where neither Famine, Peſtilence, or War have had any ſooting for many years. In this caſe men would devour one another, the place not being extenſive
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:49471:80"/>enough to feed all, were it not that Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians by their <hi>male</hi> practice prevent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Plethory of Inhabitants.</hi> p. 97.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Are the <hi>Peſtilence, War</hi> and <hi>Famine</hi> become ſuch pretty. diverſions to you, ever ſince you were<note n="*" place="margin">Caſus M. Ch. <hi>p. 143.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Doctor-General</hi> (as you proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and in likelyhood falſly, phraſe it) <hi>to the Army in</hi> Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? They have the <hi>Peſtilence</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> almoſt as often as your heart can wiſh, yet the Turks find no ſuch convenience in it as you imagine. But I ſee you have ſome reaſon for being at con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual <hi>War</hi> with your ſelf, and for fighting one of your <hi>Tracts</hi> againſt the other, as you have done; ſince it is a Maxim with you (you learnt it no doubt in the Camp) <hi>Bellum pace potius;</hi> or that <hi>War,</hi> and a Kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Phyſician, are ſo highly neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to hinder <hi>men</hi> from <hi>devouring one another.</hi> And the ſame Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple may be one reaſon, why you
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:49471:80"/>look ſo exceeding meagre and <hi>lean</hi> (as your acquaintance tell me) as if you were <hi>starv'd</hi> and <hi>famiſh'd,</hi> and would <hi>devour</hi> all that you meet, it may be in order to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a <hi>Plethora</hi> or redundance of corrupt and cacochymical humours. But <hi>the uſe of pretended Anatomical Phyſicians is great and neceſſary, leſt men ſhould devour one another.</hi> Take it in the right, proper, and even literal ſenſe, and the Paradox may hold pretty good Water. Your ſelf, <hi>Momus,</hi> is the boldeſt, the veryeſt <hi>Pretender <hi>to Anatomy,</hi>
                     </hi> that we may happen to hear of in many an Age. You cry aloud, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in your Preface, that all Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers who cannot ſtay above a minute or two in a Bookſellers Shop, may take ſpecial notice of your groſs <hi>Pretenſions</hi> to <hi>Anato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>I my ſelf</hi> have divulged more new Anatomical Obſervations,</hi> &amp;c. And you dare to ſay it in the moſt <hi>Anatomical Age</hi> that ever was
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:49471:81"/>known. There is no doubt but ſuch bold deſperate <hi>Pretenders</hi> to <hi>Anatomy</hi> may be their <hi>male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practice</hi> do much to <hi>prevent á</hi> Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thora <hi>of Inhabitants.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I would ask you to what length do you intend to ſpin out this <hi>Treatiſe?</hi> I am grown very weary of theſe your Reflections; I have skipped over abundance of places that you had mark'd, and yet we make but a ſlow advance. We are not yet come to the <hi>Chief Subject</hi> of this <hi>Tract.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>In troth then I could find in my heart to let alone the <hi>Chief Subject,</hi> until ſome other time. It is very unuſual with other Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thus to lead us a dance ſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to the <hi>Chief Subject</hi> for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Pages of a little Pedling <hi>Tract,</hi> and to keep the <hi>Chief Subject,</hi> as Children do the beſt Plum or Cherry, to he laſt. It begins <hi>p.</hi> 101. ends <hi>p.</hi> 113. And all the leſſer tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling <hi>Subjects</hi> are commanded to
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:49471:81"/>ſtop, and make a full point in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a Sheet more of this El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Duodecimo.</hi> One thing I have to ſay to your <hi>Chief Subject</hi> (though it being matter of <hi>Fact,</hi> and not having duely examined it, I ſhall ſay but little to it) that meeting one of the four Phyſicians concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſoon after your crude Pamphlet was firſt ſpawned abroad, and knowing your <hi>Chief Quarrel</hi> was againſt the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> I ask'd him whether the <hi>Bark</hi> were given in that caſe, and he proteſted to me, <hi>that it was not given at all,</hi> at leaſt that he knew of; that he was indeed very much for the giving it, but the other Phyſicians being of another mind, he had acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſced, and did not rudely fling out of the <hi>Conſult-Room,</hi> as <hi>Momus</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every Pett was wont to do in a <hi>Caſe</hi> of his own deſcribing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, at this rate the <hi>Chief Subject,</hi> that was kept as a Dainty to the latter end, e'en comes to juſt nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:49471:82"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot help that; <hi>valeat quantulum valere poteſt.</hi> When a Man fleys a Catterwauler, what can he have, bating Anatomical hints, more than the <hi>Skin?</hi> the <hi>Chief Subject</hi> of many a Pamphlet beſides this proves to be a ſorry pittance, and as light as a <hi>Feather,</hi> or <hi>Cobwebb,</hi> when it comes to be weighed in the ſcales of Senſe or Reaſon. Men oftentimes write <hi>they know not what, and they know not why.</hi> And, <hi>Momus,</hi> do you ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to receive better Quarter than you give? you that find ſuch faults with others when there is no need, and who kick and ſpurn at all other men, who come in your way, let them treat never ſo carefully, can you expect in reaſon that they ſhould take ſtrict care not to treat upon your Toes? <hi>Momus,</hi> paſs on at a round rate, and skip over moſt of the diſmal paſſages before you, that we may have a few ſhort touches at your Younger <hi>Duodecimo, the ſecond Part of the Conclave.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="159" facs="tcp:49471:82"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>The 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter <hi>proves that the Jeſuits Powder never yet cured any remitting Fever.</hi> p. 118. And the next Chapter tells you what it is, and what it is not. But <hi>after all, I could wiſh theſe Fathers had kept their</hi> Indian <hi>Bark to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſure I am, hundreds would be on this ſide the Grave, whoſe Bones are now turned into their firſt Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> p. 129.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe that are skill'd a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in Logick, do find it <hi>a hard Chapter</hi> to <hi>prove a Negative.</hi> And ſo your 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
                     <hi>Chapter</hi> in dint of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument will prove you a very ſorry Sophiſter, who ſo idly undertake to prove that, which it is <hi>impoſſible</hi> to make out. The famous <hi>Freſhman,</hi> who coming from the Univerſity (his head being glowing hot with <hi>Syllo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſms</hi>) undertook to prove to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mohter, that the <hi>two Eggs</hi> they had for Supper were <hi>three,</hi> and who was ſain to riſe a hungry Wretch when his plain and illogical Father
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:49471:83"/>and Mother had eaten each their <hi>one Egg,</hi> bidding him to eat the <hi>third:</hi> this half-witted Logician would never have been ſo ſimple, as you, who moſt ridiculouſly and yet moſt confidently, in the very Title of your Chapter, do preſme to <hi>prove that the Jeſuits Powder, <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet</hi> cured any remitting Fever.</hi> The raw Wag, before-mentioned, knew better things than ſo. His Tutor, I warrant, had ſoon taught him among general Rules:
<q>
                        <l>Syllogizari non eſt ex particlari,</l>
                        <l>Neve Negativis, rectè concludere ſi vis.</l>
                     </q> And, <hi>Negans eſt deterior Affirman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> that is, the <hi>Negative</hi> is a worſe end of the ſtaff, in Logical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bats, than the <hi>Affirmative.</hi> The reaſon is plain, becauſe a Fool can make more Objections in a day, than a wiſe man can anſwer in a year. Therefore you are a fit man with all my heart, to write <hi>Archae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologia Philoſophica Nova,</hi> or, New
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:49471:83"/>Princiles of Philoſophy! Go, learn your Rudiments again, <hi>young Doctor,</hi> before you preſume to teach Profeſſors ſuch <hi>Falſe,</hi> and <hi>New Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Philoſophy.</hi> But to return, <hi>you could wiſh the Fathers had kept the</hi> Indian <hi>Bark to themſelves.</hi> And <hi>p.</hi> 2. you call it the <hi>Devil's-Bark.</hi> Oh how your head was <hi>tickled</hi> with that <hi>New Notion!</hi> But before we are much older, you muſt own, that if it was a <hi>Devil's Bark,</hi> it was a very kind <hi>Devil</hi> to you, however unkind it has been to others. <hi>Was</hi> it ſo long ſince your ſelf was taken ill of a <hi>Remitting Fevor,</hi> (a <hi>febris lenta</hi> it could not well chooſe but be, in ſuch a depraved, ſowre, and melancholick Habit of Body) which <hi>Fevor</hi> afterwards turned into a <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian-Ague,</hi> that made you to <hi>trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> many a time? you cannot have forgot, that you then ſent for two of our <hi>Aſſociated Phyſicians,</hi> who propoſed to you the Specifick aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this <hi>Devil's-Bark.</hi> At firſt
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:49471:84"/>indeed you were very averſe to its aſſiſtance, thinking it to be a <hi>Black</hi> and unkind <hi>Devil,</hi> but at laſt you were over-perſwaded, and heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to <hi>ſome who were wiſer than ſome,</hi> you admitted the <hi>Devil</hi> to take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of your body, and it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a more gentle, harmleſs, and <hi>whiter Devil,</hi> than you deſerved; for which great kindneſs you ought not to be ſo ungrateful as you are, but <hi>give</hi> even <hi>the Devil his due.</hi> And now if <hi>the Fathers had kept the Bark to themſelves,</hi> what a ſweet loſs might the Faculty have had! For all that I know, both <hi>Parts</hi> of the <hi>Conclave</hi> had never been hatch'd, and ſo you might have loſt the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many a ridiculous Jeſt, and we the laughing at you now in very good earneſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I am a declared Enemy to the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> and would rather in my own judgment, have been but half-cured by any thing elſe, than to have received ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:49471:84"/>a Cure by a thing I naturally hate. <hi>Sure I am,</hi> if <hi>the Fathers had kept that</hi> Deviliſh <hi>Bark to themſelves, hundreds would be on this ſide the Grave, whoſe Bones are now turned into their firſt Element.</hi> p. 129.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>How come you to be ſo cock-ſure, concerning <hi>hundreds of Patients,</hi> and <hi>hundreds of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans?</hi> You may have learn'd a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in Rhetorick, <hi>Certum pro in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certo,</hi> of putting down a <hi>Certain</hi> extravagant Number, when you are the moſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g> ncertain</hi> in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that 'tis poſſible. <hi>We</hi> are very <hi>ſure,</hi> that many a Patient had been on <hi>th'other ſide the Grave,</hi> if it had not been for the <hi>Bark,</hi> under God; and you are ſure that God knows who had been <hi>on this ſide the Grave,</hi> if the <hi>Bark</hi> had remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſome <hi>Terra incognita.</hi> But a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! <hi>Their Bones are turned into their firſt Element.</hi> Do <hi>Bones</hi> then uſe to <hi>turn</hi> ſo ſoon <hi>into Element?</hi> If you had but viewed the Churches
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:49471:85"/>and minded them here and there with a little Curioſity, as you travelled to and fro, <hi>ſure</hi> you would have heard of <hi>Charnel-Houſes, Oſſuaria,</hi> where dead mens <hi>Bones</hi> are kept for <hi>many Ages.</hi> Fleſh indeed is frail, but <hi>Bones</hi> are tough and firm, and <hi>that which is in the <hi>Bone</hi>
                     </hi> (you might have heard) <hi>will not eaſily out in the Fleſh.</hi> No, <hi>they</hi> do not ſo ſoon <hi>turn into Element.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>When I ſay <hi>the Bark never yet cured any one man of a Remit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Fevor,</hi> I alſo ſay, <hi>excepting poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly three or four among a Million, whoſe robuſt natures neither Diſeaſe nor Remedy could deſtroy.</hi> p. 119.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You think your ſelf now a cunning Sophiſter, in diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſoon as you do, <hi>that the Bark never yet cured any Remitting Fevor quà talis,</hi> that is, <hi>qu tenus continua,</hi> but <hi>quatenus intermittens.</hi> Ibid. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it does not cure <hi>quà talis,</hi> it <hi>never cures</hi> at all. And becauſe it does <hi>not cure</hi> as you would have it
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:49471:85"/>do, <hi>quatenus continua,</hi> it muſt be fain to cure, as that which the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor is not, that is, <hi>quatenus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittens.</hi> So that in your Logick a <hi>Remitting Fevor</hi> has two faces, a blind ſide <hi>(quatenus continua)</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to be cured, and a pretty gay look, <hi>(quatenus intermittens)</hi> to be cured by halfs, or between Hawk and Buzzard. But, <hi>Momus,</hi> I can tell you one remarkable Story of <hi>One</hi> that was <hi>cured</hi> of a certain <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor, quatenus intermittens;</hi> and in which you were very highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned. An <hi>Apothecary,</hi> living near <hi>Lumbard ſtreet,</hi> I think, in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                     <hi>Swi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thin</hi>'s <hi>Lane</hi> (who had the honour to be eſteemed your <hi>Apothecary in Ordinary,</hi> but without much <hi>Fee,</hi> as you <hi>Phyſician in Ordinary to his late Majeſty,</hi> but without any <hi>Fee</hi> at all.) This <hi>Apothecary</hi> having lingred long under an <hi>Intermittent Fevor,</hi> and being a <hi>Sufferer</hi> under your hands, and under thoſe <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifick <hi>Remedies</hi>
                     </hi> you boaſt <hi>you have
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:49471:86"/>equal to</hi> Riverius <hi>his Febrifuge, Jeſuits Bark, or any other, in Intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents,</hi> (as Part II. p. 31.) and yet, unfortunate man that he was, he ſtill grew worſe and worſe, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Energy of your rare and wonderful <hi>Febrifuges, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual</hi> to that of <hi>Riverius,</hi> or the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Bark, or any other,</hi> all the World over. But at laſt two Good Women, <hi>who had no mind,</hi> it ſeems, <hi>to loſe their Apothecary,</hi> applyed themſelves to a worthy Phyſician of the College, whom you often ſpurn and ſpit at, and call <hi>the Doctor of Contraries,</hi> who had never ſeen the face of the <hi>Sufferer</hi> before, and who then knew nothing of his unhappy Deſtiny in <hi>ſuffering</hi> ſo much under your rigid will and pleaſure. The Doctor aforeſaid is prevailed to viſit your <hi>Sufferer,</hi> finds him in a very ill and lamentable condition, advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes him to take of the <hi>Jeſuits Bark Scrupulos duos quartâ quâque horâ,</hi> for two days; which he had no
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:49471:86"/>ſooner adviſed, but going down ſtairs he met <hi>Momus</hi> himſelf, who declared with open mouth, that he was utterly againſt giving the <hi>Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> to ſave the man's life. But he was grown wiſer, than to <hi>ſuffer</hi> any longer, he took it according to order, and became incontinently <hi>as ſound as a Roch.</hi> Now this was the true cauſe that mov'd your Spleen to ſo high a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree againſt this worthy Doctor, and that which occaſioned you to call him by ridiculous Names, and among others, <hi>the Doctor of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries,</hi> p. 67. as if <hi>Opium,</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits Powder</hi> were ſuch oppoſite <hi>Contraries;</hi> whereas it is known to every body, that they are both of them, exhibited in due time, and with due caution, moſt powerful Allayers of febrile commotions. And this made you talk of <hi>the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federacy of the Female Legate,</hi> p. 54. But the <hi>Confederacy</hi> was in truth like the <hi>Confederacy</hi> of <hi>Aſſociated
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:49471:87"/>Phyſicians,</hi> for the good and ſafety of men, and not for their hurt. Henceforth therefore we will not call you the <hi>Doctor of Contraries,</hi> as you do ſillily and improperly call a Good Phyſician, but we will very appoſitely and properly call you, from your groſs inconſiſtencies and manifold repugnancies between your own writings, the <hi>Doctor of Contradictions.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Would it not move a ſtone, that he ſhould have the Devil and all of thanks, and a <hi>Soſtrum</hi> of two Piſtoles for his two Viſits, when the Patient ought in duty to have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended on my Skill? But ſtill I <hi>except</hi> only <hi>three or four</hi> among a Million, <hi>whoſe robuſt natures neither Diſeaſe nor Remedy could deſtroy.</hi> p. 119.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>What pity 'tis, their <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>robuſt!</hi> and how punctual you are in <hi>three or four a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong a Million!</hi> as if <hi>a Million</hi> of Patients were as common in your Obſervation, as a Flock of Pidge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:49471:87"/>in the Countrey. It is all alike to you, and ſounds to the Tune of <hi>No Carrion will kill a Crow.</hi> Or, <hi>Dav veniam Corvis, vexat cenſura Columbas.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now open <hi>The ſecond Part of the Conclave,</hi> that we may ſee whether either of the two <hi>Barrels be better Herring;</hi> or whether upon two or three years muſing on your former Follies, you are grown e'er a whit wiſer than before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Beofre I have done with this, I could edifie the Reader more than he's aware, <hi>had I not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to forbear utting more ſenſe into my Friends of</hi> Paris, <hi>than Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or their School-Learning hath planted into them.</hi> p. 128.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>If it be ſo <hi>determined,</hi> to the prejudice of your <hi>Mock-friends,</hi> we will e'en be contented, and ſhed no tears, I'll promiſe you, Come, read ſome few paſſages in the <hi>Second Part.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then I will begin
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:49471:88"/>with <hi>Thomas Willis, <hi>who for couching Phyſical Romances, and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantick Notions, ſmoothly, elegantly, and to Phyſicians of</hi>
                     </hi> Par. <hi>only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Truth, doth exceed</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Scudery <hi>in his Hiſtorical Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, could it but be believed, the ſtyle and the Latin were as much his own as the Matter.</hi> p. 17.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Never did man deſerve the name of <hi>Momus</hi> better than your ſelf. For the greater and more excellent any <hi>Medicine</hi> is in its kind, the more violently you are ſet againſt it; and ſo the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, more conſpicuous, and of Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Fame or Memory any Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician is, the more venemous and bitter, and the more implacably malicious you are againſt him. Do you dare to ſpeak of <hi>Thomas Willis,</hi> as of Tom-Fool, or Tom of <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam?</hi> That great and incompara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble man of <hi>Immortal Memory,</hi> has left a Name behind him, which will never be forgotten. He died in
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:49471:88"/>the height of Honour, and will be commemorated with Glory by fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Phyſicians in the learned World, when your Memory like your Carcaſs will ſtink, and when <hi>your Bones are turned into their first Element,</hi> as you inſpidly expreſs it. To this ſame <hi>Thomas Willis,</hi> you (like an unmannerly proud Quaker, who has mighty reaſon indeed to boaſt of <hi>Education</hi>) will not vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe even the Title of <hi>Doctor;</hi> which he hath infinitely more <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,</hi> as well as his others, than you that of <hi>Batchelor,</hi> or even <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in Phyſick.</hi> You unwittingly couple him with a man moſt admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable in his Way, the famous <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Scudery,</hi> whoſe Works, though <hi>Romances,</hi> if you had ſtudied more than you have done, or even if you had <hi>peruſed them twice</hi> in their moſt Elegant, and Polite Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you might have mended your Style, and in part have mended your Manners. And do this Great
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:49471:89"/>man's <hi>Notions to Phyſicians of Par. only reſemble Truth?</hi> Yes, they are held in wonderful eſteem by <hi>Phyſicians</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> and <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> of <hi>Padua.</hi> If you have any little Correſpondence that you hold in thoſe Places, deſire your Friend to ask any, or all the <hi>Profeſſors</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion concerning <hi>Doctor Willis</hi> his Works, and you will find them All on his ſide, Admirers of the Man. His <hi>Pharmaceutice Rationalis</hi> will always ſhew the World, how <hi>ſmoothly, elegantly,</hi> and ſolidly, he could <hi>couch Phyſical Notions,</hi> and explicate, beyond all that ever went before him, the Operation of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines in Humane Bodies. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thoſe few <hi>ſmooth</hi> words you give unto <hi>Thomas Willis,</hi> you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently ſuſpect and ſay, <hi>could it but be believed, the Style and the Latin were as much his own as the Matter. The Matter</hi> indeed, and the <hi>Senſe</hi> of a Book is the main thing that deſerves to be minded, but every
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:49471:89"/>Reader is not judicious enough to dive to the bottom of <hi>the Matter,</hi> and therefore politeneſs of Style, appoſite Words, perſpicuous, eaſie, proper, and unaffected Expreſſions, are alſo of ſingular uſe. If <hi>You</hi> had been better acquainted with <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur Scudery,</hi> you would have had words enough at command, and not be forced to coin baſe, and nonſenſical words, ſuch as <hi>Grove, Catochization,</hi> &amp;c. and think to bring your ſelf off with crying, <hi>it is Philoſophical ſo to do,</hi> as in the Preface to your <hi>Quarto.</hi> Your <hi>Senſe</hi> as well as <hi>Style</hi> would have had more Uniformilty, than to be one while calling <hi>the Divines Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, Cheats and Hypocrites,</hi> and anon wiping your mouth, demurely to tell us of <hi>that moſt Honourable Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> and to hint as if you were concerned about <hi>the ſaving of Souls from Perdition. Doctor Will is</hi> did in many things <hi>rectè ſentire,</hi> and in all things <hi>id quod ſenſit, politè eloqui
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:49471:90"/>potuit.</hi> But to do as you do, for a man to put his Thoughts into Print, who has no skill to place them in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tolerable order, nor to illuſtrate them with any good Fancy, nor to delight a judicious Reader in any manner of reſpect, is the part of a man who cares not how abominably he abuſes our Patience, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpends his own time, and he's a ſhame to Letters or Learning. <hi>Mandare quenquam literis cogitationes ſuas, qui eas nec diſponere, nec illustrare poſſit, nec delectatione aliquâ allicere Lecto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, hominis eſt intemperanter abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis &amp; otio, &amp; literis,</hi> as <hi>Tully</hi> has it <hi>Tuſc. qu. lib.</hi> 1. But how ſhall we cure your Unbelief, as to the property, or <hi>menum</hi> and <hi>tuum</hi> of his Style and Latin? To ſatisfie all the Scruples of <hi>Momus</hi> will be a <hi>had Chapter,</hi> and it may be as hard as your 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Chapter, Part 1. wherein you made bold <hi>to prove a Negative.</hi> But this I ſhall ſay, that he was known to be an <hi>Excellent</hi>
                     <pb n="175" facs="tcp:49471:90"/>Latin <hi>Scholar,</hi> and an acute <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> and was therefore choſen to by <hi>Sydley Profeſſor of Philoſophy,</hi> in <hi>Oxford.</hi> He was the moſt general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applied to, by Scholars, and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity-men of all ſorts, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps was ever known before. And his Cuſtom was, when he was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Patients out of Town, ſo that he had ſome time to ſpare, he carried a Tinder-Box with him, would trike fire himſelf, at Three or Four a Clock in the Morning, and would be as buſie at <hi>Couching Phyſical Notions,</hi> for the Benefit of the Faculty, as ever <hi>Momus</hi> could be at rakeing together ridiculous and detracting Stories. Whoever would read the juſt Character of this Great and Eminent Phyſician, let him but run over two or three Leaves, the <hi>Poſt-ſcript Preface</hi> to the <hi>ſecond Part</hi> of his <hi>Pharmaceutice Rationalis,</hi> which <hi>Poſt-ſcript</hi> was written when men do not uſe to be flattered, after his Death.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:49471:91"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Had the ſaid</hi> Willis <hi>from Obſervation abſtracted his Novels, a happier Succeſs would have attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Practice, than which nothing ever proved more pernicious and fatal to moſt of thoſe Patients, that ſubjected themſelves to his, and the followers of him, Their debauch'd Advice, which the Bills of Mortality of his time, and ſince, did amply teſtifie.</hi> p. 18.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall leave his nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Patients,</hi> who many of them do ſtill lament his loſs, to judge the <hi>Happy Succeſs</hi> of his <hi>Practice.</hi> But you do very <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply teſtifie</hi> a moſt inveterate ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and malice, as well as inſupportable Folly, who thus to gratifie a Deadly Hatred, and moſt unreaſonable Pique, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not forbear thus Sacrilegiouſly diſturbing and profaning the Memory of ſo Pious, ſo Great, and ſo Admirable a Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:49471:91"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>When I was a Student in</hi> Exeter <hi>College,</hi> Willis <hi>was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, that he was forced to block at his Pen, and ſo by forgeing of Novelties, thereby removing the Buſhel from over his Candle, ailured a number of poor Countrey Patients, though at that time very raw in all manner of Experience, nor advanced in the leaſt in practical Obſervations; ſo that at laſt</hi> Juſtice <hi>for his having ſo long impunitely injured Mankind, made him his own Executioner, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under the ſame miſapplications, ſo many hundreds had miſcarried by.</hi> p. 27, 28.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You were a ſpecial Student indeed, who <hi>ſeveral Years</hi> before <hi>ſeventeen</hi> could thus paſs your raſh and haſty cenſure on the Practice of Learned Phyſicians. Could your ſo early <hi>ſtudy</hi> of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> make you a proper Judge either of his Practice, or his Works in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, which you do call (like a real, but malapert Blockhead) <hi>to block
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:49471:92"/>at his Pen? Momus,</hi> your Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions are ſo contemptible, mean and ſenſeleſs, and your Vanity ſo extravagant, that I have hardly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to entertain more Diſcourſe at a time with ſuch an empty Puff.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure You could not think ſo hardly of me, if you had well conſidered, or <hi>twice peruſed</hi> the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of my <hi>Education, Caſus M. Ch.</hi> p. 140, 141. or if you had but ſtayed to the end of this my <hi>Williſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Chapter,</hi> which my head has run ſo much upon, that I have beſtowed no leſs than eight Leaves upon it; whereas I did not, or then would not, write ſix entire Leaves upon <hi>the Chief Subject</hi> of my <hi>firſt Part.</hi> But in ſhort, <hi>Should I charge my ſelf with the trouble of Copying out the Theory of intermittent, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Fevors, abſtracted from Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, and experimental Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the ſole Original and Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental of true Knowledge, you would at the ſame moment be furniſhed with
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:49471:92"/>a Guide eaſily to conduct you to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies equal to</hi> Riverius <hi>his</hi> Febri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, Jeſuits Bark, <hi>or any other in Intermittents, and to Medicines in continual, putrid, or malignant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond any yet diſcovered, that ſhall manifeſtly abate the Distemper, and extinguiſh malignity; but it is fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign to my intention ever to gratifie that ingrateful and malicious Tribe of</hi> Par. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> p. 31.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will give</hi> much the ſame <hi>Advertiſement,</hi> you did in your <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Med. Ch.</hi> p. 146. <hi>That there is one</hi> Momus, to <hi>whom the Courteſie of</hi> England <hi>gives the Title of Doctor, he lives ſomewhere about</hi> Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, <hi>or</hi> Uxbridge, <hi>learn'd his Trade of</hi> John Pontaeus, <hi>and doth,</hi> more than any other Mountebank before him, bounce and crack of the worth of <hi>his Medicines up and down the City and Countrey, though whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he keeps the Stage I cannot in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form.</hi> I have read many a Quack-Bill in my time, but do not remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:49471:93"/>that any of them yet have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to more, than to <hi>have Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies beyond any yet diſcovered, in continual, putrid, or malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Febors, and equal to any</hi> the beſt in the World <hi>in Intermit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents.</hi> Other Quacks have had ſome ſmall ſhare of Modeſty, and have been contented with pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Remedies beyond any yet diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered,</hi> in the Scurvy, Dropſie, Pox, Griping of the Guts, the Stone, Conſumptions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but you are the firſt man <hi>to whom the Courteſie of</hi> England (ah ſhame on it!) <hi>gives the Title of Doctor,</hi> who would thus wretchedly monopolize the Cure of <hi>all acute Diſeaſes.</hi> You did not <hi>learn that</hi> of your Maſter <hi>Pontaeus.</hi> He had indeed a <hi>Salve</hi> for Burns and Sores, he had an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote</hi> that would do no hurt, and he had a <hi>Plaiſter</hi> for <hi>Corns on your Feet or Toes.</hi> But he had the grace to leave <hi>Fevers</hi> to the management of Phyſicians; and was abundantly
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:49471:93"/>more civil and ingenuous in his way; he contented himſelf to be <hi>Mountebank Paramount,</hi> but never offered to <hi>copy out the Theory of Fevors,</hi> and ſay that <hi>at the ſame mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> he <hi>furniſhed</hi> the World with a Treaſure greater than the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Willis <hi>his Purge ſignifies nothing in a ſtubborn, or inveterate Tertian; it muſt be a Cathartick of another nature, and greater energy, among which <hi>I could diſcover</hi> one to the Phyſicians of</hi> P. <hi>that at once or twice purges off thoſe viſcous putrid Humours in a great part, the other it precipitates to the Bladder, and the remainder it fixes, which three Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties ought to concur in any Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine that deſerves to be named a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brifuge, or ſpecifick Antipyretick; but that would be caſting Pearls to Sw.</hi> p. 38.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Purge then is a very diſcerning and intelligent Purge, and makes a very good hunter,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:49471:94"/>that will ſearch to the bottom of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very cranny of the body, in order to purge, fix, or precipitate by U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, the naughty febrile Humour. <hi>Which three properties,</hi> you ſay, are neceſſary to the being a <hi>Specifick,</hi> and yet we find little or nothing of them in the <hi>Jeſuits Powder,</hi> the main modern <hi>Specifick;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>true Specifick,</hi> becauſe it makes no Evacuation. But you will not <hi>diſcover, or caſt your Pearls before Swine,</hi> that is, you dare not bring your Works of Darkneſs to the light of the Sun, or your coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, and baſe adulterations to the Teſt of a skilful Artiſt. Your <hi>Pearls</hi> are meer Pebbles, and you ſhall never perſwade us that your cackling Geeſe can be melodious Swans.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After all, I muſt tell you, Fevors are curable by Methods diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from theſe, and Remedies, which they never yet have found out, nor e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver will. For if any of a Genius
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:49471:94"/>inquiſitive ſhould endeavour to conduct them into a true path, would for his pains, be rewarded with ill language, reproach, and all manner of ingratitude; and therefore no more ſhall be ſiad at preſent.</hi> p. 53, 54.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sat verbum ſapienti.</hi> There is no <hi>neceſſity</hi> of your <hi>telling us,</hi> that the Moon is made of green Cheeſe. Conſult the wiſe Women, and <hi>inquiſitive</hi> Aſtrologers, and they will all tell you the very ſame, you ſo often cloy us with. They have a great many <hi>Infallible Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines,</hi> as well as you <hi>Specificks</hi> of a new Invention. But if ever you ſhould chance in a kind mood to impart to the World, or <hi>tell</hi> your notable <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Remedies</hi> that are ſuch <hi>curing</hi> contrivances in <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors,</hi> I would earneſtly requeſt one thing of you, and that is, <hi>not</hi> to let us know the <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies</hi> you uſed in the <hi>Cure</hi> of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors,</hi> when you took your Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at <hi>Ipſwich;</hi> for they could
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:49471:95"/>not be theſe you now ſpeak of, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a ſtrong report in Town, that you could not, or did not, ſave the life, (hardly) of one perſon in a <hi>Fever,</hi> whom you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook at <hi>Ipſwich;</hi> your <hi>Methods</hi> and <hi>Remedies</hi> that you then uſed, proving ſo fatally unfortunate. I do not <hi>averr</hi> this of them, as you do worſe things, upon leſs grounds, of all Phyſicians, neither do I call Heaven to witneſs, but I muſt ſay, that the Report is no blind Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, and that I have reaſon to think it came from the Place it ſelf, and was brought to Town, as I am told, by thoſe who were the moſt capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judges of ſuch matters. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore don't <hi>endeavour to conduct</hi> us <hi>into true paths</hi> with thoſe <hi>Killing Methods</hi> and <hi>Remedies</hi> that you u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, when <hi>there was a time to kill,</hi> but be ſure you give us a touch of your <hi>Healing Remedies,</hi> if you have any in <hi>banco,</hi> that belong <hi>to the time of Healing.</hi> But I am afraid you
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:49471:95"/>have no other <hi>Genius</hi> that guides you, and is <hi>to conduct us into true paths,</hi> but an <hi>Evil Genius,</hi> an <hi>Ignis Fatuus,</hi> a Will-with-a-wiſp, whoſe <hi>conduct</hi> indeed will never be taken in good part by Learned Collegiate Phyſicians, but deſerves to <hi>be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded with Reproach, ill Language, and all manner of</hi> Indignation: <hi>and therefore no more ſhall be ſaid at preſent.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In concluſion, may I never be guilty of ſo much Knavery, and Ignornace, as to become a Conclave-Phyſician.</hi> p. 51. <hi>This toucheth not my Copy-hold, never intending to herd with any Society of Phyſicians, unleſs there ſhould happen a wonderful Reformation, though I cannot deny, but I have formerly been a Fellow of a College of Phyſicians,</hi> &amp;c. p. 72, 73.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>You would teach us to call down right <hi>Knave</hi> without Craft or Decency. I muſt <hi>therefore</hi> tell you, that you need not fear, but
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:49471:96"/>Honeſt Men ſo well forewarned as they are, will never be guilty of ſo much folly, as to admit <hi>Knaves</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Society, nor Learned Men become ſo ſtupid, as to admit igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, but horribly fantaſtical Dolt-heads, into their Conclave. But, <hi>Momus,</hi> however you ſay here, <hi>may I never be guilty,</hi> and you <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver intend to herd with any Society of</hi> Learned and Honeſt <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> yet I am at this time credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, that you are turning ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Millſtones which lye in your way, and uſing Intereſt, to gain admittance into the <hi>Pariſian Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave,</hi> the College of Phyſicians in <hi>London.</hi> But <hi>you cannot deny but</hi> that <hi>you have formerly been a Fellow of a College of Phyſicians;</hi> Look you there! <hi>You cannot deny</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth, no, you cannot forbear, proclaiming it aloud, even in the <hi>Title-leaf</hi> (as you call it) of ſome of your <hi>Tracts,</hi> that you were once (and how you came to loſe that
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:49471:96"/>
                     <hi>Title,</hi> the <hi>College</hi> not dying, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Titles</hi> ſometimes do, I know not) an unworthy and ungrateful <hi>Fellow of the College of Phyſicians at the</hi> Hague. But for <hi>that,</hi> as I ſaid before, you are to thank your Good Mothers Bohemian Intereſt, not your native or natural <hi>Mother-Wit.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding, I do utterly deſpiſe theſe <hi>Pen and Ink Doctors, who are ignorant how to bruiſe, powder, ſift, infuſe, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract</hi> a Medicine, <hi>and to weigh it into Doſes.</hi> Wherefore <hi>the Peſtil and Mortar Doctors for that reaſon attain ten Patients to the others one,</hi> p. 56. And in the next Page, I conclude, <hi>That generally throughout all</hi> Paris, <hi>the Apothecaries having fifty or a hundred Patients to the Phyſicians one, it's an infallible Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, that the Company of Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caries get fifty or a hundred times more than the Band of Phyſicians.</hi> p. 57.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Can you, who have ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:49471:97"/>ſo many Pens, and ſpilt ſo much <hi>Ink,</hi> in ſcribling ſuch a deal of traſh and waſt Paper, can you be ſtill ſo weak and ſilly, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clouded with Malice, as to know <hi>the Pen and Ink Doctors</hi> no better? Is it poſſible, that you can ſo wretchedly inſinuate, and beyond any glimpſe of probability miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent ſuch <hi>Perfect Maſters of the Pen and Ink,</hi> as if they were Men, who can neither write nor read, nor tell one, two, and three, as if they had never ſeen <hi>a Peſtil and Mortar</hi> in all their lives, and knew not the difference between a pair of Spectacles and a pair of Scales? This Paragraph conſiſts of three <hi>Doſes,</hi> whereof the <hi>firſt</hi> we have weighed already, and find it ſo light and heedleſs, that it will not weigh ſo much as an Atome, much leſs any part of a <hi>Grain,</hi> whether of <hi>Senſe,</hi> or even appearance of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> The ſecond is your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of <hi>the Peſtle and Mortar
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:49471:97"/>Doctors ten to one</hi> before the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Indeed if you mean by <hi>Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents</hi> every one that comes for a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-worth of <hi>Mithridate,</hi> or a half-pe'th of <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nguentum,</hi> we ſhall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily grant them the greater num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber by far. And beſides, theſe <hi>mock-Doctors,</hi> let me tell you, have more dextrous cunning, and notable Cajoling Arts with 'em, in one of their little fingers, than you have (if we may believe your own Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phelts, the bolts you ſo often ſhoot at random) in your whole body, But that we may the more exactly. weigh this Doſe, let us e'en take in with it the third Doſe, and put them together in the ſame ſcale. And that, you ſay, is an <hi>Infallible Concluſion, that generally throughout all</hi> Paris <hi>the Apothecaries have fifty or a hundred Patients to the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians one; and the Company of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries get fifty or a hundred times more than the Band of Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</hi> How eaſily do they <hi>get Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi>
                     <pb n="190" facs="tcp:49471:98"/>by the help of your heedleſs Pen, from <hi>ten to one,</hi> in the turn of the hand, or of one leaf, multiplyed into <hi>a hundred to one!</hi> But notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this Complement to the <hi>Man-Doctors,</hi> they might e'en ſhut up their Shops, and <hi>the Pestle and Mortar</hi> might grow ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, if they were condemn'd to wait until <hi>Momus</hi> ſends them Cuſtomers. You <hi>meaſure</hi> other mens Practice by your own diminutive <hi>Buſhel;</hi> and <hi>you talk ike an Apothecary,</hi> things that you don't underſtand. But for all you thus deſpiſe the <hi>Phyſicians gettings,</hi> you may have heard of fifty or a hundred Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, more than once preſented to a <hi>Conclave Phyſicians.</hi> when an <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary</hi> is well contented to get half a Crown for a Purge or a Glyſter, of one of his ordinary <hi>Patients.</hi> The Apothecaries tell us, that they run many hazards in their <hi>gettings,</hi> and, if they be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:49471:98"/>are at a conſiderable expence too; they are of late Years exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly multiplyed, and the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er fry ready to devour one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Beſides, People have not now-a-days the patience to go through a courſe of Phyſick for a Year or two together in Chroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſtempers, as they did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. The frequent uſe of <hi>Jeſuits Powder</hi> by the Doctors, and their curing thereby ſo ſoon as they do, is of no ſuch mighty advantage to their <hi>gettings,</hi> that they have any great reaſon to boaſt. But to <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,</hi> though not <hi>Infallibly,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever your raſh and incongruous <hi>Concluſion</hi> be with you <hi>Infallible,</hi> like your pretended Medicines, I can tell you, that one of the moſt Eminent Practicers now in Town, did lately aſſert publickly in my hearing, that according to the beſt Obſervation he could make of <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians gettings,</hi> he thought the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of Phyſick</hi> (notwithſtanding
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:49471:99"/>the preſent boundleſs Interlopings of Empiricks, Apothecaries, Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanks, Bill-men, wiſe Women, and all-knowing Aſtrologers) does at this time <hi>get</hi> more Money, than ever it did in any Age before us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>That's very ſtrange to me, who have maintained, that <hi>five ſixths of the Phyſicians go with their hands in their Pockets all day, the greateſt part of buſineſs paſſing only through few mens hands,</hi> p. 58. But afterwards I ſay, <hi>Practica eſt multiplex; <hi>it's no wonder if half the Phyſicians cannot get ſo much, as will buy water to waſh their hands. Thus much of</hi>
                     </hi> Pantagruel <hi>and</hi> Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragantua. Simon <hi>and</hi> Judas, <hi>or</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puleius <hi>and's Aſs.</hi> p. 71.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>When you talk of <hi>five ſixths of the Phyſicians</hi> ſo very punctually, ſure you forgot, <hi>that you do abandon the acquaintance of Phyſick-Doctors for their male-pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice,</hi> and other horrid ſaults there drawn in black, and <hi>that there is
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:49471:99"/>no ſort of men you look upon with greater contempt.</hi> As Part I. p. 90. But whatever you ſpleen makes you ſay, a great part of the <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians</hi> do go in their Coaches good part of the day, and do ſeldom put their <hi>hands in their pockets,</hi> unleſs to drop a good Fee; and however you ſay <hi>the greateſt part of buſineſs paſſes only through few men's hands,</hi> yet it is an odd ſign of <hi>buſineſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo <hi>ſcarce</hi> in this Great and ſpreading City, that every Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, who is of late admitted into the <hi>College,</hi> is fain to pay near twice as much for his <hi>Admiſſion</hi> as ever was <hi>required</hi> before. One would think therefore, that <hi>Practica est multiplex,</hi> or there is Practice e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for many; elſe why do they pay ſo much, is it only to purchaſe one of your <hi>Airey Titles?</hi> But in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſadneſs, do <hi>five ſixths of them go with their hands in their Pockets all day?</hi> Will they not take them out to feel a Pulſe? And you ſay <hi>half the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:49471:100"/>cannot get ſo much, as will buy water to waſh their hands,</hi> (Oh wonderful!) in a place where water is ſo ſcarce, that perhaps no City in the World, not <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, with her famous <hi>Aquaeducts</hi> was ever more plentifully ſupplied with Water. <hi>Half</hi> then, and <hi>five ſixths</hi> are the ſame identical Number in your Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick. Thus much of Fool and Knave, Puſh-pin and Bawbles, Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wham and Nonſenſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Before we part, I muſt tell you, I am no ſuch Friend to the Apoſthecaries. <hi>You may believe, it's not one Bill in twenty is exactly made up according to the Doctor's Order; neither is it fitting it ſhould, for oft his Preſcriptions are ſo idle and incongruous, did not the Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of the Apothecary correct, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and ſubſtitute what he pleaſes, there would be mad work in the ſick man's Gutts. Therefore grant the Doctor preſcribes over-night a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorifick Cordial Julep; the other
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:49471:100"/>prepares it, with the addition of a few grains of Reſin of</hi> Gialap, <hi>or</hi> Scammony, <hi>without the leaſt ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of diſcovery,</hi> &amp;c. p. 62, 63.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>In troth your friendſhip is ſuch an odd and inartificial Medley of Bitter, Sweetiſh, and Sowre, that a man had better be without it. Your Complements are like <hi>Judas</hi> his Kiſs. If the <hi>Apothecaries do not make up exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one Bill in twenty,</hi> our Patients are finely brought to bed. This is much to the Credit <hi>of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecarie's Shop you went to once a day, kept by a Relation of your Landlord, where you were taught the Trade of an Apothecary,</hi> as in your <hi>Caſus, <hi>p.</hi>
                     </hi> 141. I am glad, it was not in <hi>England,</hi> and I hope it is not our Apothecaries trade, to play ſuch wicked Pranks. But <hi>the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Apothecary</hi> is of ſingular uſe <hi>to correct, alter, and ſubſtitute what he pleaſes.</hi> Many of our Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſing Apothecaries are ſo buſie in
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:49471:101"/>viſiting their ſmall Patients, or elſe are grown ſo lazy and high, that oftentimes <hi>not one Bill in twenty</hi> is made up by the Maſter Apotheca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but that piece of drudgery is left to the ſhatter-brain Boy or Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentice. And has the Boy ſuch wonderful <hi>Experience,</hi> that he may <hi>alter, and ſubſtitute what he pleaſes?</hi> Sure <hi>the Doctor's Preſcriptions are not ſo idle and incongruous. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> you make as <hi>mad work</hi> with the Apothecaries, as you have done with the Phyſicians, but we ſhall both pardon the random flights of a hot-headed <hi>Pair-brain.</hi> You ought to be ſent to the Doctor of <hi>Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam,</hi> to take ſome Doſes of <hi>Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore.</hi> Though your <hi>idle and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous</hi> ſcribling will never hurt one jot, either the Apothecaries Trade, or the Phyſicians Practice. But <hi>grant the Doctor preſcribes a Cordial Julep, the other prepares it with the addition of a few grains of Reſin of</hi> Gialap, <hi>or</hi> Scammony <hi>without the
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:49471:101"/>leaſt hazard of Diſcovery.</hi> I will for once <hi>ſupponere non ſupponenda,</hi> grant your ridiculous Whimſies, and, I hope, groundleſs Imaginations, <hi>the Reſin of Jalap or Scammony</hi> will certainly make ſuch <hi>mad-work in the ſick man's Guts,</hi> that there will not only be the greateſt <hi>hazard of diſcovery</hi> imaginable, but the plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evidence in the World, as plain and ſenſible <hi>as the <hi>Roſe</hi> in your face,</hi> againſt the Apothecary who dared to make ſuch <hi>mad work</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a <hi>Cordial.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Though from theſe Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I could deſume Matter enough to expatiate into a large Volume (by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riving thence the various kinds of continual and intermittent Fevors) I judge it at preſent unneceſſary, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the further ſearch to thoſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant lazy Drones that are called <hi>Conciave-Phyſicians.</hi>
                     </hi> p. 102.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>We are too well ſatisfied of your abilities that way; we grant that you have a Talent that
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:49471:102"/>can <hi>expatiate,</hi> if you have a mind to't, <hi>into a large Volume</hi> (larger than any <hi>Nick Culpepper</hi> ever writ) as by woful Experience we too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten find, that the weakeſt man in the Company can <hi>expatiate</hi> in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and talk more than all the reſt together. But by no means do not exerciſe your Talent to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extent;
<q>
                        <l>— <hi>It will be no</hi> great ſin,</l>
                        <l>To hide that Talent in a Napkin.</l>
                     </q> as a late Ninny has it. <hi>Leave the further ſearch</hi> of thoſe matters to wiſer heads, and they will take it ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry kindly of you. But pray what are thoſe pretious <hi>Notions,</hi> that you could wire-draw to ſuch a frightful length? They are <hi>Fevors, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Distempers explained</hi> (that's well) <hi>and cured</hi> (that's better) <hi>by New Principles.</hi> p. 93. This <hi>New Principle,</hi> as old as it is, taking in your explanation, is New News to us, and no leſs than <hi>the Circulation of the Blood,</hi> which <hi>as it was the
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:49471:102"/>moſt eaſy</hi> thing in the World <hi>to be found out, ſo might the manner and ways of it, which notwithſtanding hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto have lain aſleep, though this could ſcarce have happened, unleſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong ſuch, as are greater Block heads than common Seamen.</hi> p. 98. Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians then have been to blame for explaining <hi>the Circulation</hi> by <hi>Anaſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſes, or Inoſculation of</hi> the Capilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Arteries</hi> into the <hi>Veins,</hi> and then afterwards for <hi>taking their refuge to the Pores,</hi> and <hi>explaining the Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <hi>per taecos meatus,</hi>
                     </hi> and <hi>qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litates occultas,</hi> their old <hi>aſylus ignorantiae.</hi> p. 99. I would there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ask you, becauſe you are ſuch a knowing man, and given to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries, which way, or by what <hi>ductus</hi> the pond of Water that ſtagnates in the <hi>Abdomen</hi> of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dropical Perſons does come to be evacuated in ſuch quantities by Stoole, upon the taking a ſtrong Hydragogue. Tell me that frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and plainly, without refuge to
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:49471:103"/>
                     <hi>aſylum ignorantiae,</hi> and you will winn my Love and Admiration too. <hi>Eris mihi Magnus Apollo,</hi> both in Latin and Engliſh, both in hard words, which you love dearly, and in plain and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per terms, which I love as well. <hi>How</hi> things come to paſs, is often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times as puzling to be in Divinity. <hi>How</hi> is found to be in Divinity. We <hi>ſee</hi> Light and Colours, abut notwithſtanding all you have ſaid about them in your early days, or in your <hi>Natural Philoſophy,</hi> yet I muſt needs confeſs we are ſtill too much in the Dark, and are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſatisfied in the matter, though indeed one would think a man might ſafely enough <hi>believe his own eyes.</hi> Again, <hi>in tempore vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vimus, &amp; quid tempus ſit ignora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus: in loco ſumus, &amp; quid Locus ſit ignoramus.</hi> We know the <hi>Wind</hi> blows from every Quarter, and the <hi>Maggot</hi> bites from every corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of your head, but why the
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:49471:103"/>Eaſtern Wind to all Countries is the moſt unwholſome, why are South Wind is ſo moiſt, and the North ſo cold, is beyond ev'ry man's skill to determine; as it is why you ſhould declare your ſelf ſo bitter and implacable an Enemy to <hi>all Societies of Phyſicians,</hi> and in them not only to thoſe with whom you have contended face to face, as it has been your practice to do in the <hi>Conſult-room,</hi> but even to thoſe who never <hi>offended</hi> you, and whom you <hi>never ſaw,</hi> nor perhaps <hi>ever heard of.</hi> Is it Manners, or at all agreeable to the <hi>Rules of Civility</hi> you might have learnt in <hi>France,</hi> when you were <hi>making the petit tour, went to l' Hoſtel Dieu,</hi> or <hi>aſſiſted Monſieur</hi> Jannot <hi>at the greater Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations in Surgery at the Charitè-Hoſpital;</hi> it is Manners, I ſay, or agreeable to your French Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, thus to call Phyſicians in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, <hi>ignorant and lazy Drones, great Blockheads and Ideots</hi> in the ſame
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:49471:104"/>Chapter? Will you needs prefer the Invention of Common Seamen before that of the beſt Phyſicians, in the buſineſs of <hi>the Circulation?</hi> Is the Great Inventor of the Circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation <hi>of Immortal Memory,</hi> who made <hi>Britain Divine,</hi> thus to be dwindled from a Gyant into a Dwarf? Is the Learned Doctor <hi>Harvey</hi> to be degraded below the <hi>invention of Common Seamen?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Not to detain you longer with theſe impertinencies.</hi> p. 100. <hi>I know your Curioſity will demand, what Remedies they are, that are virtuated with a power to effect ſo great a Work,</hi> to wit, the Infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Cure of Fevers. <hi>I anſwer, that the <hi>Materia Medica,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out they are to be prepared; you ſee one ſort every day, if you look but a little beyond your Noſe</hi> (that's plain enough) <hi>you need not grub for it in the depth; another you tread upon,</hi> that's pity; <hi>any a third is as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon in your mouth</hi> (whether you
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:49471:104"/>be Rich or Poor, Sick or Well) <hi>as the Bread you eat: what they are further, I ſhall never diſcover pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly</hi> (not for a World) <hi>nor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their Preparation to any Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cary;</hi> you muſt come to me in private, and bring Faith along with you, as well as Money, <hi>for it's not fit ſuch Medicines ſhould be abuſed,</hi> or ſlighted as Dirt, <hi>by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Conclave Phyſician.</hi> p. 108, 109.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I ſhall never be ſuch a Curious Coxcomb, as to be inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive after you idle <hi>Impertinencies.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed your ought not to be ſo Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal of your little ſtock of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. They ought to be kept very charily and warm, as a Snake in your boſome, or a little weakly Babe that comes at the beginning of the ſeventh Month. You need not talk of what we <hi>ev'ry day ſee,</hi> or <hi>tread upon,</hi> or <hi>eat.</hi> If you had happen'd to read <hi>Martinus Rulan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> his <hi>Pharmacopoea Nova, de Ster<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coribus &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rinis,</hi> you would have
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:49471:105"/>found, that there is exceeding great <hi>virtue</hi> and <hi>power</hi> in a <hi>Stercus;</hi> and that a man may have reaſon to expect greater effects from a wholſome <hi>Stercus,</hi> and without Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical Preparation, in its plain <hi>puris naturalibus,</hi> than from any of your <hi>Remedies,</hi> prepared according to Art, of which you crack and bounce, <hi>without fear or wit.</hi> The <hi>Publick,</hi> I dare engage, will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have reaſon to lament the want of <hi>your Diſcoveries.</hi> We know that you have been very profuſe and laviſh, like a common Proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, of <hi>All</hi> you have, and in your little trifling <hi>Tracts</hi> have told us all that you know, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly more than you can juſtify; and becauſe you find that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberal vent of Trifles inſtead of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies does turn to a ſmall account, do you now think to Cajole the World with telling them, what rare things you have ſtill in ſtore? <hi>Bonum quò melius, eò magis communicabile.</hi>
                     <pb n="205" facs="tcp:49471:105"/>One Modeſt and Ingenious Man, who is more ready to learn of others, than to teach crude and jejune Notions, ſhall <hi>Diſcover</hi> better Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, and more Excellent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies in a ſingle ſheet, than a thouſand ſuch as you with all your noiſe and clamour, with your ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant Pretences, and vain Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, can for your life (do the beſt you can) in a <hi>Volume larger than the Septuagints.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The truth hereof appears, by the Remedies I have uſed on ſuch occaſions, which in half an hours time have reduced the Patients to their right reaſon</hi> (out of a <hi>Deliri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um) by no other manner of operating, than by cauſing a free Circulation in the Brain.</hi> p. 109.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſo I have known a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Stercus</hi> (I can aſſure you) to do wonders in the like caſe; and if it does not operate ſo well <hi>in the firſt half hour,</hi> yet it has not failed in a few <hi>half hours</hi> to <hi>reduce the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:49471:106"/>to their right reaſon.</hi> You ſee, I am not ſhy of Diſcovering ſo precious a treaſure, for the good of the World; and I would not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recommend it to your Particular Uſe, but you deſerve to be forced to take liberally of it, and to make it your daily food, as well as Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, until your notorious <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium</hi> goes off, and you be at laſt <hi>reduced to your Right Reaſon,</hi> and to better Manners than you have yet learnt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>I have no manner of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience thus to hear not only my Incomparable Remedies ſo vilely abuſed, but the gravity of my Perſon ſo ſhamefully ridicul'd, my Anatomico-Philoſophical Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries thus contemned, and my Books I have written to be ſo horribly miſrepreſented with that which galls me more than any thing elſe, I mean, with plain and undeniable <hi>Truths.</hi> I hated <hi>all Phyſicians</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently before, but now I am
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:49471:106"/>thus provoked, <hi>I hate all the World,</hi> Man, Woman and Child, and if I were a <hi>Conjurer</hi> (as God knows I am not) and ſo had Skill in the Black-Art, I would raiſe ſuch a Tempeſt, and univerſal Hurricane, as ſhould confound them all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and bury me and my Books, with the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to them, in one <hi>Knock</hi> to a <hi>Chaos.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Fy, <hi>Momus,</hi> fy! Such an extravagant paſſion does not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a man of <hi>your Education.</hi> Remember what you once taught us in your <hi>Natural Theology: When a man is incenſed; they ſay he is as full of hatred or venom as a Serpent, or when he is inflamed with anger, they reſemble him to the Devil, in ſaying he is as angry as the Devil,</hi> Nat. Theol. <hi>p.</hi> 111. Again, <hi>the greateſt advantage which the Devil ever takes of men, is in their Paſſions. How many are there that hang and murther themſelves in Wrath, Love,</hi> (this, they ſay, does ſeldom happen now-a-days)
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:49471:107"/>
                     <hi>Sadneſs, &amp;c.</hi> Ibid. Once more, <hi>a Paſſionate man is by wiſe men</hi> (by <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf often) <hi>accounted a Fool, for it was one of the Tenents of the</hi> Stoicks, <hi>That no wiſe man was Paſſionate.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Would you have a man burſt with Rage and Vexation, and not to expreſs mind a little? Are not Women and Children allowed ſometimes to cry and roar, when they are croſs'd and anger'd? And do they not ſay they find eaſe by ſhedding of Tears? Would you have me burn to a <hi>Cinder,</hi> with the Fire and Flame within me, and ſuffer no Water, or Tears, to quench the devouring Flame?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, one <hi>Tear</hi> from your haughty evil Eyes, one deep <hi>ſigh</hi> from your hard, and unrelenting Heart, one good <hi>Reccavi</hi> from your foul, and moſt abuſive <hi>Pen,</hi> would give us ſome hopes of your Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, for one of the greateſt ſins that can be committed, an habitual
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:49471:107"/>courſe of Calumny and Detracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I remember your tell us that <hi>A Paſſion ſeldom ſeizes on a man, but it leaveth a Cinder, ſo that it eaſily blazes again,</hi> Nat. Theol. <hi>ibid.</hi> p. 111. And withal, that <hi>there is no Paſſion but what is full of Pain,</hi> ibid. p. 112. Therefore have a care of the <hi>Cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and conſider that you fill your ſelf full of pain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you then think that I can cry, whine, or relent? I am too <hi>old</hi> to alter my Natural Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Thoſe ſimple Fancies I writ in my younger days, when I was raw and unexperienced in the World, when I hardly knew what I did, and when <hi>I only ſaid what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men ſaid before me.</hi> But now I am a man of Might and Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. There is no Phyſician upon the Earth, but I ſcorn to truckle to him. And I am not now to learn of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> or <hi>Galen. Then Phyſicians do probably wiſh all the World ſick at once,</hi> 11.
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:49471:108"/>Part <hi>p.</hi> 58. And to conclude all in one word, <hi>There is no trust to be put in</hi> Religio Medici, <hi>many of whom, I verily dare affirm, believe, there is neither God, Heaven, Devil nor Hell,</hi> p. 69.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O tempora, ô mores!</hi> Oh dreadful and abominable! Is it ſo verily? Is it ſo <hi>probable</hi> that <hi>the Phyſicians do wiſh all the World ſick at once?</hi> Do they wiſh Friends and Foes, Rich and Poor, Nurſes and Apothecaries, all to be down toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther? Would they ſpare none to call them to their Patients, to open the door to them, or to give them their Fee? Would they be content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for one ſhort term of a Hurry of buſineſs <hi>to go with their hands in their pockets</hi> all the reſt of the year? According to your way of reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they are moſt wretchedly ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and know their own Intereſt but little. But to your <hi>Concluſion</hi> which is ſo black and diſmal, that I hardly know how to meddle with
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:49471:108"/>it. You ſpeak for <hi>your ſelf,</hi> I hope, in the firſt place. And in good truth you write at ſuch a Mad and Frightful rate, that a man may juſtly conclude, you <hi>not having the fear of God before your Eyes,</hi> but unwitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>moved and ſeduced by the inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Devil,</hi> did <hi>dare to affirm</hi> ſuch horrible things of your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; Brethren, I ſay, in Title or Profeſſion, but by no means <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> with you in <hi>iniquity.</hi> You do not do well to let that ſame <hi>Religio Medici</hi> run ſo mightily in your head. There is more Senſe, and Religion too in a Paragraph of that Book, than in all your fantaſtical, raw, and yet borrowed conceits of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Theology,</hi> your own Natural Mother (to whom you dedicated that precious piece of Divinity) being Judge. <hi>Religio Medici</hi> is a ſerious thing, conſiſting of very Uncommon Notions, and ſuch as every paltry Pretender is not a competent Judge of. The <hi>Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
                     <pb n="212" facs="tcp:49471:109"/>have the ſame unhappy Fate, as moſt other <hi>Wiſe</hi> men have, when they talk frankly of Religious Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, <hi>to be eaſily and exceedingly mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken.</hi> The <hi>things above us</hi> are ſeen at a great diſtance even by the Divines, and the Phyſicians, or Natural Philoſophers, do bring them good part of the way to the <hi>Coelum Empyreum.</hi> If therefore the ſagacious <hi>Naturaliſt</hi> does ſometimes without reſerve diſcourſe of things far above their, and every man's apprehenſion, muſt he preſently be cenſured by ignorant or malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Coxcombs, for <hi>Religio Medici,</hi> or for little or <hi>Ro Religion;</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he never ſo ſtrictly obſerves the main duties of True Religion, I mean, <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Charity, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> and <hi>Honeſty,</hi> rather than put his Truſt in things of far leſs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but more Popular in the Eyes of the World, I mean, <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Performances. You verily dare affirm,</hi> as extravagant things, as
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:49471:109"/>much plain Nonſenſe, as ridiculous and improbable Stories, as many palpable Untruths, and even flat Contradictions, as perhaps any man that ever pretended to be an <hi>Author.</hi> But <hi>verily</hi> I never had patience to read to much of other inſignificant Scriblers, being quickly cloyed with one leaf or two of the Pamphlet, where I was drawn in by the uſual decoy, the tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing promiſes of a <hi>Title-leaf.</hi> But <hi>pour Game, <hi>Momus,</hi>
                     </hi> and your big <hi>Titles,</hi> did promiſe more than was every where to be met with. And the <hi>Subject</hi> was <hi>extraordinary;</hi> it made ſome noiſe too before it came out, and we had mighty expectation of the <hi>Birth</hi> of no leſs than a <hi>Mountain,</hi> and after all, we find not a ridiculous <hi>Mouſe,</hi> but a <hi>Worm,</hi> or a <hi>Maggot</hi> brought forth. To conclude, <hi>I verily dare affirm,</hi> that reckoning the whole number of Legal Phyſicians of the College, you ſhall hardly find in any other
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:49471:110"/>Profeſſion (the <hi>Divines</hi> only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) or in any other Society, Trade, or Title, (unleſs you pick and chooſe) ſo many Good men, and Good Chriſtians (number for number) as among the Phyſicians, to whom you are ſo grievouſly and unreaſonably <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>You have the beſt opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Phyſicians that ever I knew, and am apt to think men will judge you t have as much too good an opinion of them, as you would perſwade, that I have too little. Are you your ſelf ſo well careſs'd, and courted among them, that in return you complement them at this high rate? Or, have you not ſome latent ſelf-intereſt you aim at? For certainly you could never dare thus to enter the Liſts with <hi>Me</hi> for nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>I know the Phyſicians Faults, as well as their Virtues, and would neither have the one magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in your Microſcope, nor the
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:49471:110"/>other leſſened by the weakneſs of my Praiſes. They are <hi>Men</hi> (though they have been ſometimes in a manner <hi>deified,</hi> even whilſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live) as well as other people; and therefore it is no ſuch marvel if the <hi>Art of Phyſick</hi> may have ſome that are no better than they ſhould be, as well as the <hi>Law,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> There is no doubt but there is miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>management of Affairs among them, or elſe you would never have <hi>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to affirm</hi> ſuch groſs things of them all in general. Your Horns would elſe have been pull'd in long ago, and you would have been contented to confine your roving head within the circumference of your Shell. Time was, when they knew how to manage their own Power to better purpoſe, and to curb the intolerable inſolences of Prating Quacks, and Impudent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piricks, after another-gueſs rate than they now do. And time will come, I hope, before you are a
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:49471:111"/>little older, that they will know their own ſtrength again, and not tamely ſuffer any foul-mouth'd Wretch thus to beſpatter and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſie Admirable men, the Glory of the Age they live in, with ſuch a licentious freedom, an unlimited and full cry of <hi>Billingſgate</hi> dialect, <hi>as if you neither feared</hi> God, <hi>nor</hi> Heaven, <hi>Devil,</hi> nor <hi>Hell.</hi> As for Careſſes and Endearments, they ſeldom happen to any great degree, among the ſame Members of any Profeſſion, and eſpecially here in <hi>England;</hi> and it is commonly ſaid, <hi>Men of the ſame Trade do ſeldom</hi> ſo far <hi>agree.</hi> I have no reaſon to <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain,</hi> for want of their reciprocal Civility. But for any <hi>ſelf-intereſt</hi> in what I have now done towards the ſerving them according to my ſmall Capacity, I have not the leaſt <hi>Aim</hi> of that kind And to convince you the more that I have no ſuch Aim, I ſhall take ſome care to keep my ſelf <hi>Incognito,</hi> leaving to you
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:49471:111"/>the ſuppoſed pleaſure of <hi>quàm pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum</hi> (or rather for you <hi>quàm foedum</hi>) <hi>eſt monſtrari, &amp; dicier Hic eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay, do your beſt to hide or conceal your ſelf, I ſhall find you out in time. And if I do, by <hi>Heavens</hi> and all that's Good, by <hi>Hobgoblings</hi> and <hi>Bugbears,</hi> and all that's Evil, by my <hi>Mother-Wit,</hi> and by <hi>both my Degrees,</hi> I will ranſack every paſſage of your Life, I will rummage every corner you have haunted, I will dreſs you in ſuch an Antick and Ridiculous Habit, and make you ſo hideous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed a Creature, that you had better <hi>be half-hang'd,</hi> or even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo <hi>my Herculaean,</hi> or <hi>Gigantean Cure of the Pox,</hi> than ever have preſumed thus to contend with me, and hazard a tryal of Skill with the ſharpeſt <hi>Caſe-maker</hi> in Town.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Threats are like Chaff before the Wind. By thus ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:49471:112"/>you do but intangle your ſelf the more. And pray do not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade your ſelf, that no body could have <hi>anſwered you according to your Folly</hi> before now, or that no body had the Courage to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake it. You are infinitely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the conſideration, or Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion of the <hi>more Curious Pens</hi> in our <hi>Society.</hi> I have foreborn with abundance of Patience all this while, giving way to others (who could do it much better) to undertake this Phyſick-quarrel with you. But fearing leſt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued ſilence might make you ſtill <hi>wiſer in your own conceit,</hi> I have for your good and Amendment made this <hi>gentle Rod</hi> for you, a <hi>Rod</hi> more gentle than your <hi>gentle Pox,</hi> and a <hi>Rod,</hi> you ſee, that will break no Bones, but only ſmart; and I have ſerved you ſomewhat as the Learned Doctor <hi>Gill</hi> did the ſaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy <hi>Tom Triplett,</hi> hoiſted you up, and ſcourged you a little, but more
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:49471:112"/>
                     <hi>gently</hi> than you have deſerved, for making ſuch a noiſe, and thus rudely and Clowniſhly entering into <hi>the Conclave of Phyſicians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I verily dare affirm,</hi> that you have done the worſt you can, and believe, you cannot write ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Dialogue</hi> upon this Subject, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you have ſaid <hi>ſo much</hi> in this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure you, that have been ſo tireſome a Scriber, who have ſo often diſtracted the Studies of Young men, from uſeful Authors, to hear <hi>Cerberus</hi> bark, or ſpit fire at the Faculty of Phyſick, do not at laſt think it ſuch a mighty buſineſs to write a little Book. Do you not ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that Grocers Shops, and Paſtry-Cooks are very plentifully ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Printed Traſh, which they do put to a much better uſe, than the Authors, or <hi>Pen and Ink-ſpoilers</hi> could do before. Have you never been ſaluted in the ſtreets by poor pedling Hawkers with, <hi>Maſter, won't
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:49471:113"/>you pleaſe to be ſo kind to buy a Book? You will do a poor body a deed of Charity.</hi> And after all, in ſo liceu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious an Age of Printing, do you now doub, that I can't write a <hi>Second Dialogue</hi> between a conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſilly <hi>Momus,</hi> and a man of ſome Senſe, when the Subject is inexhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtible? Be contented, and take this Chaſtiſement quietly, and without muttering, or elſe you ſhall find <hi>worſe Rods in piſs</hi> prepared for you. <hi>Multum poſt terga relictum eſt, ante oculos plus eſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>You are unreaſonably <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced</hi> againſt this Author, or elſe you could never be ſo violent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis very right. I am ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding <hi>prejudiced</hi> againſt this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Author, who, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he had ſuch ſtrange and wonderful advantages of a Liberal Education, that the like was hardly ever known, if we may take his word for it; who notwithſtanding
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:49471:113"/>than he had a Phyſical <hi>Cap of Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance</hi> clapt upon his head, by way of Complement Extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and a fair and fine <hi>Diploma</hi> put into his hand, at <hi>ſeventeen,</hi> yet that he ſhould turn the Badge of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour into a <hi>Fool's-Cap,</hi> and that the Hand which was once ſolemnly laid upon <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his Works, ſhould dip his Pens in the Gall of an Aſs, inſtead of downright Ink, in order to expoſe to the ſcorn of the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant <hi>Mobile,</hi> and miſchievouſly to leſſen the <hi>Faculty</hi> he was ſo much beholding to: How can I chooſe but be <hi>prejudiced</hi> againſt ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and errant a <hi>Mad-cap? Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> you have more reaſon too than you are aware to be <hi>prejudiced</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this man. He has been no great Friend to you once upon a time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>No! What has he done? Tell me. I hope, he has not been guilty of ſpeaking well of others, eſpecially his Superiors, more than
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:49471:114"/>
                     <hi>once</hi> in his life. I hope he has not kept Peace in his Family, defended the Innocent, or been ſhie in ſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Faults.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>No. None of thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. But he has abuſed and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul'd even <hi>Momus</hi> himſelf the moſt groſly, and unpardonably that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was known.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherein?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, at the end of that ſame Preface to his <hi>Archaeologia</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, he adjoins ſix Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to <hi>Momus,</hi> ſo Poetaſtick or fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtick, ſo wretchedly ſimple and Nonſenſical, that you would won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to hear them. they do hobble upon all ſix at ſuch a frightful and ſhameful rate, and the third is ſo lame of moſt of his Feet, that I think it has got a <hi>Gangrene,</hi> for it has no manner of <hi>Senſe</hi> in it, though I have tried all the ways imaginable to put any little life into it, rather than none at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Let's hear what they are.
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:49471:114"/>Sure my Friend could not ſo far forget himſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Open both your Ears, or both your Eyes then; and keep your Mouth wide open, that if you ſhould <hi>cast,</hi> you may be ready:</p>
                  <lg>
                     <head>
                        <hi>To</hi> Momus.</head>
                     <l>Thou croſs-grain'd <hi>Mome,</hi> 'tis time forbear to ſquint,</l>
                     <l>If not, I'll coyn and caſt thee in the Mint.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Bodel</hi> be ſtamp a Dog gnorring at a Bone,</l>
                     <l>More ſtupid, more dull than any dunghil Stone;</l>
                     <l>If now thou ſhouldſt grow civil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what I can</l>
                     <l>Hope, then thou art no more a Beaſt, but a True Man.</l>
                  </lg>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thou croſs-grain'd Mome!</hi> He might have <hi>Thou'd</hi> me a little more Civilly than ſo. I can eaſily paſs by <hi>Squint, Bodel</hi> (or <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi>) <hi>gnorring Dog, dull and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid, dunghill ſtone,</hi> and his calling me <hi>Beaſt;</hi> I could paſs by <hi>this</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rybdis
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:49471:115"/>
                     <hi>of a carping</hi> Momus, <hi>or that</hi> Scylla <hi>of a livid</hi> Zoilus, as a notable expreſſion, and a ſign of his Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in the foreſaid Preface; but to leſſen me into a diminutive Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſyllable, like <hi>Bob, Dick,</hi> and <hi>Tom,</hi> is a thing I do not allow, and cannot but take unkindly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>To be ſhort, what think you of thoſe <hi>ſix Verſes?</hi> are they not beyond compare?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed they are the worſt that ever were made to me. And the worſe becauſe they come from the Pen of a <hi>Philoſopher.</hi> I would not adviſe him to meddle with <hi>Rhime-doggrel</hi> any more. But this is to be ſaid for him. It was in his <hi>younger.</hi> Years, when his head did rove upon Greater Matters, upon <hi>Philoſophico-Ontologico-Dyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milogico-Theologico-Macrocoſmical and Microcoſmical Principles.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>Thoſe were not doubt great and weighty matters, which wanted to be uſhered in ſtate with
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:49471:115"/>ſix ſuch ſpecial Attendants. To my ſeeming, they are more inſipid Poetry, than thoſe on that wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Aſtrological Poetaſter, <hi>Sof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold's Beſt Pills; <hi>Read, Try, Iudge,</hi> and ſpeak as you find.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The Head, Stomach, Belly, and the Reins they</l>
                     <l>Will cleanſe and Cure while you may work or play.</l>
                     <l>His Pills have often to the makers praiſe</l>
                     <l>Cur'd in all Weathers, aye in the Dog-days.</l>
                     <l>In ſhort, no Purging Medicine's made, that can</l>
                     <l>Cure more Diſeaſes in Woman or Man, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>The very ſame thing in <hi>Verſe,</hi> that you ſo ſtifly maintain'd in <hi>Proſe,</hi> concerning <hi>your Remedies,</hi> that you have made us Deſpair to know, becauſe <hi>you never will Diſcover them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mom.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My Remedies!</hi> I ſcorn them. I would have you to know,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:49471:116"/>that I can make better <hi>Remedies,</hi> than his, when I make <hi>Water;</hi> and I can make better Verſes in my Sleep, than he can waking in his moſt Poetical muſement. If he had ſhewed <hi>Wit</hi> (as well as Malice) in his <hi>Tracts,</hi> I would have ſtood by him, like a Friend. The <hi>very reading</hi> of them <hi>has made</hi> me Dull and Sleepy. <hi>Philiater, Leon Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theram Remunerâſti,</hi> you have <hi>given him a</hi> Rowland <hi>for his</hi> Oliver.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Momus,</hi> we know that you can <hi>verba dare;</hi> you ſlip a Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that might have been ſpar'd. Your precious Friend may e'en curſe his ill Fate, which gave him an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable <hi>Knock in his Cradle.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>The Reader is deſired to Correct the following Miſtakes.</p>
            <p>PAge 18. line 25. for <hi>blacker</hi> read <hi>blackeſt.</hi> p. 47. l. 3. r. <hi>anatomia.</hi> p. 59. l. 2. for <hi>Tittle</hi> r. <hi>Title.</hi> p. 120. l. 10. inſtead of <hi>you are not for libera.</hi> r. <hi>you ſay libera.</hi> p. 134. laſt line, for <hi>Caſes</hi> 1. <hi>Caſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <gap reason="intruder" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page inserted from a different book〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
